<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0017">Due to isolation, prevention of epidemic, and control requirements, interviews were conducted by telephone, WeChat voice, or face-to-face. Prior to the interview, the doctor and nurse in charge of the patient were contacted to ascertain any changes in the patient's condition. If the condition of the patient was deemed stable and suitable for interview, it was conducted via WeChat or telephone at an appointed timeslot, typically in the afternoon when diagnosis and treatment activity was reduced. To establish a relationship between the consultant and visitors and to improve data collection, all subjects were initially interviewed face-to-face. The study was performed in a negative pressure ward by nurses working in the infectious disease department trained in qualitative interviewing. During diagnosis and treatment and where time allowed, a recorded face-to-face interview with each patient was conducted for at least 20 minutes. During the interview, nurses were protected by wearing isolation garments, gloves, masks, goggles, and face screens, in accordance with the disinfection and isolation procedures of the COVID-19 infection ward. Telephone interviews were performed in the clean area of the office of the infectious diseases department to ensure privacy and without the presence of a third party. Patients were contacted by telephone or WeChat. Interviews were performed using a hands-free device and recorded. Each interview lasted for 20-60 min, depending on the condition of the patient. If the patient felt unwell or was unwilling to continue the interview, the interview was terminated immediately. As a supplement to the interview, WeChat was used to communicate and interact with the patients for data analysis. The final analysis was returned to the research subjects for verification. To avoid secondary psychological harm caused by the interview, psychological interventions were performed to deal with any psychological distress. Due to the need for dynamic observations based on the theory of timing (
 <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Cameron and Gignac, 2008</xref>), the hospitalization period was divided into three stages: (1) Early stage: from admission to the infectious diseases department to the first positive nucleic acid test period; (2) Late stage: from the first negative viral nucleic acid test to discharge from hospital; (3) Middle stage: the hospitalization interval between the early and late stages. Depending on circumstances, 1-2 interviews were conducted during each period. Interviews generally took place within 24 hours of admission, receiving positive nucleic acid test reports, receiving a negative nucleic acid test report and receiving a discharge notice. The arrangements for interviews were determined according to the patient's condition and willingness. The numbers and intervals of interviews are presented in 
 <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> . For critically ill patients, interviews were performed upon stabilization of their condition. All data were strictly confidential.
</p>
