<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The HIV epidemic in the US is currently marked by significant disparities among racial/ethnic, gender, and sexual minorities. Out of the over 38,000 new HIV infections in 2017, 70% were among gay and bisexual men [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In 2018, African Americans made up 42% of new HIV infections while only comprising 13% of the population, and HIV infections increased among Latinos in all 50 states from 2010 to 2016 [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. People living with HIV who lie at the intersection of these identities see the most glaring disparities. Among all MSM, Black MSM account for 37% of new HIV diagnoses, with growing concentration in the South, and fare worse at each step along the HIV care continuum (e.g., linkage, retention, and viral suppression) compared to their White counterparts [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Half of Black MSM are projected to acquire HIV in their lifetime [
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Nearly half of all Black transgender women and a quarter of all Latina transgender women are estimated to be living with HIV [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Given that iART may quickly medicalize the post-diagnosis experience for some patients, potentially in advance of emotional processing, it is critical to understand iART’s impact in these communities to avoid the potential of emerging HIV-related health disparities. Consider, for example, that many well-intentioned major advancements in HIV prevention, care, and treatment (e.g., pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP), widespread testing, advances in antiretroviral treatment) have not improved racial disparities in HIV care outcomes. While improving time to viral suppression, iART has the potential to further racial disparities if not implemented with a deep understanding of how Black people living with HIV understand and perceive the iART intervention.
</p>
