<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Unknown origin pneumonia has been furiously spreading since the late of December 2019, which has been epidemiologically and etiologically investigated by the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention immediately.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
  <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]
 </sup> Subsequently, a novel coronavirus, as the pathogen, was identified,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]
 </sup> which was termed as 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) by the WHO. Currently, the virus boasts a new nomenclature: severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-COV-2), and the disease triggered by it is entitled 2019 Corona Virus Disease-19 (COVID-19); those infected patients mostly involved their lungs, the National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China, therefore, named pneumonia induced by the virus as novel coronavirus pneumonia (NCP), and listed COVID-19 as a Class B infectious disease specified in the Law of the People's Republic of China on the Prevention and Treatment of Infectious Diseases, indicting the prevention and control measures for Class A infectious diseases should be taken. By 18:00 on April 9, 2020, a total of 83,264 confirmed cases and 3344 cumulative deaths have been reported nationwide. Additionally, confirmed patients had been reported in several countries, most involving those people living or visiting Wuhan; and the virus has been well-established that person-to-person transmission is a truth.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
  <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
  <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
  <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]
 </sup> This article summarizes the relevant etiology, epidemiology, clinical manifestations, imaging findings, and medication on COVID-19 and analyzes and reviews the etiology, epidemiology, clinical manifestations, image findings, and medication of COVID-19 to help comprehensively understand and correctly cope with COVID-19.
</p>
