<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) has periodically emerged as epidemics and its natural history could be utilized as a “compass” to comprehend and manage the current pandemic of SARS-COV-2. SARS-COV-2 the etiologic agent of the novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), belongs to RNA coronavirus family (
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic>) and is a zoonotic coronavirus that has crossed species barriers to infect human (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The initially investigated strains of COVID-19 exhibited low potential for transmissibility and infectivity, similar to SARS coronavirus (SARS-COV) (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Moreover, SARS epidemic was potentiated due to super spread events (SSEs), which led to unexpected elevation of the basic reproduction numbers as calculated via associated epidemiology equations (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Specifically, SSEs resulted from secondary contacts of carriers (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Infected individuals, as mediators of SSEs, represent the initial cluster of viral transmission (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>); thus, inducing an exponential secondary contamination (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Although the prediction and subsequently the prevention of SSEs seems to be complicated, the virus, host, environmental, and mass behaviors determine relative approaches to prevent and control SSEs; core community health programs can inhibit and decrease the incidence and the effect of SSEs (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Nevertheless, horizontal austerity measures, such as recommending or compelling individuals to self-isolate at home, which might cause serious social and psychological burden, and quarantine, also leading to loss of income due to social distancing, are associated with negative psychological and religious effects, which can be long lasting (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), thereby leading to serious instability of the global society. Prolonged social isolation and loneliness are associated with increased mortality (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). 
</p>
