<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">During the epidemic period, China has imposed a series of multifaceted public health measures to practice social distancing, so as to control the rapid dispersion of the virus. The implementation of stringent quarantines has improved the control of the COVID-19 outbreak in China, reducing the number of incident COVID-19 cases (
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2020</xref>). Moreover, our results indicated that large quarantine in China contributed to a significant decline in concentration of air pollutants except O
 <sub>3</sub>. Starting from Jan. 23rd, the cities gradually entered level 1 of emergency response, carrying out epidemic prevention as well as control measures, including traffic restriction, community containment, personal protection, etc. Compared to the same hibernal period in 2019 (from Dec. 2018 to Apr. 2019), the ambient air pollutants’ concentrations reduced 9.31% for PM
 <sub>2.5</sub>, 14.49% for SO
 <sub>2</sub>, 11.54% for NO
 <sub>2</sub>, and 13.89% for CO respectively. However, the concentrations of the PM
 <sub>10</sub> and O
 <sub>3</sub> enriched 0.57% and 6.90% (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mee.gov.cn/" id="intref0025" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.mee.gov.cn/</ext-link>). During the quarantine period, the number of people and vehicles in public places were reduced, most industrial enterprises, construction site, entertainment and catering company were shut down, according to the compulsory measures. As a possible side effect of lockdown, many regions experienced an unprecedented reduction in ambient air pollution. A latest study illustrated that the traffic restriction taken in 44 cities in northern China in COVID-19 pandemic period reduced air pollution emissions significantly, with a 7.80% decrease of AQI (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bao and Zhang, 2020</xref>), close to the our results of a 12.7% decrease of AQI. Another study investigated the impact of reduced human activity on air quality over the Yangtze River Delta Region, finding that during the most stringent Level I response period, primary pollutants like SO
 <sub>2</sub>, NOx, PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and VOCs have been reduced by 26%, 47%, 46% and 57% (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>). Besides, due to the stringent lockdown measures, the O
 <sub>3</sub> concentration increased by 32.9%. The increase of O
 <sub>3</sub> attributed to the strong reduction in NO
 <sub>x</sub> emissions by transport, which caused a lower titration of O
 <sub>3</sub> (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Sicard et al., 2020</xref>). Chen et al. compared the changes in PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and NO
 <sub>2</sub> in 2020 versus 2016–2019 during quarantine period, with those changes in the before quarantine period, suggesting that improved air quality avoided NO
 <sub>2</sub>-related and PM
 <sub>2.5</sub>-related deaths due to lockdown (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
