<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0150">In the analyses of PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and PM
 <sub>10</sub>, we observed a 7% and 6% increase in COVID-19 morbidity per IQR increase in PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and PM
 <sub>10</sub> concentration respectively, with a lag of 15 days. Recent studies have also found positive associations of PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and PM
 <sub>10</sub> with the transmission dynamics of COVID-19 in China (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>), Italy (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Zoran et al., 2020b</xref>) and the USA (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Zoran et al., 2020b</xref>) by different means. There have been some studies demonstrating close associations between exposure to PMs and respiratory infectious diseases caused by some microorganisms. For instance, exposure to PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and PM
 <sub>10</sub> have been proved to be associated with increased risk of drug resistant tuberculosis in a two-year study of 752 cases in Jinan, China (
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2019</xref>), and increased risk of influenza in a six-year study in Taiwan (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). Besides, a former study reported significant short-term association between ambient PM levels and increased hospitalization for pneumonia by nationwide time-series study in China (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Tian et al., 2019</xref>). It has also been verified that air pollutants emitted from vehicles and industries, including NO
 <sub>x</sub> and PMs, may affect viral transmission dynamics and increase the risks of hospital admissions due to respiratory virus bronchiolitis and asthma (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Glencross et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Sarmadi et al., 2020</xref>). Although the exact mechanisms for a causal association between PMs and SARS-CoV-2 transmission remains unclear, previous studies found that viruses are more likely to attached to suspended particles, rather than be airborne independently (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2010</xref>). Since the enveloped virion of SARS-CoV-2 measures as small as 50–200 nm (
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2020b</xref>), the PM effect could occur if the virus associates physically with the particles, and the particles might prolong the aerosol transmission of viruses, thus increase the probability of infection. Recent studies revealed that the accelerated transmission dynamics of COVID-19 had a significant association with highly polluted cities, and transmission dynamics of COVID-19 is due to mainly to the mechanism of airborne viral infectivity rather than “human-to-human transmission” (measured with density of population) (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2020</xref>), which might explain the possible mechanisms for the association.
</p>
