<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0165">In stratified analyses, Hubei province was separated from other part of nation and demonstrated a respectively violent risk ratio change on several lag days. Fewer cities included and diminishment cases on rise period in model would increase the statistical uncertainty in estimations of the effect. Moreover, the real relation between air pollution and coronavirus infection would be exaggerated and concealed due to the fact that the count of confirmed cases in Hubei was way much higher than other areas which means little change in concentration of air pollutants came along with great fluctuation in new confirmed cases. Thus, it might explain the positive relation between O
 <sub>3</sub> and coronavirus new cases on account of the gentle rise of ozone shown in 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>. What’s more, a significant adverse effects of air pollutants and number of daily confirmed cases were observed in North China. The probable interpretation might be that strict lockdown policies in North China resulted in a sharp decrease of air pollutant concentration, which may affect the supposed effect. The North China is considered as one of the most polluted regions in China and smog events have occurred frequently (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2017</xref>). It is reasonable to speculate that control measures contributed to a more significant decline in North China compared to other regions. Additional research is needed to determine the biological mechanisms behind this phenomenon. In addition, the effects of CO and SO
 <sub>2</sub> in northeast and southwest of China remained positive while the eastern and northern part of China showed a negative relation between those gaseous pollutants and COVID-19 infection. The discordance resulted in the overall negative association came from differed measures of control and diversity of population density and medical resource in disparate areas.
</p>
