<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The data of 1,635 patients included in this study were retrieved from the electronic medical record database and segregated in a single excel sheet. The columns included the data on demographics, clinical presentation, and ocular diagnosis and were exported for analysis. The excel sheet with the required data was then used for analysis using the appropriate statistical software. Standardized definitions were used for occupation and socioeconomic status.[
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] The geographic categorization of the districts of India was performed under the National Sample Survey Organization (NSSO) which defines “rural“ as an area with a population density of up to 400 per km
 <sup>2</sup>.[
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] The Constitution (seventy-fourth Amendment) Act, 1992 defines a metropolitan area in India as, an area having a population of one million or more, comprised in one or more districts and consisting of two or more municipalities or panchayats or other contiguous areas, specified by the Governor by public notification to be a metropolitan area. The remaining districts were classified as urban.[
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] The weather parameters of 33 districts of the state of Telangana were obtained from the Telangana State Development and Planning Society (TSDPS), Government of Telangana. TSDPS facilitates data collection through 1044 Automated Weather Stations (AWS), 64 global radiation sensors, and 41 soil moisture sensors across the state of Telangana to acquire data on a real-time basis. The AWS measures 6 weather parameters, namely, rainfall, wind speed, wind direction, pressure, humidity, and temperature in addition to Global Radiation and Soil Moisture at desired locations at every 1 h interval and transmits it in the form of SMS using GSM technology. At least, one AWS for each Mandal is installed in a grid of 10 km × 10 km.[
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] The weather parameters were then mapped to the cohort of patients from the district of Hyderabad.
</p>
