<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">To return to the present pandemic, one important fact that must be mentioned once more is that the early cases in Europe, and the localized outbreaks in China prior to the Wuhan outburst, had failed to spread epidemically. A number of reasons have been proposed to explain the finding. For example, in those initial episodes, the virus had not been permitted to spread to an adequately large number of individuals such as the infected people in remote villages close to the bat caves in China, and the patient who was immediately hospitalized in France. It has now become clear that the most important reason is the virus itself, which at that initial stage still had a relatively low transmission ability. As of today, about 160 complete genomes of COVID-19 have been sequenced from human patients: phylogenetic work on them has identified three central variants distinguished by aminoacid changes: A, B, and C
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup>. A is the ancestral type, as it is the closest to that discovered in bats. The three variants have different geographical distribution, B being the most common in East Asia, and A and C outside East Asia, i.e., Europe and the Americas. More than 80,000 sequences of the virus are now available (the majority of them from COVID-19), and well over 100 mutations have been described. Among them, the most interesting is a D614G mutation in the C terminal region of subunit S1 of the Spike protein, which is the region in which subunit S1 associates with subunit S2 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). It is still not clear whether this mutation has originated in East Asia or in Europe, but what is known is that the mutated virus has been found to spread with alarming speed outside East Asia over a period of a few months becoming the dominant form of COVID-19 in Europe and the Americas
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. The form of the disease caused by the virus with the D614G mutation was first documented in a case in Germany in February 2019 (sequence deposited on January 28), and then the mutated virus spread across Europe to rapidly represent the dominant form of the COVID-19 pandemic. By the end of January, 98.3 % of the sequences submitted from East Asia and 90-to 100% of those submitted from the remainder of the world were of the “correct” subtype with an aspartate in position 614. By the end of February the frequency of the mutated subtype had already risen to over 50% in Europe, and about 10% in North America (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). By contrast, the non-mutated subtype has remained low in China and other East Asia countries
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>. The spread of the mutated sub-type in Europe and the American continent has then continued to grow explosively to more than 200 countries in different continents.
</p>
