<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">The current study involved 376 HIV patients (212 females and 164 males) on ART showed a high knowledge and practice score towards COVID-29 prevention measures and a high poor attitude score (1/4). There was no association between knowledge score and gender, age, residence, employment, or duration on ART. Duration on ART significantly affected both attitude and practice scores while also, employment was associated with attitude and gender was associated with practice scores. The correlational study showed that attitude scores increase as knowledge scores increase, practice scores increase as knowledge scores increase, and attitude scores increase as practice scores increase. The findings of the current study revealed a high prevalence of poor attitude among the participants (26%), unlike other studies in Saudi Arabia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] and China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], which reported low prevalence. Although Rwanda's government put strict measures against preventive measures against COVID-19, this might be due to theories that people tend to develop negative emotions like panic and anxiety during a pandemic, which significantly affects their attitude [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The study revealed high knowledge and practice scores, and these findings are consistent with other KAP studies done in Ethiopia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], Kenya [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and Iran [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. This may be explained by the easy availability and accessibility of health information online, improving patient knowledge and practice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The study was also conducted in an urban setting with limitless access to COVID-19- associated updates and preventive actions posted online by the Rwandan MOH and various media platforms that have been positively associated with improving knowledge and practices. These findings differ from those of a study done in rural setting Ethiopia with limited COVID-19 access due to lack of electricity and the internet, where the prevalence of poor knowledge was 33.9% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The current study showed that participants knowledgeable about COVID-19 were more likely to have good practices. This finding is similar to a study in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. This can be justified by the reason that knowledge is a key modifier of positive attitudes for preventive practices of COVID-19, and these practices are executed after acquiring awareness and information of practices to be implemented. Knowledge of COVID-19 reduces the possibility of infection by improving patient’s practices [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The current study reported that gender is considerably associated with practice score, and these findings corroborate studies done in other settings, which reported that females are more likely to take preventive and protective measures than males [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The study found no association between gender, age, residence, employment, and duration on ART, contrary to Nepal's studies conducted during the peak of COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. This could be due to the fact that this study was conducted at a later stage of the pandemic than in Nepal when information about COVID-19 was found everywhere and accessible to all age groups. Also, the government of Rwanda deployed drones to raise COVID-19 awareness in communities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The current study reported an association between ART duration and attitude and knowledge scores, with those on ART for less than one year recording high attitude and knowledge scores. This might be because those on ART for less than a year were enrolled during the pandemic and benefited from opportunistic health promotion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].
</p>
