<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0020">On December 31, 2019, the World Health Organization (WHO) was informed of an outbreak of respiratory illnesses, including atypical pneumonia, which seriously threatened the global public health, detected around Wuhan Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market in the Chinese city of Wuhan, Hubei Province–the seventh-largest city in China with 11 million city residents. Of note, some of the first reported infected individuals from the wet market showed symptoms as early as December 8, 2019. Subsequently, the wet market was closed on January 1, 2020. The virus causing the outbreak of mysterious pneumonia cases was quickly determined to be a novel coronavirus, and this novel coronavirus was further named 2019-nCoV by WHO (
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020a</xref>). On 23 January, 2020, Chinese authorities introduced unprecedented measures to contain the virus, stopping movement in and out of Wuhan and 15 other cities in Hubei Province. Consequently, WHO declared the 2019-nCoV outbreak to be a Public Health Emergency of International Concern (PHEIC) under International Health Regulations on 30 January 2020. The newly emerged coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) is similar to betacoronaviruses detected in bats, reportedly sharing ∼96 % sequence identity to the BetaCoV/bat/Yunnan/RaTG13/2013 (EPI_ISL_402131) genome, a coronavirus isolated from an intermediate horseshoe bat (
 <italic>Rhinolophus affinis</italic>) in Yunnan Province, China (
 <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020b</xref>). SARS-CoV-2, a member of the betacoronavirus genus of the Coronaviridae family, is a single, positive-strand RNA, approximately 30 kb in length, however, the mortality and transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2 are still unknown. On 11 February 2020, the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses officially renamed 2019-nCoV, which is responsible for the current outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). This virus belongs to the same family as the SARS-CoV-1 pathogen, which was responsible for &gt;8 000 cases and 774 deaths in 37 countries during the 2002–2003 SARS outbreak (
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Drosten et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">Ksiazek et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">Zhong et al., 2003</xref>), and the MERS-CoV pathogen, which was responsible for 2 494 cases and 858 deaths in 27 countries during the 2012 MERS outbreak (
 <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">Zaki et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">de Groot et al., 2013</xref>). Notably, the current COVID-19 outbreak is characterized by its significant dispersal into many major urban centers in China and beyond, further facilitating its continued spread from person to person (
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020a</xref>), and has caused considerable morbidity and mortality in China and elsewhere. As of 14 July 2020, a total of 12 964 809 confirmed cases including 570 288 deaths in 216 countries, areas or territories, have been reported globally by WHO (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" id="intr0005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link>), with USA, Brazil, India, and Russia especially hard hit. Although the number of confirmed cases of COVID-19 worldwide has excessed 12 million, it showed that countries had only discovered on average about 6 % of coronavirus infections and the true number of infected people worldwide may already have reached several tens of millions(
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://medicalxpress.com/news/2020-04-covid-average-actual-infections-worldwide.html" id="intr0010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://medicalxpress.com/news/2020-04-covid-average-actual-infections-worldwide.html</ext-link>). Notably, there are many asymptomatic carriers remaining in humans and the nucleic acid of SARS-CoV-2 from some convalescent patients could be tested positive again which means that the virus cannot be eradicated and can replicate again. These factors will contribute the subsequent COVID-19 outbreaks, and many scientists believe that COVID-19 outbreaks will be recurrence.
</p>
