<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0025">Over the past three and half decades at least 30 new infectious agents affecting humans have emerged including SARS-CoV-2, and most of them are zoonotic. It was also reported that 61 % infectious organisms affecting humans are zoonotic diseases which can infect both human and animals (
 <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">Nii-Trebi, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">McArthur, 2019</xref>). Previous studies have revealed that both SARS-CoV-1 and MERS-CoV originated in bats (
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">Lau et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">Lau et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2005</xref>), with SARS-CoV-1 jumping to humans from palm civets (
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Chinese, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2005</xref>) and MERS-CoV jumping to humans from camels (
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Muller et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2014</xref>) following intermediate transmission from bats (
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">Lau et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">Lau et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2005</xref>). Research has also revealed that SARS-CoV-2 likely originated in bats, either directly or through an as-yet unidentified animal host (
 <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020b</xref>). Initial cases have been linked to Wuhan Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market; however, the specific animal source is yet to be determined (
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020a</xref>). The detection of SARS-CoV-2 in humans without knowing the animal source of infection has heightened concerns not only in China, but also internationally. Therefore, identifying the animal source of SARS-CoV-2 is still a top research priority for controlling the COVID-19 outbreak. The deadly pandemic has prompted a high-speed race to understand how the coronavirus is evolving and spreading. But doing so requires an unprecedented collaboration among scientists, across the globe, to decode the virus and its path.
</p>
