<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38">Faced with a deceitful, capricious, and fierce opponent like COVID-19, we cannot simply watch the medical staff in the emergency department fight alone at the frontline, while the others in the hospital make no contributions. If the war on COVID-19 is to be won, forces across multiple departments must be united in the hospital. Studies related to Ebola prevention and control show that a scientific and effective emergency plan is critical for the early response and comprehensive interventions of HAI outbreaks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Therefore, at the very beginning, PKUFH set up the "leading group for prevention and treatment of COVID-19" and "expert group for prevention and diagnosis of COVID-19" by clarifying their respective responsibilities, and formulated a feasible "
 <italic>Working Plan for Diagnosis, Treatment and Prevention of COVID-19</italic>". The leading group was responsible for the overall management of the prevention and control tasks, formulation and dynamic adjustment of the prevention and control programs and measures, collection of information and feedbacks, and deployment of medical staff and supplies. The leading group consisted of experts from the head of the hospital, the Prevention and Control of Healthcare-associated Infections Department, the Medical Affairs Department, the Nursing Department, the Pharmacy Department, the Medical Equipment Department, the Human Resources Department, and the General Affairs Department. On the other side, the expert group, consisted of experts from the Infectious Diseases Department, the Emergency Department, the Respiratory Department, the Intensive Medicine Department, the Obstetrics and Gynecology Department, the Pharmacy Department, the Laboratory Department, the Medical Imaging Department, and the infection prevention and control, was responsible for the diagnosis and treatment of COVID-19 and the work of infection prevention and control guidance and training.
</p>
