<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0390">
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://asia.nikkei.com/Spotlight/Coronavirus/None-of-Japan-s-new-coronavirus-patients-had-direct-China-links" id="ir0040" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://asia.nikkei.com/Spotlight/Coronavirus/None-of-Japan-s-new-coronavirus-patients-had-direct-China-links</ext-link>
 <list list-type="simple" id="l0030">
  <list-item id="u0100">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0395">A Kanagawa Prefecture woman in her 80s died from the coronavirus. Her son-in-law also tested positive for the disease. A doctor in Wakayama Prefecture and a man in Chiba Prefecture are confirmed to have the virus. None of them traveled to China recently or had contact with people who visited Hubei Province, the epicenter of the outbreak. The 80 year old woman's symptoms began January 22 when she felt fatigue, the health ministry said. Symptoms worsened on January 25, prompting her to see a doctor 3 days later. She was placed under observation. The victim was hospitalized February 1, diagnosed with pneumonia. She underwent screening for the coronavirus Wednesday. The test results came back positive Thursday, the day she died. Her son-in-law also tested positive for the coronavirus. The man, a taxi driver in his 70s living in Tokyo, has been hospitalized since February 6, but the symptoms are reportedly mild. He developed a fever January 29.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0105">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0400">A doctor in Wakayama Prefecture south of Osaka has been infected with the virus, prefectural officials said Thursday. The man, in his 50s, has been hospitalized with symptoms of pneumonia, but is otherwise in stable condition. The doctor did not travel outside the country in the 14 days prior to the onset of symptoms, nor can any contact with people coming from China be confirmed. Wakayama officials suspect the infection had domestic origins.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0110">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0405">Elsewhere, a man in his 20s from Chiba Prefecture near Tokyo is also confirmed to have the virus. He developed a fever and other symptoms February 2. The man reportedly has not travelled overseas or had contact with other infected individuals.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0115">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0410">Besides the outbreak on the Diamond Princess cruise ship, which has infected over 200 people aboard the vessel quarantined in Yokohama, 29 cases of coronavirus had been confirmed inside Japan through Wednesday.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0120">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0415">These cases raise new challenges for health officials, who until now had been trying to contain the virus by closely monitoring people with the possibility of contracting the disease. If more people with no direct links to China become sick, determining infection routes will become impossible. Instead of containment, treating seriously sick people may have to become the priority.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
