<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0012">Epidemic outbreaks of emerging infectious diseases including severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) (
 <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Hong et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mak et al., 2009</xref>), Ebola (
 <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">James et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Kamara et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Shultz et al., 2016</xref>), influenza A (H1N1) (
 <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Luyt et al., 2012</xref>), and Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) (Kim et al.,2018) have led to serious psychological effects on patients including anxiety, fear, and depression. In severe cases, post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and other mental disorders have occurred. The SARS outbreak was a catastrophic event for mental health (
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mak et al., 2009</xref>). During the epidemic, survivors of infected medical staff displayed high levels of stress which manifested as depression and anxiety. Up to 64% of these individuals developed lasting mental illnesses such as PTSD (
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). In addition, 50% of Ebola patients have exhibited mild distress or depression, anxiety, sadness, and social problems. Approximately 20% of patients required psychotropic medications (
 <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Kamara et al., 2017</xref>). Similarly, H1N1 survivors retained psychological barriers and a poor quality of life one year after discharge from the intensive care unit (ICU) (
 <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Luyt et al., 2012</xref>). The MERS epidemic increased the risk of psychological distress and mental illness, with 70.8% of survivors showing mental symptoms and 41.7% diagnosed and treated for psychological symptoms during hospitalization (
 <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
