<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Lat Am Enfermagem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rlae</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Revista Latino-Americana de Enfermagem</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0104-1169</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1518-8345</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Escola de Enfermagem de Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto / Universidade de S&#x000e3;o
Paulo</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7529449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">00410</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1518-8345.3614.3365</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Economic and epidemiological evaluation of text message-based
interventions in patients with the Human Immunodeficiency Virus<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="pt"><trans-title>Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o econ&#x000f4;mica e epidemiol&#x000f3;gica de interven&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es baseadas em
mensagens de texto em pacientes com o V&#x000ed;rus da Imunodefici&#x000ea;ncia Humana
</trans-title></trans-title-group><trans-title-group xml:lang="es"><trans-title>Evaluaci&#x000f3;n econ&#x000f3;mica y epidemiol&#x000f3;gica de intervenciones basadas en
mensajes de texto en pacientes con el Virus de la Inmunodeficiencia Humana
</trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1943-4525</contrib-id><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>Wendel Mombaque</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9735-6502</contrib-id><name><surname>Primeira</surname><given-names>Marcelo Ribeiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5471-148X</contrib-id><name><surname>de Paiva</surname><given-names>Larissa Garcia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3272-054X</contrib-id><name><surname>Padoin</surname><given-names>Stela Maris de Mello</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Empresa Brasileira de Servi&#x000e7;os Hospitalares, Hospital Universit&#x000e1;rio
de Santa Maria, Santa Maria, RS, Brazil.</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Universidade Federal de Santa Maria, Departamento de Enfermagem,
Santa Maria, RS, Brazil.</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Scholarship holder at the Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal
de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (CAPES), Brazil.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding author: Wendel Mombaque dos Santos E-mail:
<email>wendelmombaque@hotmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Associate editor: Andrea Bernardes</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><elocation-id>e3365</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Revista Latino-Americana de
Enfermagem</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Revista Latino-Americana de Enfermagem</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objective:</title><p>to evaluate the cost-effectiveness ratio and the budget impact of sending
text messages associated with medical consultations in order to reduce the
viral load of patients infected with the Human Immunodeficiency Virus.</p></sec><sec><title>Method:</title><p>a randomized clinical trial, basis for the development of a dynamic cohort
model with Markov states in order to compare medical appointments for adults
infected with the Human Immunodeficiency Virus <italic>versus</italic> the
alternative strategy that associated medical consultations to sending text
messages through telephone.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>156 adults participated in the study. As for the viral load, it was verified
that in the control group there was an increase, in the intervention group A
(weekly messages) there was a reduction (p = 0.002) and in group B (biweekly
messages) there was no statistically significant difference. Sending text
messages would prevent 286,538 new infections by the Human Immunodeficiency
Virus and 282 deaths in the 20-year period, compared to the standard
treatment. The alternative strategy would result in saving R$ 14 billion in
treatment costs.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>weekly sending messages in association with the standard treatment can reduce
the circulating viral load due to its effect in decreasing new infections,
in addition to reducing health costs.</p></sec></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="pt"><sec><title>Objetivo:</title><p>avaliar a raz&#x000e3;o custo-efetividade e o impacto or&#x000e7;ament&#x000e1;rio do envio de
mensagens de texto, associadas &#x000e0;s consultas m&#x000e9;dicas, para redu&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da carga
viral de pacientes infectados com o V&#x000ed;rus da Imunodefici&#x000ea;ncia Humana.</p></sec><sec><title>M&#x000e9;todo:</title><p>ensaio cl&#x000ed;nico randomizado, base para o desenvolvimento de um modelo de
coorte din&#x000e2;mica com estados de Markov a fim de comparar consultas m&#x000e9;dicas
para adultos infectados pelo V&#x000ed;rus da Imunodefici&#x000ea;ncia Humana
<italic>versus</italic> a estrat&#x000e9;gia alternativa que associou consultas
m&#x000e9;dicas, ao envio de mensagens de texto pelo telefone.</p></sec><sec><title>Resultados:</title><p>participaram do estudo 156 adultos. Quanto &#x000e0; carga viral, foi verificado que
no grupo controle houve aumento, no grupo interven&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o A (mensagens semanais)
houve redu&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o (p=0,002) e no grupo B (mensagens quinzenais) n&#x000e3;o houve
diferen&#x000e7;a estatisticamente significante. O envio de mensagens de texto
evitaria 286.538 novas infec&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es pelo V&#x000ed;rus da Imunodefici&#x000ea;ncia Humana e 282
mortes no per&#x000ed;odo de 20 anos, ao comparar com o tratamento padr&#x000e3;o. A
estrat&#x000e9;gia alternativa resultaria em uma economia de R$ 14 bilh&#x000f5;es nos
custos de tratamento.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclus&#x000e3;o:</title><p>o envio semanal de mensagens em associa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o ao tratamento padr&#x000e3;o pode reduzir
a carga viral circulante por seu efeito na diminui&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de novas infe&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es,
al&#x000e9;m da redu&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de custos em sa&#x000fa;de.</p></sec></trans-abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="es"><sec><title>Objetivo:</title><p>evaluar la relaci&#x000f3;n costo-efectividad y el impacto presupuestario del env&#x000ed;o
de mensajes de texto, asociados con consultas m&#x000e9;dicas, para reducir la carga
viral de pacientes infectados con el Virus de Inmunodeficiencia Humana.</p></sec><sec><title>M&#x000e9;todo:</title><p>ensayo cl&#x000ed;nico aleatorizado, que sirve de base para el desarrollo de un
modelo de cohorte din&#x000e1;mico con estados de Markov para comparar consultas
m&#x000e9;dicas para adultos infectados con el Virus de Inmunodeficiencia Humana
versus la estrategia alternativa que consisti&#x000f3; en asociar las consultas
m&#x000e9;dicas al env&#x000ed;o de mensajes de texto por tel&#x000e9;fono m&#x000f3;vil.</p></sec><sec><title>Resultados:</title><p>156 adultos participaron en el estudio. En cuanto a la carga viral, se
encontr&#x000f3; que en el grupo control hubo aumento, en el grupo de intervenci&#x000f3;n A
(mensajes semanales) hubo una reducci&#x000f3;n (p = 0,002) y en el grupo B
(mensajes quincenales) no hubo diferencias estad&#x000ed;sticamente significativas.
El env&#x000ed;o de mensajes de texto podr&#x000ed;a evitar 286.538 nuevas infecciones por
el Virus de Inmunodeficiencia Humana y 282 muertes en el per&#x000ed;odo de 20 a&#x000f1;os,
en comparaci&#x000f3;n con el tratamiento est&#x000e1;ndar. La estrategia alternativa
resultar&#x000ed;a en un ahorro de R$ 14 mil millones en costos de tratamiento</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusi&#x000f3;n:</title><p>el env&#x000ed;o semanal de mensajes de forma complementaria al tratamiento est&#x000e1;ndar
puede reducir la carga viral circulante debido a su efecto en la disminuci&#x000f3;n
de nuevas infecciones, adem&#x000e1;s de reducir los costos en materia de salud.</p></sec></trans-abstract><kwd-group><title>Descriptors:</title><kwd>HIV</kwd><kwd>Costs and Cost Analysis</kwd><kwd>Text Messaging</kwd><kwd>Controlled Clinical Trial</kwd><kwd>Cost-Benefit Analysis</kwd><kwd>Communicable Diseases</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group xml:lang="pt"><title>Descritores:</title><kwd>HIV</kwd><kwd>Custos e An&#x000e1;lise de Custo</kwd><kwd>Envio de Mensagens de Texto</kwd><kwd>Ensaio Cl&#x000ed;nico Controlado</kwd><kwd>An&#x000e1;lise Custo-Benef&#x000ed;cio</kwd><kwd>Doen&#x000e7;as Transmiss&#x000ed;veis</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group xml:lang="es"><title>Descriptores:</title><kwd>VIH</kwd><kwd>Costos y An&#x000e1;lisis de Costo</kwd><kwd>Env&#x000ed;o de Mensajes de Texto</kwd><kwd>Ensayo Cl&#x000ed;nico Controlado</kwd><kwd>An&#x000e1;lisis Costo-Beneficio</kwd><kwd>Enfermedades Transmisibles</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Infections caused by the Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) have shown a progressive
increase over time since the first identified cases of the disease<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. After the appearance and registration of these cases, dating from the
early 1980s, approximately 70 million people contracted the infection and, of these,
about 35 million died<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Currently, it is estimated that approximately 37 million people live with HIV in the
world, characterizing it as one of the main threats to public health, especially in
low or middle income countries<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Despite all the progress made in recent years and the reduction of
annual infections by 3% in the period from 2007 to 2017, this infection continues to
spread throughout the world, leading to 1.8 million new infections/year and 1
million deaths/year<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>An example of one of the greatest progresses made in combating this epidemic was the
discovery of anti-retroviral treatment (ART) for HIV infection, but its
effectiveness and efficiency depend on a series of factors associated with patient
compliance. For this reason, the assessment of adherence has been verified by
different mechanisms, such as real-time assessment and the verification of the
concentration of ART in the hair or blood<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The adoption of measures to assess adherence is essential, as
inadequate adherence to ART causes an increase in circulating viral load and,
consequently, directly interferes in the control of infection and disease
progression<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In addition, there is an impact on the patient&#x02019;s life expectancy and
influence on medical costs related to the progression of the disease, complications,
hospitalizations and the treatment of new infections, with adherence being the
primary factor for the control of this infection and the early detection of
HIV<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>In Brazil, ART, as we currently know it, was introduced in 1996 with the principles
of universal and free access to the health services and medications, in accordance
with the Brazilian health system policy<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. This policy has achieved good results, mainly in terms of reducing
morbidity and mortality, reducing hospitalizations and treatment costs, leading to
rates similar to those of developed countries<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>However, this success achieved by Brazilian health policy still faces the poor
adherence of patients to ART, which goes beyond free access to treatment, since it
depends on the patient&#x02019;s ability to overcome the barriers that negatively impact
their adherence<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In this sense, there is a need for investment in actions and
strategies that can mitigate the cultural, social, and economic differences of these
patients, collaborating in improving the adherence and effectiveness of ART, which
must be proposed by health services and supported by public health
policies<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>In recent years, some systematic reviews have shown that interventions based on
medical consultations, nursing consultations, telephone calls, text messaging,
financial incentives and behavioral therapy have improved adherence to ART, but none
has carried out an assessment from an economic and epidemiological perspective,
aiming to demonstrate how these interventions interfere in the long term in the
incidence of new cases<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In this sense, non-medication and cost-effective interventions, from
an economic point of view, such as sending text messages, can help maintain
adherence throughout ART without dispensing high costs to the health system and with
easy applicability for large populations regardless of their location and facility
to the health system<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In addition, few studies estimate the impact of these interventions on
the population scenario, considering their costs and the possibility of reducing new
infections.</p><p>Thus, this study aimed to assess the cost-effectiveness ratio and the budget impact
of sending text messages associated with medical consultations in order to reduce
the viral load of HIV-infected patients. Additionally, the number of new infections
prevented and the budget impact were evaluated as a way to propose a cost-effective
action to improve adherence and decrease HIV infection rates.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Method</title><p>This is a randomized controlled trial (RCT) that served as a basis for the
development of a dynamic cohort model with Markov states to compare the standard
treatment (isolated medical visits) for HIV-infected people <italic>versus</italic>
the alternative strategy (medical visits and sending text messages). The Markov
model is indicated for use in dynamic models of transmission of infectious diseases,
since this model is capable of simulating interactions among human beings and how
these interactions affect the spread of a disease, HIV in the case of this study,
throughout time<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In addition, this model allows for the inclusion of details relevant
to the spread of these diseases, such as different mortality rates, birth rates, and
probability of infection according to the severity of the pathology<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Text messages are also known for their acronym, SMS (Short Message Service),
compatible with practically every mobile phone today. In order to increase the
transparency of the economic model of the proposed study, this study was prepared
according to the recommendations of the CHEERS Task Force Report
checklist<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Conducting the RCT was necessary due to the lack of information in the literature
regarding the best frequency of sending text messages to reduce viral load in the
context of the public health system in Brazil. The prospective and double-blind RCT
was performed at the University Hospital of Santa Maria, linked to the Federal
University of Santa Maria, from July 2016 to October 2018, in order to assess the
impact on the viral load of sending SMS. The referred Hospital assists approximately
1,200 people infected with HIV, of whom 500 are being followed up at the infectious
disease outpatient clinic and the others attend the service for laboratory tests and
medication withdrawal. This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of
the Federal University of Santa Maria and published in the Brazilian Registry of
Clinical Trials, under the RBR-9nt9hv identifier.</p><p>The population was composed of adults infected with HIV and who had been on ART for
at least 3 months. The exclusion criteria were the following: presenting some
limitation that would make it difficult to understand or express themselves verbally
and being in prison, due to the unavailability of access to cell phones.</p><p>For the sample calculation, &#x003b1; = 0.05, &#x003b2; = 0.2, q1 = 0.25; q2 = 0.25, q0 = 0.5, P0 =
0.85, and P1 = 0.6 were considered, using the following formula: <inline-formula><mml:math id="e01"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathsize="12.0pt"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>Za</mml:mi><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>.</mml:mi><mml:mn>750</mml:mn><mml:mi>;</mml:mi><mml:mspace/><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x003b2;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>.</mml:mi><mml:mn>722</mml:mn><mml:mi>;</mml:mi><mml:mspace/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>.</mml:mi><mml:mn>063</mml:mn><mml:mi>;</mml:mi><mml:mspace/><mml:mi>Total</mml:mi><mml:mspace/><mml:mi>Pop</mml:mi><mml:mi>.</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>147</mml:mn><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. When the formula was applied, a minimum total population of 147
participants was obtained. The selection of participants was carried out in a
randomized way by simple draw.</p><p>The interventions were carried out according to the following groups:</p><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Control group &#x02013; They received reminders of consultations with an
infectious disease physician containing date and time and monthly check
for receipt of messages.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Intervention group A &#x02013; They received reminders of consultations with an
infectious disease physician containing date and time, monthly check for
receipt of messages, and a weekly social support text message.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Intervention group B &#x02013; They received reminders of consultations with an
infectious disease physician with date and time, monthly check for
messages, and a biweekly social support text message.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>The monthly check for the receipt of text messages consisted of sending a message
every 30 days, in which the patient should answer this message with a requested
number and letter. This confirmation aims to ensure that the study participants were
still receiving and reading the messages that were sent to them.</p><p>There was no group with daily and monthly messages, based on studies that showed that
these sending frequencies are less effective than the weekly or biweekly ones, and
the text messages used in the intervention groups are based on the conceptual
framework of social support<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The messages sent did not inform the diagnosis of HIV infection,
respecting the patients&#x02019; privacy. The messages were sent in the following order
based on social support domains and, at the end of the last message (number 6), it
returned to the initial message (number 1)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>)</sup>:</p><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Keep strong. We at the Santa Maria University Hospital care and take care
of you.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Everyone feels sad at times. Remember that you can talk about depression
at your next appointment.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Smile, breathe, and go ahead.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Invest in your health. Remember to eat healthy foods and practice
physical activities.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Be active in your health. Keep your appointments scheduled.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Have you taken your medication? They help, even if you think they are not
working.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>Data collection was carried out by applying a questionnaire to characterize the
population of adults infected with HIV, which occurred at 2 different moments:
Moment 1 &#x02013; Questionnaires for characterization of the population and viral load
(month 0); Moment 2 &#x02013; Viral load (month 6).</p><p>Data analysis was performed by means of a descriptive analysis of the variables and
multiple linear regression in order to assess the hazard ratio for the reduction of
viral load values, considering viral suppression (viral load below 50
copies/ml).</p><p>The dynamic cohort model was based on a hypothetical cohort of 210,659,013
individuals in Brazil in 2019, of which 827,000 were infected with HIV, being
studied for a period of 20 years. The analysis was performed in the TreeAge Pro
2019r software (TreeAge Software Inc., Williamstown, MA).</p><p>The model was based on HIV infection prevalence rates in Brazil considering the year
2017<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The 20-year period was chosen to demonstrate the HIV infection chain,
in which it is important to keep infected people on viral suppression to avoid the
risk of transmitting the virus. In this scenario, possible outbreaks of infection
were not considered.</p><p>The analysis compared two strategies: the standard treatment provided by the Unified
Health System (<italic>Sistema</italic> &#x000da;nico <italic>de Sa&#x000fa;de</italic>, SUS) and an
alternative strategy with the inclusion of sending text messages to the standard
treatment (the most effective sending frequency). According to the model diagram
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>), the treatment strategy
considers four transition states, which are changed in annual cycles:</p><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>People not infected with HIV, that is, are susceptible to infection. At
each cycle they may remain uninfected, acquire HIV infection or evolve
to death.</p></list-item><list-item><p>People infected with HIV and with a viral load above 50 copies/ml, that
is, are the people who have the possibility of transmitting the virus.
At each cycle they can remain infected, evolve to undetectable viral
load or evolve to death.</p></list-item><list-item><p>People undergoing treatment and with an undetectable viral load (viral
load below 50 copies/ml), that is, they have HIV, but do not have the
possibility of transmitting the virus. At each cycle they can have
detectable viral load or evolve to death.</p></list-item><list-item><p>People who die, which may or may not be related to the infection
situation. People who are in this cycle do not have the possibility to
change to another state of health.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>
<fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Markov Model</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104-1169-rlae-28-e3365-gf01"/></fig>
</p><p>The economic analysis was carried out from the perspective of the SUS. The
perspective of the public health system included direct medical costs (medical
consultation, medication, laboratory tests, and hospitalizations due to
complications). The costs were estimated in reais, with reference to the year 2018
(US$ = 1.00 - R$ 3.89). Future costs and effectiveness were discounted at 5%
<italic>per</italic> year.</p><p>The effectiveness data were based on data from the RCT (reduction of viral load) and
on data from the literature (general infection rate)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In the model, an estimate was made that, in 2018, approximately 90% of
the HIV-infected patients were aware of their serological condition<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The cost data were estimated on the cost of sending a weekly text message for a
period of 1 year, the costs of treating people with an undetectable viral load, and
the cost of treating people with a detectable viral load. The cost of the treatment
considered the possibility of hospitalizations, as well as the greater or lesser
need for laboratory tests.</p><p>The multivariate analysis verified the impact of the set of variables on the model,
which was performed by Monte Carlo simulation (100,000 interactions), which randomly
chooses values from the parameter distributions to jointly estimate the costs and
effects of each strategy.</p><p>The variables and values used to estimate the parameters for the distributions were
described in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Model parameters. Santa Maria, RS, Brazil, 2018</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col width="70%" span="1"/><col width="30%" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial population - Not infected with HIV</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210,659,013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial population - HIV infected</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285,150</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial population - Infected with HIV and viral load
below 50 copies/ml</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541,850</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial population - Dead</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time horizon<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">*</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cycles per year</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual mortality rate - Not infected with HIV</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00647</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual mortality rate - HIV infected</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0066284</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual mortality rate - Infected with HIV and viral
load below 50 copies/ml</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006518</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natality</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01461</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discount rate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utility - Not infected with HIV</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utility - HIV infected</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utility - Infected with HIV and viral load below 50
copies/ml</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection rate<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">&#x02020;</xref></sup>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual cost<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">&#x02021;</xref></sup> - HIV infected</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,430.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual cost<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">&#x02021;</xref></sup> - Infected with HIV and viral load below 50 copies/ml</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,867.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual cost<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">&#x02021;</xref></sup> - Weekly SMS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effectiveness - SMS<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN4">&#x000a7;</xref></sup>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2683</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effectiveness - Standard treatment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101030524</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><label>*</label><p>In years;</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Beta distribution;</p></fn><fn id="TFN3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Value expressed in reais;</p></fn><fn id="TFN4"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>Hazard ratio</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Initially, 168 individuals participated in the study; however, only 156 completed the
RCT. Among the individuals who did not complete the research, 1 withdrew, 1 died,
and 10 did not show up for final data collection, resulting in 51 participants in
the control group, 53 in intervention group A, and 52 in intervention group B. They
were predominantly female (57.1%; n = 89), lived with a spouse or a partner (51.3%;
n = 80), and HIV infection occurred through sexual transmission (69.9%; n =
109).</p><p>
<fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Flowchart of the randomized clinical trial</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104-1169-rlae-28-e3365-gf02"/></fig>
</p><p>Regarding the circulating viral load values according to the groups, it was verified
that, in the control group, there was an increase in the studied period (pre viral
load = 2,638.85; post viral load = 11,890.31; p = 0.001), in intervention group A
(weekly SMS sending) there was a reduction in the studied period (pre viral load =
4,598.92; post viral load = 5.68; p = 0.002) and, in group B (biweekly SMS sending)
there was no statistically significant difference in the studied period (pre viral
load = 854.11, post viral load = 3.367,83; p = 0.649). Thus, sending weekly SMSs was
1.26 times more likely to have a viral load below 50 copies/ml when compared to the
group not submitted to intervention.</p><p>The dynamic cohort model estimated that, with the standard treatment in the 2019
cohort, 29,386,767 people would die and 2,011,964 would be infected with HIV in the
20-year period. These cases would result in R$ 141 billion in total treatment costs.
The alternative strategy (SMS) would avoid 286,538 new HIV infections and 282 deaths
in the 20-year period when compared to the standard treatment. The alternative
strategy would result in saving R$ 14 billion in treatment costs (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Comparison between standard and SMS treatment over 20 years. Santa Maria,
RS, Brazil, 2018</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/><col width="9%" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid"><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Population without<break/>HIV
infection</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Population with<break/>HIV infection</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Population with<break/>HIV infection and
undetectable viral load</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Deaths total population</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Cumulative cost</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMS Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMS Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMS Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMS Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current Scenario</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMS Scenario</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209,832,013</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209,832,013</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285,150</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285,150</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541,850</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541,850</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,214,564,522</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,224,488,522</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211,513,910</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211,513,910</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298,465</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291,572</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">565,731</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">572,624</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,358,635</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,358,635</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,616,136,229</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,611,886,617</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213,208,094</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213,209,124</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">312,395</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298,133</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">590,736</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">603,970</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,728,360</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,728,359</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,213,248,604</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,165,116,514</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214,914,599</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214,917,752</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">326,968</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304,834</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">616,918</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">635,902</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,109,265</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,109,262</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,014,815,697</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,887,162,131</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216,633,457</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216,639,894</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342,214</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311,680</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644,330</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">668,432</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,501,442</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,501,437</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,030,148,567</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,781,070,170</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218,364,698</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218,375,650</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">358,161</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318,673</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">673,029</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">701,574</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,904,983</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,904,974</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,268,972,369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,849,951,221</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2025</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220,108,348</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220,125,121</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374,843</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">325,815</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">703,074</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">735,342</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,319,980</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,319,967</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,741,444,138</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,096,980,889</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2026</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221,864,430</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221,888,408</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392,292</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333,110</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">734,526</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">769,750</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,746,528</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,746,509</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39,458,171,271</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,525,400,929</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2027</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223,632,965</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223,665,613</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410,541</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340,561</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">767,451</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">804,811</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,184,721</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,184,694</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,430,230,742</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,138,520,407</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2028</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225,413,968</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225,456,838</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">429,629</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">348,171</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">801,916</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">840,541</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,634,654</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,634,618</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,669,189,075</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,939,716,870</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2029</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227,207,453</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227,262,187</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449,590</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">355,943</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">837,991</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">876,953</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,096,423</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,096,376</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58,187,123,086</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,932,437,535</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2030</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229,013,430</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229,081,763</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">470,465</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363,880</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">875,750</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">914,064</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,570,124</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,570,065</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64,996,641,437</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62,120,200,499</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2031</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230,831,904</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230,915,671</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">492,295</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">371,986</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">915,270</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">951,888</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,055,856</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,055,782</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72,110,907,005</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68,506,595,958</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2032</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232,662,876</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232,764,016</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">515,121</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">380,264</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">956,630</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">990,442</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,553,716</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,553,625</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79,543,660,111</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75,095,287,449</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2033</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">234,506,344</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">234,626,904</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538,987</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">388,717</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">999,915</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,029,740</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,063,804</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,063,694</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87,309,242,618</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81,890,013,107</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2034</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236,362,299</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236,504,441</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">563,940</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397,349</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,045,213</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,069,800</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,586,219</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,586,088</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95,422,622,933</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88,894,586,939</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2035</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238,230,731</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238,396,734</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">590,026</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406,164</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,092,614</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,110,638</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,121,063</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,120,908</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103,899,000,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96,112,900,115</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2036</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240,111,621</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240,303,891</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">617,297</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">415,164</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,142,214</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,152,271</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,668,436</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,668,254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112,756,000,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103,549,000,000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2037</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242,004,947</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242,226,021</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">645,804</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">424,354</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,194,112</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,194,715</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,228,443</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,228,230</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122,009,000,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111,207,000,000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2038</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243,910,683</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244,163,232</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">675,599</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433,736</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,248,412</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,237,989</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,801,185</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,800,939</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131,677,000,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119,090,000,000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2039</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245,828,793</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246,115,635</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">706,741</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443,316</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,305,223</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,282,110</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,386,767</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,386,484</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141,778,000,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127,204,000,000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>From the SUS point of view, the alternative strategy (SMS) is dominant (lower cost
and greater effectiveness) compared to the standard treatment. SMS showed a
cost-effectiveness ratio of R$28.24 and the standard treatment R$ 31.48, at the
population level.</p><p>The probabilistic sensitivity analysis indicated that, regardless of the willingness
to pay, the alternative strategy (SMS) is the most economical intervention when
compared to the standard treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure
3</xref>).</p><p>
<fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Probabilistic sensitivity analysis</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104-1169-rlae-28-e3365-gf03"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study verified that, compared to the usual clinical practice, the addition of
weekly SMS sending was economically more effective in reducing the circulating viral
load of patients infected with HIV and on ART. Within the period studied, the weekly
SMS intervention increased by 26% the chance of the patient having an undetectable
viral load. Despite the additional cost of the SMS intervention for each research
subject, a long-term saving was verified, as shown in the economic impact study, due
to the reduction in the incidence of HIV infections.</p><p>The SMS intervention generates savings of nearly R$ 14 billion in terms of treatment
costs for the SUS in Brazil and helps in the reduction of 263,424 new HIV
infections, considering the 20-year period. When projecting the effects of the
discrepancy at the beginning of treatment between the two groups, for the same
period of life, we verified that the SMS-based intervention accumulated more years
of life gain (incremental effectiveness) and lower cost (incremental cost) than the
control group. Maintaining the standard treatment would result in an additional cost
of R$ 50,862.36 per infection when compared to the SMS intervention. The robustness
of the lifetime model was verified by the sensitivity analysis, with variations of
the transition probabilities and costs. The SMS intervention was the dominant
treatment (lowest cost and highest effectiveness) compared to the current treatment
(highest cost and lowest effectiveness), which leads to a negative Incremental
Cost-effectiveness Ratio (ICER).</p><p>The results found in this study are similar to those of other analyses regarding
savings in interventions to improve adherence to treatment, which consider the
feasibility of screening in the population, nursing interventions, and connectivity
through an application to clarify and control patients with HIV<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Our conclusions are consistent with the arguments that even
interventions with modest effects can be more cost-effective compared to only the
usual care and treatments<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. These indicators demonstrate that the adoption of additional health
care strategies may enhance the maintenance of adherence in medium to long term.</p><p>Approaches based on sending SMS, as shown in this study, may improve adherence to
ART; however, there is no consensus in the literature regarding the content of SMS,
particularly with regard to the open discussion of the exposure of patients under
treatment. Thus, this study used indirect messages or reminders, used as a means for
initiating contact or for reminding the participants about the treatment, similarly
to research carried out in developing countries. The adoption of these measures
contributes to the patient&#x02019;s perception of the support offered by the health team,
corroborating the maintenance of adherence<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Sending SMS has been significantly used in the health area, mainly to improve quality
of life and attendance in primary care, and to reduce non-adherence and improve
health results at low cost, as well as the possibility of wide dissemination of
information in real time for the entire target population of the
intervention<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Additionally, the use of SMS reminders is an accessible, adequate, and
more cost-effective tool compared to those already spent on medication<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In this way, there are basically four types of benefits of
interventions performed by SMS: (1) improved efficiency in the provision of health
care; (2) improvement in treatment adherence; (3) public health benefits; (4) low
cost and good accessibility<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The main strength of this dynamic cohort analysis was that the sources of the
intervention parameter (sending SMS, and control group) were based on real-life
data, from an RCT. In addition, the model estimated the evolution of the
intervention over 20 years, demonstrating the linear increase in cost over this
period, and the sensitivity analysis demonstrated the robustness of the predicted
model. It is worth highlighting that this is the first study carried out in the
context of the SUS that considers an intervention based on SMS at the population
level.</p><p>This study had some limitations. First, the effectiveness of the SMS intervention was
based on the RCT data, but some clinical and epidemiological data were obtained from
the Ministry of Health data source; however, the values of these parameters were
applied to both groups (SMS <italic>versus</italic> control), thus not affecting the
relative effectiveness of the model. Second, the parameters of this study were
derived from a 6-month intervention, which may have diluted the effect of the SMS
intervention in the population context over time, just as with each year of planned
intervention there is an increase in data uncertainty. However, these limitations do
not preclude the results presented since, in the first year after the intervention,
positive results are already obtained.</p><p>The results presented in this study demonstrate an advance in knowledge through the
use of an RCT associated with a dynamic cohort model with Markov states, of the
long-term evolution of interventions in patients with HIV, demonstrating its impact
on transmissibility, mortality, and costs. Therefore, this study may subsidize
complementary health actions through other technologies of communication with the
patient which contribute to the increase of adherence in patients on ART and to a
consequent reduction of transmissibility, as well as allowing for its replication in
different contexts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The analysis of this dynamic cohort reflects that, when implemented at the population
level, weekly sending SMS to people infected with HIV and on ART can reduce the
circulating viral load and lead to a consequent reduction of new infections, in
addition to the reduction of direct costs related to treatment in health.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>Supported by Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (CAPES)
&#x02013; Grant # 408709/2016-2, Brazil.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahagirdar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Biehl</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Douwes-Schultz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and
mortality of HIV, 1980-2017, and forecasts to 2030, for 195 countries and
territories: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Diseases,
Injuries, and Risk Factors Study 2017</article-title><source>Lancet HIV</source><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Feb 1, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e831</fpage><lpage>e859</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(19)30196-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31439534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo-Mancilla</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Haberer</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherence Measurements in HIV: New Advancements in Pharmacologic
Methods and Real-Time Monitoring</article-title><source>Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 7,2019</date-in-citation><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11904-018-0377-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29380227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altice</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Evuarherhe</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Shina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaubrun</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherence to HIV treatment regimens: systematic literature review
and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Patient Prefer Adherence</source><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Feb 2, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>13</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/PPA.S192735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31040651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Detsis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsioutis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Karageorgos</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sideroglou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatzakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylonakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors Associated with HIV Testing and HIV Treatment Adherence:
A Systematic Review</article-title><source>Curr Pharm Des</source><year>2017</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 7, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>23</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>2568</fpage><lpage>2578</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1381612823666170329125820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28356038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzaken</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>GFM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanuri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiretroviral treatment, government policy and economy of
HIV/AIDS in Brazil: is it time for HIV cure in the country?</article-title><source>AIDS Res Ther</source><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Feb 1, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12981-019-0234-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31412889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frasca</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Atlani-Duault</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decentralisation of Brazil's HIV/AIDS programme: intended and
unintended consequences</article-title><source>Glob Public Health</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 7, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>13</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1725</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17441692.2018.1455888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29582707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello Padoin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost-Effective Analysis to Incorporate Non-Drug Interventions to
Increase Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy</article-title><source>Value Health Reg Issues</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 5, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>17</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vhri.2018.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29529587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvao</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Information and communication technologies for adherence to
antiretroviral treatment in adults with HIV/AIDS</article-title><source>Int J Med Inform</source><year>2016</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 3, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>92</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2016.04.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27318071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shubber</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nachega</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vreeman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient-Reported Barriers to Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy:
A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2016</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Jan 31, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e1002183</elocation-id><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1002183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27898679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enane</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vreeman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retention and adherence: global challenges for the long-term care
of adolescents and young adults living with HIV</article-title><source>Curr Opin HIV AIDS</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Oct 27, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/COH.0000000000000459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29570471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaitses Fontanari</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanella</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Feijo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues Lobato</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV-related care for transgender people: A systematic review of
studies from around the world</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Jan 31, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>230</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2019.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31035207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>With HIV: Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title><source>JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</source><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Feb 3, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e14404</elocation-id><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/14404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31621641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitzel</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanable</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Necessity and concerns beliefs and HIV medication adherence: a
systematic review</article-title><source>J Behav Med</source><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Feb 4, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10865-019-00089-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanters</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Socias</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interventions to improve adherence to antiretroviral therapy: a
systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet HIV</source><year>2017</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 3, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e31-e40</elocation-id><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(16)30206-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27863996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Molina</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Blasco</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arribas</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Domingo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Iribarren</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the costs and cost-effectiveness of the guidelines
recommended by the 2018 GESIDA/Spanish National AIDS Plan for initial
antiretroviral therapy in HIV-infected adults</article-title><source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin</source><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Feb 3, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eimc.2018.04.010">https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.eimc.2018.04.010</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29884455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haeussler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>den Hout</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Baio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A dynamic Bayesian Markov model for health economic evaluations
of interventions in infectious disease</article-title><source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Dec 3, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12874-018-0541-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30068316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Husereau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carswell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards
(CHEERS) statement</article-title><source>Value Health</source><year>2013</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 8, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2013.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Uccellini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating mobile phone applications for health behaviour change:
A systematic review</article-title><source>J Telemed Telecare</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 8, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1357633X16673538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27760883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christopoulos</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Tulsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrico</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A text messaging intervention to improve retention in care and
virologic suppression in a U.S. urban safety-net HIV clinic: study protocol
for the Connect4Care (C4C) randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 7, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>14</volume><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-014-0718-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25551175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komninakis</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Late Presentation HIV/AIDS Is Still a Challenge in Brazil and
Worldwide</article-title><source>AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/AID.2015.0379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28797184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bavinton</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Phanuphak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinsztejn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Prestage</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zablotska-Manos</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Viral suppression and HIV transmission in serodiscordant male
couples: an international, prospective, observational, cohort
study</article-title><source>Lancet HIV</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>5</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e438-e47</elocation-id><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(18)30132-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30025681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Germanaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Derache</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Traore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Toure</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicko</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Level of viral load and antiretroviral resistance after 6 months
of non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor first-line treatment in
HIV-1-infected children in Mali</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2010</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>65</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkp412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19933171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LeMessurier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Traversy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Varsaneux</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Weekes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Avey</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Niragira</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk of sexual transmission of human immunodeficiency virus with
antiretroviral therapy, suppressed viral load and condom use: a systematic
review</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 27, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>190</volume><issue>46</issue><fpage>e1350</fpage><lpage>e1e60</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.180311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30455270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mujugira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Celum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndase</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HIV Transmission Risk Persists During the First 6 Months of
Antiretroviral Therapy</article-title><source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source><year>2016</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 19, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>72</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAI.0000000000001019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27070123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baggaley</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambiano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of screening for HIV in primary care: a health
economics modelling analysis</article-title><source>Lancet HIV</source><year>2017</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>4</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e465</fpage><lpage>ee74</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(17)30123-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Bruin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberje</surname><given-names>EJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Viechtbauer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobel</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiligsmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Nieuwkoop</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of a nurse-delivered
intervention to improve adherence to treatment for HIV: a pragmatic,
multicentre, open-label, randomised clinical trial</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Sep 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(16)30534-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28262598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walensky</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling and Cost-Effectiveness in HIV Prevention</article-title><source>Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</source><year>2016</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Jan 27, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11904-016-0303-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26830283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nucifora</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>McNairy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Gachuhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of a combination strategy to enhance the HIV
care continuum in Swaziland: Link4Health</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Sep 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e0204245</elocation-id><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0204245">https://doi.org/ 10.1371/journal.pone.0204245</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30222768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canan</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Waselewski</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>ALD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Flickinger</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long term impact of PositiveLinks: Clinic-deployed mobile
technology to improve engagement with HIV care</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Feb 6, 2020</date-in-citation><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e0226870</elocation-id><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0226870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31905209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon-Tuval</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of adherence-enhancing interventions: a
systematic review</article-title><source>Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res</source><year>2016</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14737167.2016.1138858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26732615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Braithwaite</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nucifora</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thirumurthy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Economic evaluation of mobile phone text message interventions to
improve adherence to HIV therapy in Kenya</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2017</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Aug 20, 2019</date-in-citation><volume>96</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e6078</elocation-id><comment>Available from: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000006078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28207516</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>