<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">The main benefit of a public holiday for outbreak control in and of itself is thus that it buys time to develop effective responses that are not immediately available. First, a country can use the time of halted epidemic spread during an outbreak-control holiday to build critical infrastructure for further epidemic control measures, such as emergency field hospitals. Second, the time allows a country to organize medical supplies for the screening, diagnosis, and treatment of COVID-19 patients and to train and deploy specialized human resources for the long-term epidemic response, including hospitalists and infection-control specialists. Finally, the time can be used for scientific discovery and knowledge gain, which is important for designing the most effective and efficient epidemic response for the longer term 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. During the outbreak-control holiday in China, substantial progress was made toward the characterization and identification of COVID-19 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, the origin and transmission routes of the virus 
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, the epidemiological pattern of the epidemic 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, and potential treatment approaches 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. At the same time, however, our knowledge of COVID-19 transmission routes remains imperfect, and specific antiviral treatment and vaccines are not yet available 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>.
</p>
