<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Patient trajectories began with time from onset to admission: some patients progressed rapidly and required hospitalization in the week after the onset of symptoms (quick progressors), while others arrived at the hospital after a longer time since the onset of symptoms (slow progressors). Bimodal distributions in trajectories of COVID-19 patients have already been reported; in an early case series, an old patient died rapidly after disease onset, and two young men had worsening 10 days after onset [
 <xref rid="B4-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. A case series from New York also reported a bimodal distribution from disease onset to intubation in the first few days, then around 9 days [
 <xref rid="B5-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. We found that this bimodal distribution is informed by age: young individuals were on average hospitalized later than older patients. It has been proposed that COVID-19 causes an early disease due to the acute viral infection, and a later disease related to the inflammatory reaction. This later phase of clinical worsening leads to increased disease severity [
 <xref rid="B6-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Along with this description, older patients may be more prone to the first type of disease and younger patients to the second type. However, it is also possible that the disease is recognized later in the old, because of the typical low symptomatology and non-prodromal nature of viral infections in the elderly [
 <xref rid="B8-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Furthermore, atypical symptoms have been described in the elderly that may complicate the initial diagnosis of COVID-19. Thus, especially in the elderly, a shorter duration between the onset and admission to hospital/ICU could be related to a measurement bias. From a practical point of view, short duration from the onset should be considered as an additional risk factor in hospitalized patients. Reinforced clinical vigilance in the elderly is required as soon as the first symptoms appear in order to plan hospitalization as soon as possible to allow optimal treatment. Although no etiological treatment for COVID-19 has been discovered, treatments such as anticoagulation or corticosteroids can improve the outcome of patients [
 <xref rid="B9-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Starting these therapies as early as possible could further reduce mortality.
</p>
