<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A recent systematic review evaluating the length of stay (LOS) in hospital and/or ICU for patients with COVID-19 showed wide variation in the average LOS, ranging from 4 to 53 days depending on country, admission criteria, and timing of the pandemic [
 <xref rid="B16-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Yet, most surveys included in this review concerned small number of subjects who were hospitalized during the first month of the epidemic and did not account for censoring. Here, we had little censoring (5%) and used dedicated statistical procedures. We found that the length of stay in the hospital was highly variable, depending on age and wards (ICU or not). In most cases, an extended period of stay was found in the young patients, especially in those with poor outcomes. The durations of ICU stays were long in the young patients compared to other pulmonary diseases requiring intensive care. For example, the median LOS in ICU for all-cause acute respiratory distress syndrome was 18 days in a recent trial, while it was 32 days in the younger age group in our study [
 <xref rid="B17-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The extent of initial lung damage may contribute to this extended duration, but also to the high frequency of the need for another organ-supportive care, such as dialysis [
 <xref rid="B18-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The lack of downstream beds for the management of COVID-19 patients requiring extensive post-intensive care is also a possibility that may explain the long duration of hospitalization in ICU for surviving patients. Managing healthcare capacity is of prime importance during a health disaster. While most research focused on ICU and conventional units [
 <xref rid="B19-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], the place of downstream beds and rehabilitation units need more assessment [
 <xref rid="B20-jcm-09-03148" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. We acknowledge that the choice of a log-normal distribution and the small number of young patients who died led to more uncertainty in the duration estimations. However, the sensitivity analysis using shorter tailed distribution was consistent with our main analysis.
</p>
