<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">We analyzed all available diagnoses of respiratory viruses, including SARS-CoV-2, performed between September 2013 and May 2020 at the clinical microbiology and virology laboratory of the University Hospital Institute Méditerranée Infection (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mediterranee-infection.com/" id="intr0015" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.mediterranee-infection.com/</ext-link>) and the University Hospitals of Marseille, the second-largest French city, southeastern France. Testing of respiratory samples was performed using the FTD Respiratory pathogens 21 (Fast Track Diagnosis, Luxembourg), the Biofire FilmArray Respiratory panel 2 plus (Biomérieux, Marcy-l'Etoile, France), the Respiratory Multi-Well System r-gene (Argene, BioMérieux), or the GeneXpert Xpert Flu/RSV (Cepheid, Sunnyvale, CA) assays, or by one-step simplex real-time quantitative RT-PCR amplifications as previously reported (
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Hoang et al., 2019</xref>). Diagnosis by reverse transcription-PCR of SARS-CoV-2 infection was performed as previously described (
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Amrane et al., 2020</xref>). This study retrospectively analyzed patients' data from the hospital information system (RGPD/APHM 2019-73). Statistics were performed using OpenEpi version 3.01 software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.openepi.com/Menu/OE_Menu.htm" id="intr0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.openepi.com/Menu/OE_Menu.htm</ext-link>); a p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. Moreover, epidemic curves were analyzed by Markov Chain Monte Carlo fitting of five commonly used distributions with different skewnesses (Normal, Log-normal, Gamma, Weibull, Gompertz) using R-4.0.1 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/" id="intr0025" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>). Distributions with the best goodness-of-fit criteria [Akaike's Information Criterion, (AIC)] were chosen, and their parameters bootstrapped.
</p>
