<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Gao Group reported 3 patients with pneumonia of unknown cause found in the first time, with clinical manifestations of fever and cough with chest discomfort.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]
 </sup> Huang et al,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]
 </sup> reported the clinical features of the first 41 patients diagnosed with COVID-19, with infectious symptoms including fever, cough, and generalized weakness, but their upper respiratory symptoms were not prominent; however, gastrointestinal symptoms such as diarrhea, which are common in SARS-CoV infected patients, were not significant in COVID-19 patients. Chen et al,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]
 </sup> retrospectively analyzed the clinical manifestations of 99 patients with COVID-19 and found that among 99 patients, fever and cough accounted for &gt;50% of the total patients, shortness of breath accounted for 31%, muscle pain for 11%, and there were also few patients with confusion, headache, sore throat, runny nose, chest pain, diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting (Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). As we can see above, common symptoms are fever, cough, dyspnea, and fatigue, which may be accompanied by upper respiratory tract symptoms. COVID-19 Quick Advice for Diagnosis and Treatment Guidelines (standard version) points out fever as a typical symptom. It should be noted that patients with mild disease may have no positive symptoms and signs, and some ill and critically ill patients may have moderate to low fever or even no significant fever. Gastrointestinal symptoms may exist as the first manifestation of the virus due to the expression of ACE2 in the intestine
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]
 </sup>; cough with nausea, vomiting, and abnormal stools was reported in the first diagnosed patient in the United States.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]
 </sup>
</p>
