<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While many international studies have shown promising results along the HIV care continuum for iART, others have had uneven results. A recent meta-analysis, for example, highlighted an increase in loss to follow-up in some cases [
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In South Africa and Kenya, Rosen et al. conducted a study in which they randomized newly diagnosed patients with HIV to an intervention called SLATE (Simplified Algorithm for Treatment Eligibility), which involved conducting a patient history, a physical exam, and a readiness assessment for same-day initiation versus usual care [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The SLATE intervention increased ART uptake at 1 month, however, there was no effect on retention in care at 8 months in either South Africa or Kenya [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A more recent observational study from France showed that newly diagnosed patients starting ART less than 9 days after HIV diagnosis had higher loss to follow-up at 1 year than those who had started ART greater than 90 days after HIV diagnosis [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The authors pointed to a need to understand the “social and life context” of the population with increased loss to follow-up, surmising that issues of migration and stigmatization among immigrants from sub-Saharan Africa in France may have contributed to poor outcomes [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Yet another recent prospective cohort study from South Africa showed that patients initiated on same-day ART had an increased risk of loss to follow-up compared to those initiating &gt;1 day [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. These data point to lack of current consensus in the literature regarding iART’s impact on long-term outcomes. There is debate whether even measuring the impact of iART on long-term outcomes is warranted, given that the same barriers to viral suppression and retention in care likely exist for patients regardless of iART. However, a patient’s initial experience after diagnosis, the immediate offer of treatment, and the introduction into the HIV clinical care setting likely does have some impact on long-term engagement [
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-17-07345" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This points to the need for a mindful approach in the implementation and rollout of iART, despite the consensus among international clinical care guidelines. 
</p>
