<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">SARS and MERS coronaviruses are both capable of infecting human monocyte-derived macrophages and dendritic cells; however, with SARS, in vitro infections are abortive and do not support production of virions, whereas with MERS, productive infections and rising viral titers are seen (Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2015</xref>; Cheung et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2005</xref>; Tseng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2005</xref>). In vitro, different characteristics of monocyte-derived cell infection are associated with differences in the pattern of immune response and cytokine elaboration (Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2015</xref>; Perlman and Dandekar 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2005</xref>; Law et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2005</xref>). Whether these differences have nervous system relevance is unclear (Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2015</xref>; Cameron et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2008</xref>). SARS and MERS also directly infect T lymphocytes (Perlman and Dandekar 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2005</xref>; Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2015</xref>). In tissue samples of individuals with SARS-CoV, virions, viral proteins, and nucleic acids have been identified in macrophages, T lymphocytes, granulocytes, and, to lesser degrees, B lymphocytes and NK cells (Gu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2005</xref>; Shi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2005</xref>; Nicholls et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2006</xref>). In contrast, a single autopsy report of an individual dying with MERS-CoV failed to demonstrate viral antigen in pulmonary macrophages despite detection in pneumocytes (Ng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2016</xref>). Finally, non-epidemic HCoVs are also capable of infecting human monocyte/macrophages in vitro, with variable abilities to replicate (Desforges et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>; Cheung et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2005</xref>). Thus, regardless of systemic pathogenicity, for human coronaviruses, immune cell trafficking is a potential mechanism for establishing CNS disease.
</p>
