<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Cell tropism is an essential aspect of establishing CNS disease and, for coronaviruses, the S protein dominates this characteristic (albeit not exclusively, as demonstrated by the HE protein). It is the major cell surface binding molecule, responsible for membrane fusion and viral genome entry into the cell. The S protein is a homotrimer, with each of its polypeptides containing a large, bipartite ectodomain: S1, which is highly variable and mediates receptor binding, and S2, which is more conserved and functions in membrane fusion between virus and host cell (Perlman and Masters 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2020</xref>). Virus entry into the cell occurs either in an “early” pathway of direct fusion between viral envelope and the cell membrane or a “late” pathway in which receptor binding leads to endocytosis in clathrin-coated pits, which then transition to acidified endosomes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Proteolytic priming of the S protein is an essential step in the viral life cycle, both at cell entry and upon maturation and egress; large conformational changes on cell entry are needed to expose the S2 fusion peptide. This occurs through two cleavages, at the boundary of S1/S2 and at a second S2’ site. Thus, cell entry requires not only S protein binding to its cognate receptor but also exposure to a cellular protease for priming, either in the context of the cell membrane or the endosome. While cathepsins provide this proteolytic processing in the endosome, a variety of proteases may be active at the cell surface. The cell surface serine protease TMPRSS2 can provide priming function for all human coronaviruses, and there is evidence to suggest that wild type viruses prefer the TMPRSS2-mediated cell surface pathway to cathepsin-mediated endosomal pathways of cell entry (Shirato et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2018</xref>; Kleine-Weber et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2018</xref>; Hoffmann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2020</xref>). TMPRSS2 is not expressed in human brain, and it is unclear what impact this absence might have on neurotropism (Jacquinet et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2001</xref>). Of interest, SARS-CoV-2 has acquired a polybasic site at the S1–S2 junction that allows for effective cleavage by furin, an endoprotease abundantly expressed in CNS, located on cell membranes, in endosomes, and also cleaved and secreted (Andersen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2020</xref>; Thomas 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2002</xref>; Braun and Sauter 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>).
</p>
