<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">The importance of cell receptor expression to neuropathogenesis is demonstrated by transgenic animal models. Mice can be infected with SARS-CoV and support viral replication, but generally fail to develop the severe disease seen in humans. When mice are made transgenic for human ACE2 (hACE2), their disease becomes lethal, characterized by severe pulmonary and extra-pulmonary infection, including the brain (McCray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2007</xref>). When hACE2 transgenic mice are inoculated intranasally with SARS-CoV, virus spreads through the olfactory bulbs into the brain and then rapidly disseminates via trans-neuronal pathways, with viral protein detected in brain regions with first- and second-order connections to the olfactory system (McCray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2007</xref>). Neuronal infection is subsequently followed by neuronal loss (McCray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2007</xref>; Netland et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2008</xref>). This model is remarkable in that expression of the transgene is very low in brain, contrasting with the extensive neuronal infection (McCray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2007</xref>). Furthermore, the model does not demonstrate a cellular immune response—that is, inflammatory cell infiltration/meningoencephalitis does not develop (Netland et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2008</xref>). A similar model featuring brain infection has been created for MERS-CoV, with mice transgenic for human DPP4 (hDPP4) (Li et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2016a</xref>). In contrast to mouse models of SARS, hDPP4 transgenics have high levels of receptor expression in brain and, when inoculated intranasally with MERS-CoV, show viropathic effects in neurons with most significant early damage in regions unrelated to olfaction; these mice also demonstrate perivascular inflammatory cell infiltrates (Li et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2016a</xref>). Both SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV transgenic mouse models highlight the importance of receptor expression to neuropathogenesis, raising the important question of whether HCoV receptors are found in human brain.
</p>
