<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">While present on pulmonary, nasopharyngeal, and gastrointestinal epithelia, the ACE2 protein was not described in human brain parenchyma in the single publication documenting its distribution (Hamming et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2004</xref>). However, ACE2 was demonstrated in brain vascular (arterial and venous) endothelia and smooth muscle, as well as systemic vasculature (Hamming et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2004</xref>). In human heart, vascular pericytes demonstrate abundant ACE2 expression (Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2020</xref>). While reports of brain parenchymal ACE2 are often cited in the literature, none have entailed analysis of human tissue. Neuronal cytoplasmic ACE2 has been described in a rabbit model of heart failure and in a transgenic mouse model of hypertension with human renin and angiotensin transgenes, with no explanation regarding its cytosolic localization (Kar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2010</xref>; Doobay et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2007</xref>). In a study of ontogeny, ACE2 immunoreactivity was detected in mouse ependyma at E18.5, with no mention of neuronal staining (Song et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2012</xref>). ACE2 activity and mRNA have been detected in mouse and rat brain tissues without cellular localization, and cultured rat astrocytes can express ACE2 mRNA and protein (Sakima et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2005</xref>; Gallagher et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2006</xref>; Elased et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2008</xref>). Thus, it remains an open question whether ACE2 is sufficiently expressed and can act as a SARS receptor in non-vascular human brain parenchyma, both under normal conditions and in disease states known to regulate ACE2 expression and/or activity, such as diabetes and hypertension (Batlle et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>; South et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">2020</xref>).
</p>
