<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Lancet. Gastroenterology &#x00026; Hepatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2468-1253</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7498470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2468-1253(20)30305-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(20)30305-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on viral hepatitis services in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>Maud</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au20"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jin Un</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au30"><name><surname>Ndow</surname><given-names>Gibril</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au40"><name><surname>Bah</surname><given-names>Sulayman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au50"><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au60"><name><surname>Rwegasha</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au70"><name><surname>Bouyou</surname><given-names>Marielle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au80"><name><surname>Napon</surname><given-names>Delphine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au90"><name><surname>Somda</surname><given-names>Sosthene</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au100"><name><surname>Sawadogo</surname><given-names>Appolinaire</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au110"><name><surname>Sombie</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au120"><name><surname>Shimakawa</surname><given-names>Yusuke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Metabolism, Digestion and Reproduction, Section of Hepatology and Gastroenterology, Imperial College London, St Mary's Hospital, London W2 1NY, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Medical Research Council Unit, The Gambia at London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, Fajara, The Gambia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Hepatology and Gastroenterology, Muhimbili National Hospital, Dar es-Salaam, Tanzania</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Parasitology, Mycology and Tropical Medicine, Universit&#x000e9; des Sciences de la Sant&#x000e9;, Libreville, Gabon</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>D&#x000e9;partement de M&#x000e9;dicine, CHU Bodogodo, Ouagadougou, Burkina Faso</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>D&#x000e9;partement d'H&#x000e9;pato-gastroent&#x000e9;rologie, CHU Yalgado Ou&#x000e9;draogo, Ouagadougou, Burkina Faso</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>D&#x000e9;partement de M&#x000e9;dicine, CHU Souro Sanou, Bobo-Dioulasso, Burkina Faso</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Unit&#x000e9; d'&#x000c9;pid&#x000e9;miologie des Maladies &#x000c9;mergentes, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>966</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">The global response to limit the spread of COVID-19 has diverted attention and resources from existing local health priorities, particularly in countries of low and middle income (LMICs).<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> As highlighted in a Comment in <italic>The Lancet Gastroenterology &#x00026; Hepatology</italic> by Neil Gupta and colleagues,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> the collateral damage on efforts to address the viral hepatitis epidemic in sub-Saharan Africa is of high concern. However, the potential effect of COVID-19 on viral hepatitis services has been poorly documented.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para20">We have recorded a striking decrease in use of outpatient services by patients with chronic hepatitis in three countries in sub-Saharan Africa. We retrospectively counted the number of new and known cases of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection seen at the main referral hospitals in Burkina Faso (Yalgado-Ou&#x000e9;draogo Hospital and Bodogodo Hospital, Ouagadoudou; and Souro-Sanou Hospital, Bobo-Dioulasso), Tanzania (Muhimbili National Hospital, Dar es-Salam), and The Gambia (Medical Research Council Clinical Services, Fajara) from Jan 1 to April 30, 2020, a period covering the time before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. We also asked a doctor in charge of hepatitis services at each centre about the type of clinical and laboratory services that were disrupted, and plausible reasons for such disruption, using a standardised questionnaire (<xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix pp 1&#x02013;3</xref>).</p><p id="para30">The number of patients reviewed monthly at the hepatitis clinics fell substantially from January to April, 2020, by 71% in Burkina Faso, 95% in Tanzania, and 83% in The Gambia for new cases, and by 73% in Burkina Faso, 77% in Tanzania, and 89% in The Gambia for patients in follow-up (<xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix p 4</xref>). To exclude any annual seasonal effects, we compared the number of viral hepatitis cases (new patients and patients in follow-up) in 2020 against those seen during the same period last year (Jan 1 to April 30, 2019) in The Gambia and found no significant fluctuation in cases (data not shown).</p><p id="para40">Across these countries, doctors consistently cited the patient's fear of contracting severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 at clinics as a primary reason for the drop in patient numbers. The decrease in number of outpatient visits seems to have started in February, 2020, preceding confirmation of the first COVID-19 cases in these countries (from the second to third week of March, 2020) and implementation of public health measures limiting social contacts by the respective governments (in March and April, 2020). In Burkina Faso, the number of patients regularly monitored for chronic viral hepatitis steadily fell over this period, even though clinics were maintained and treating doctors encouraged patients to be retained in care. By contrast, in Tanzania and The Gambia, hepatitis clinics were temporarily closed at the end of March, 2020, to prepare for the COVID-19 epidemic, and staff at hepatitis services were relocated to support COVID-19 preparedness, to receive patients who were febrile with a suspicion of COVID-19, and to mitigate COVID-19 outbreaks. Of the essential diagnostic tests to manage chronic hepatitis, rapid tests for HBsAg, alanine aminotransferase, and haematology were available without any disruption throughout this period in these countries. However, there was a severe shortage of nucleic acid tests for HBV DNA or HCV RNA. Moreover, in Burkina Faso, direct-acting antivirals for HCV were temporarily unavailable because of disrupted supply secondary to suspension of international flights. Nevertheless, during this period, none of the doctors surveyed witnessed a health-care system collapse attributable to overwhelming demand for COVID-19 care.</p><p id="para50">The disrupted use of viral hepatitis services in sub-Saharan Africa might have a long-term clinical effect: people newly identified as having HBsAg or anti-HCV antibody could have lost their opportunity to be linked to care, assessed for viral load, and eventually treated, and those who had been receiving antiviral therapy might have had their treatment interrupted. Moreover, in the three countries we investigated, the relative reduction in outpatient visits was substantial (&#x0003e;70%) when comparing the period just before the COVID-19 pandemic (January, 2020) with a period during the pandemic (April, 2020). This decline was far more pronounced than was the reduction in use of routine health-care services recorded during the 2014 Ebola outbreak in west Africa (mean reduction 18&#x000b7;0%, 95% CI 9&#x000b7;5&#x02013;26&#x000b7;5).<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> An economic analysis showed that the indirect effect of the 2014 Ebola outbreak on deaths from non-Ebola causes was greater than its direct effect on Ebola-related deaths,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> indicating the importance of maintaining routine health services in LMICs.</p><p id="para60">Efforts to address viral hepatitis in sub-Saharan Africa have been remarkable in recent years. The growing availability of simple point-of-care tests and antiviral therapies at low cost make elimination of viral hepatitis a realistic goal in LMICs, as set out in a <italic>Lancet Gastroenterology &#x00026; Hepatology</italic> Commission.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Yet, these encouraging prospects also need to be balanced by the reminder that a large proportion of these viral hepatitis services are not supported by national programmes in most LMICs and, in the midst of further resource limitation, remain incredibly fragile. The COVID-19 pandemic vividly highlights this fragility and the urgent need for innovative and sustainable hepatitis programmes in sub-Saharan Africa. In the face of the COVID-19 pandemic, viral hepatitis services are at great risk of being neglected.</p></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early estimates of the indirect effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on maternal and child mortality in low-income and middle-income countries: a modelling study</article-title><source>Lancet Glob Health</source><volume>8</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e901</fpage><lpage>e908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32405459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Desalegn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ocama</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Converging pandemics: implications of COVID-19 for the viral hepatitis response in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>5</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32553140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Helleringer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of non-Ebola health care services during Ebola outbreaks: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Glob Health</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">010406</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Finelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The economic and social burden of the 2014 Ebola outbreak in west Africa</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>218</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>S698</fpage><lpage>S704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30321368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrieux-Meyer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Applegate</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerating the elimination of viral hepatitis: a <italic>Lancet Gastroenterology &#x00026; Hepatology</italic> Commission</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>4</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30647010</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p id="para80">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecomp10"><caption><title>Supplementary appendix</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack><p>ML has received consultancy fees and research funding from Gilead. GN holds a Gilead public health award fellowship. YS and RS have received consultancy fees from Gilead. All other authors report no competing interests.</p></ack></back></article>