<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Mammalian coronaviruses have well-documented ability to damage the central nervous system (CNS), and most recently, concerns have been raised that severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) may be neuroinvasive. Neurologic manifestations in up to 84% of patients hospitalized with COVID-19 have been described in series from China and France (Mao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>; Helms et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2020</xref>). Symptoms related to olfactory dysfunction have been interpreted as evidence of CNS involvement (Eliezer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2020</xref>). There has been speculation that CNS infection contributes to respiratory failure in COVID-19 disease, similar to the “Ondine’s curse” of bulbar polio, in which virally mediated damage to brainstem autonomic centers causes alveolar hypoventilation during sleep, when volitional control of breath is absent (Li et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2020</xref>; Baig et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). Opposite interpretations of these phenomena have been expressed. It has been noted that patients with COVID-19 pulmonary disease display hypoxia-driven, type 1 respiratory rate increases, and not decreased respiratory rates indicative of centrally mediated type 2 failure (Turtle 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">2020</xref>; Young et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">2020</xref>). Olfactory abnormalities have been considered a reflection of peripheral nasopharyngeal, and not CNS, dysfunction (Mao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). Encephalopathy with the severe respiratory, metabolic, and immunologic derangements of critical illness, and not viral neuroinvasion, may account for non-focal neurologic manifestations (Pleasure et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2020</xref>). These issues of interpretation make it appropriate to address the following question: are concerns about the potential neurotropism and neurovirulence of SARS-CoV-2 warranted? To answer this question, it would seem helpful to examine the evidence for nervous system involvement by coronaviruses in general, both in man, and with the supporting evidence of animal models that are relevant to neuropathogenesis. Accordingly, this review will cover aspects of basic coronavirus biology relevant to nervous system disorders; the types of neurologic syndromes that have been observed in man; the evidence for virally mediated human neuropathogenesis, whether by direct CNS involvement, or indirect immunologic and vascular mechanisms; and when pertinent, how our understanding of coronavirus neuropathogenesis in animals is relevant to human disease.
</p>
