<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A 31-year-old man presented himself at the Emergency room (ER) of a hospital with myalgia and headache. He had no other symptoms and was not suffering from any chronic disease. His temperature as recorded was 39°C. A nasopharyngeal swab was taken before he was given paracetamol and sent home. The next day, he called the Ministry of Health (MOH) helpline number (937) to seek advice, as he was feeling unwell. He was advised to isolate himself until the laboratory results were available. Subsequently, the MOH staff called him to inform that his RT-PCR test for SARS CoV-2 was positive. Within hours, the MOH staff reached his house. They advised him to stay isolated, As his home was suitable for quarantine/self-isolation, they advised him to stay isolated in a separate room with an attached washroom. The patient did not develop any symptom. Three days after the onset of first symptoms, the patient felt better and stopped taking paracetamol. Unfortunately, he broke isolation and returned to his normal life, living and interacting with his family. Five days later, everyone else at the home (his wife, one daughter, two sons, and a housemaid) developed unusual symptoms. The clinical characteristics of the patients are summarized in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The man called the MOH staff, who attended and took nasopharyngeal swabs of all five household members. MOH contacted the family and informed them that they were all positive for the virus. The man called the MOH, stating that he felt very well, and requested for a nasopharyngeal swab to be taken. MOH staff attended and took his swab. The next day, they called to inform him that he was negative for CoV-2. The following day, the MOH staff took another swab. Again, the result was negative. The man stayed at home with his family without isolation for another week. At the end of the week, swabs were again taken from all the members of the household, including the original patient. All the results were negative (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).
</p>
