<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ASFV attenuated by continuous subculture can induce protective immune response against parental strains. In 1960s, the attenuated strain was widely used in Spain and Portugal, but it was abandoned due to the chronic infection symptoms of ASF, which extensively appeared in vaccinated pigs. Nevertheless, The ASFV Georgia strain, which were fully attenuated after 110 consecutive passages by Vero cells, cannot resist the attack of the parental ASFV Georgia virulence after immunizing pigs, and may not produce an effective immune response due to the change of its antigen during passage [
 <xref rid="B46-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In the follow-up study, pigs inoculated with a naturally-attenuated strain NH/P68 of ASFV were resistant to the virulent strain ASFV L60, with the activity of NK cells increased, indicating that NK cells activity is positively correlated with the protective immunity of ASFV [
 <xref rid="B47-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Moreover, vaccination with the naturally attenuated strain OURT88/3 could induce cross-protective immunity against attacks by non-homologous ASFV virulent strains, which is associated with the IFN-γ-secreting ability of lymphocytes in vaccinated pigs [
 <xref rid="B48-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. However, pigs vaccinated with naturally-attenuated ASF vaccines generally have many serious side effects, such as fever, abortion, and chronic or persistent infections [
 <xref rid="B49-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In addition, there are also safety issues with virulence reversion. In the latest study in May 2020, an attempt was made to increase the safety of the naturally attenuated strain OURT88/3 by deleting I329L, a gene previously shown to inhibit the innate immune response of the host. Unexpectedly, the OURT88/3∆I329L strain significantly reduced protection against virulent stains OURT 88/1 attacks [
 <xref rid="B50-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. To date, the hinge to immune protection of naturally LAVs still needs to be further elucidated. For the current circumstances of ASF in China, the use of conventional LAVs should be cautious or forbidden. If there are no matching technologies and products of differentiating infected from vaccinated animals (DIVA), it is largely unfavorable for the eradication of ASFV in China.
</p>
