<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There has been some understanding of SARS-COV-2, a novel coronavirus, whose epidemiology is not yet fully understood and requires further investigation. Typical symptoms after infection are fever, fatigue, cough, dyspnea, etc., and atypical symptoms may be the first manifestation. Close monitoring of inflammatory markers during treatment avoids excessive inflammatory response. Typical chest CT findings are subpleural or peripheral ground-glass opacities or fainting signs, mostly with bronchial ventilation signs. Its imaging findings change rapidly, and the lesions can increase or decrease in a short time, so the interval between reexaminations should be shorter than that of common pneumonia, and reexamination in 2 to 3 days is recommended in the early stage (when the lesions are unstable). With the gradual increase of confirmed and suspected cases, the lag of nucleic acid detection and the lack of medical resources, whether to use CT instead of nucleic acid detection to diagnose COVID-19, has become a topic of discussion. It should be clear that during the outbreak, when nucleic acid detection is negative, it still needs to be comprehensively evaluated according to the clinical manifestations of patients, relevant examinations and the experience of doctors to avoid missing suspected patients, and causing the spread of the range. Timely and effective therapeutic measures are particularly necessary. At present, there is no specific vaccine and antiviral drug. It is hoped that more effective drugs can be screened on the basis of exerting known drug efficacy, and vaccines and specific drugs can be developed as soon as possible. Timely use of immunoglobulin and antibacterial drugs, rational use of glucocorticoids, and at the same time, psychotherapy should not be forgotten. At present, there are many problems to be discovered and solved urgently for COVID-19. We must recognize that COVID-19 brings great challenges to mankind, and it is urgent to understand and control the epidemic situation.</p>
