<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0215">
 <italic>In vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> antiviral activity of prochlorperazine towards the Dengue virus (DENV) was analyzed by 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Simanjuntak et al. (2015)</xref>. The cytotoxicity analysis in human kidney (HEK293T), lung (A549), microglia (CHME3), monocytic (THP-1) cells, and mouse neuroblastoma (N18) cells showed that prochlorperazine in the concentration up to 30 μM did not influence significantly cell viability, cell proliferation, or cytotoxicity. The drug inhibits protein expression and viral progeny in HEK293T DENV-2 infected cells, with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 88 nM. Moreover, the drug inhibits the replication of the Dengue virus serotype 2 (DENV-2) at noncytotoxic doses (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 137 nM) in a dose-dependent manner. The drug inhibits also infection of DENV-1, DENV-2, and Japanese encephalitis virus. The authors showed that the drug blocks DENV entry through clathrin-mediated endocytosis. DENV-2 was located with clathrin on the cell membrane without cell penetration after prochlorperazine treatment (30 min, 20, and 30 μM) (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Simanjuntak et al., 2015</xref>). Interestingly, the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> experiment performed by the Authors, using the Stat1
 <sup>−/−</sup> mice challenged with DENV-2, showed that prochlorperazine dimaleate in the concentration of 5 mg/kg body weight/day protected the animals against death caused by DENV-2. Interestingly, 90% of vehicle control mice died, while the drug in the concentration of 1 mg drug/kg body weight/day only delayed animal mortality. Noteworthy, the authors admit that it is possible to reach the equivalent of 5 mg/kg body weight/day for mice in human (0.405 mg/kg/day). Thus, the dose for a 60-kg person would be 24.3 mg/day, what is in line with the clinical dose of prochlorperazine dimaleate recommended to prevent nausea and vomiting (5–10 mg/dose, 2–3 times daily) as well as for treating nausea and vomiting (20 mg followed by 10 mg 2 h later if required) However, detailed pharmacokinetic studies and antiviral tests in humans are still required (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Simanjuntak et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
