<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although specific anti-SARS-CoV-2 drugs are currently unavailable, most of our patients received general antiviral agents on the first day of hospitalization. Median time to viral conversion from initiation of antiviral treatments (or admission) using pharyngeal swab, urine, faeces, and blood were 2, 2, 4, and 9 days, respectively. From disease onset to viral conversion, the median duration was 8, 8, 10, and 14 days, respectively. In contrast, the median onset-conversion duration for pharyngeal swab was 20 days in Wuhan, and the shortest time was 8 days [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. It was unclear if general antiviral agents have a role to play in shortening the conversion duration, in part due to a shorter median onset-admission interval in Shanghai compared with Wuhan (4 days vs 11 days). Our data indicated that the median onset-conversion duration was longer in patients with severe-critical disease. There was no evidence for any benefits from antiviral treatment in terms of viral shedding when comparing mild patients using antivirals (
 <italic>n</italic> = 277) with those that did not (
 <italic>n</italic> = 22), suggesting that these drugs were not effective in shortening the infectious period. Longer viral shedding duration was detected in patients undergoing glucocorticoid therapy, indicating that glucocorticoid should be used with caution in COVID-19 patients. According to Chinese national guidelines [
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and WHO guidance [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], the routine use of systemic corticosteroids for the treatment of COVID-19 is not currently recommended. In our case series, longer duration of viral shedding was detected in blood and faeces in patients with mild disease who were using glucocorticoid. However, when limiting analyses to patients with severe-critical illness, no differences were observed according to glucocorticoid use. Dexamethasone has recently shown promise for reducing deaths among patients who required respiratory support [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. At the time of writing, these data were yet to be peer-reviewed. Additional trials may be necessary to assess the impact of treatment with glucocorticoid.
</p>
