<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lymphopenia was the most common laboratory abnormality at admission, occurring in nearly 70% of cases. In Wuhan, the proportion with lymphopenia was unevenly distributed between severe and non-severe patients (96.1% versus 80.4%, Pearson Chi-Square = 22.069, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. We found a lower proportion of cases presenting with lymphopenia in Shanghai compared with non-severe cases in Wuhan, (69.9% versus 80.4%, Pearson Chi-Square value = 14.301, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). In addition to the shorter median onset-admission interval, this finding supported the idea that symptomatic patients received treatment earlier in Shanghai. Temporal distribution of lymphocyte counts throughout the disease course should be further studied to arrive at a more convincing answer. Lymphocyte counts less than 800/mm
 <sup>3</sup> were found to be a strong predictor for death caused by viral pneumonia in the MuLBSTA score model [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Whether this model or lymphocyte counts can be used as a detection tool for early disease progression is unclear. Some patients were given thymosin to elicit an increase in lymphocytes, but the effect on prognosis requires further investigation. Consistent with earlier results, this study found that inflammatory markers, such as CRP, were elevated [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. D-dimer elevation was also an important feature of the disease, seen in over one-third of cases. About a quarter of our patients were offered anticoagulant drugs. For patients with severe and critical conditions, positive culture results for blood and urine samples were common, indicating that concurrent infections may have adverse effects and preventive antibiotics may be beneficial in some patients as the disease progresses.
</p>
