<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text>
 <label>Box 2</label>
 <p id="Par34">
  <bold>SL-CoVs</bold>
 </p>
 <p id="Par35">The SARS-like-CoVs has genome sequence identity of 88–90 % among themselves and 87–92 % to human or civet SARS-CoV isolates. The unique set of ORFs exclusively found in SARS-CoV was also present in bat SARS-like-CoVs, demonstrating the close phylogenetic relationship between SARS-CoV and SARS-like-CoV. SL-CoVs were also discovered in rhinolophids from Slovenia, Bulgaria and Italy in Europe but these European SARS-like-CoVs exhibited significant genetic variation from Chinese isolates
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
  </sup>. In Africa, novel betacoronaviruses related to SARS-CoV have been detected in 
  <italic>Hipposideros</italic> and 
  <italic>Chaerophon</italic> bat species from Ghana, Kenya and Nigeria. However, compared with Asian and European SARS-like-CoVs, these viruses of non-rhinolophid origin were phylogenetically distant to SARS-CoV. The Western African isolates even formed a potential new lineage of Betacoronavirus in the phylogenetic tree
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
  </sup>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36">
  <bold>WiV16</bold>
 </p>
 <p id="Par37">The gene organization of WIV16 is identical to that of WIV1 strain, and slightly different from that of the civet SARS-CoV and other bat SARS-like-CoVs due to an additional ORF, ORFx detected between the ORF6 and ORF7 genes of the WIV1 and WIV16 genomes 27. The overall nucleotide sequence of WIV16 has 96% identity (higher than that of any previously reported bat SARS-like-CoVs WIV1) to human and civet SARS-CoVs
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>,
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>
  </sup>. The high sequence conversation of the WIV16 RBD with that of SARS-CoVs predicts that WIV16 is likely also to be able to use ACE2 as a cellular entry receptor. SL-WIV16-CoV was thus considered the closest ancestor to date of SARS-CoV and the study has provided further evidence that WIV16 is not the closest strain to the human SARSCoVs with regard to ORF8. Full-length ORF8 is present in several SARS-CoV genomes of early-phase patients. all civet SARS-CoVs, and bat SARS-like-CoVs. Furthermore, two studies have found a full-length ORF9 which has higher similarities to SARS-CoV GZ02 and civet SARS-CoV SZ3, suggesting that SARS-CoV derived from a complicated recombination and genetic evolution among different bat SARS-like-CoVs
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>,
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
  </sup>.
 </p>
</boxed-text>
