<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">This is the first report describing the emergence of new PEDV G1b variants resulting from an initial genetic shift (i.e., novel recombination occurring between the Korean emergent G1b strain and the currently circulating pandemic G2b strains as the minor and major parental viruses, respectively) and subsequent genetic drift (i.e., point mutations). Genetic recombination of RNA viruses, including coronaviruses, is a major driving force of rapid viral evolution that leads to the emergence of new strains or viruses. Thus, new traits or phenotypes and novel coding sequences can frequently be acquired by recombination between members of the same or different viral species or families [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Our data indicate that the NTD of the S gene is a common target for natural recombination between two different genotypes of PEDV. Since this domain includes one putative neutralizing epitope (NTD/S0) located between aa positions 19 and 220 [19], frequent recombination events may afford some advantages (e.g., antigenic shift) that allow the virus to evade host immune defenses such as neutralizing antibodies (Supplementary Fig. S4). Also, we found ongoing genetic drift in both the major and minor parental portions of the novel G1b recombinants. In particular, the NTD of the S gene, representing the minor parental virus, contained four aa changes outside of the NTD/S0 epitope, which could genetically shift the G1b recombinant to the G2b-like virus and possibly enhance pathogenesis. Indeed, the two PEDV-naïve swine farms in this study experienced mild neonatal mortality rates, which differed somewhat from previous reports describing the low pathogenicity of G1b isolates, which commonly showed minimal to no clinical signs or mortality associated with PED in piglets [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. To corroborate this field observation, we are currently isolating new PEDV recombinants that can grow in cell culture, which will allow us to conduct a challenge study. Further, reverse genetics studies will likely provide fundamental clues regarding the possible relationship of recombination and additional mutations to PEDV pathogenesis.
</p>
