<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In July 2018, a case of male urethral inflammation associated with HAdV-B7d was detected in a 22-year-old heterosexual man. He was unmarried and did not have a specific sexual partner. He had an unremarkable medical history, no history of sexually transmitted infections, and no record of traveling abroad. He claimed to have had 2 sexual encounters during his lifetime; the first was in 2016, but the second, in 2018, we considered to be the putative infection day (day 0) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). He described it as a casual sexual encounter with a previously unknown woman and reported the encounter to include protected vaginal intercourse, cunnilingus, and unprotected oral intercourse. The patient denied insertive or receptive anal intercourse as well as mouth-to-mouth kissing. Urethral irritation and dysuria appeared on day 1 and continued to develop gradually (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>); these symptoms might be caused by mechanical irritation. On day 15, the patient experienced the most pain from his symptoms, reporting a numerical rating scale score of 5/10 and a visual analog scale score of 4.8/10. These scales are subjective scores of pain (reference 
 <italic>19</italic> in Appendix). Pharyngitis and conjunctivitis appeared on day 17. On day 19, he visited an ophthalmic clinic for confirmation of conjunctivitis; however, it was not considered to be adenoviral conjunctivitis because an adenoviral immunochromatographic kit produced a negative result. Fluorometholone and levofloxacin eye drops were prescribed. Because his urethritis symptoms were severe, he visited a sexually transmitted diseases clinic (Sendai city, Miyagi prefecture, Japan) on day 20. The patient reported no fever, chills, or malaise; on the basis of his symptoms and results of a physical examination (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), we diagnosed nongonococcal urethritis. Because we could not exclude the possibility of bacterial infection, we prescribed sitafloxacin hydrate (200 mg/d for 7 days). Pathogen screening at the first visit to the clinic detected 
 <italic>Haemophilus parainfluenzae</italic> bacteria from urethral discharge, but the clinical significance was unclear.
</p>
