<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We isolated HAdV in A549 cells from first-void urine, throat gargle, and eye discharge fluid by a previously described method (reference 
 <italic>16</italic> in 
 <xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref>). No other pathogens were identified. Sequences of the HAdV hexon, fiber, and penton open reading frames obtained by Sanger sequencing from all 3 specimen sources were identical. The full genome sequence was obtained from the urine isolate (designated strain 293) (
 <xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Tables 1, 2) and deposited in GenBank (accession no. LC530212). We also performed a BLAST analysis (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) as previously described (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>) with reference sequences of HAdV type 7 (
 <xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 1; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). On the basis of the phylogenetic tree analysis of whole-genome sequences, we classified the isolated HAdV-B7 strain into the same cluster as HAdV-B7d. In addition, we performed an in silico analysis of the genome using Restriction Analyzer software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molbiotools.com/restrictionanalyzer.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.molbiotools.com/restrictionanalyzer.html</ext-link>) by comparing the patterns of the 293 isolate with a reference HAdV-7d sequence and the following enzymes: 
 <italic>Bam</italic>HI, BclI, BstEII, 
 <italic>Hpa</italic>I, and 
 <italic>Sma</italic>I (
 <xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 2). After these analyses, we identified the 293 isolate as HAdV-7d. On the basis of these results, we concluded that the patient acquired the HAdV-B7d infection, which caused urethritis, conjunctivitis, and pharyngitis, during sexual intercourse. All symptoms disappeared by day 23. When the patient revisited the clinic on day 30, he had no urethral symptoms. We detected HAdV-B7d strains isolated from first-void urine and gargle but not from eye discharge; no other pathogens tested in this study were detected. On day 40, the patient’s third visit to the clinic, no pathogens were detected. Approximately 2 months later, no symptoms were observed, and we confirmed a good prognosis.
</p>
