<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">Other coronavirus-associated neurologic phenomena in adults, reported infrequently, are seizures and meningoencephalitis with SARS-CoV and CoV-2 (Hung et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2003</xref>; Lau et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2004</xref>; Moriguchi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2020</xref>). Recently, an adult patient with SARS-CoV-2 and acute hemorrhagic necrotizing encephalopathy was described (Poyiadji et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2020</xref>). Finally, for both children and adults, there are reports of demyelinating phenomena. Acute disseminated encephalomyelitis (ADEM) in a previously healthy 15-year-old boy with HCoV-OC43 detected in CSF and nasopharyngeal secretions has been published (Yeh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2004</xref>). While multiple T2-hyperintense, occasionally enhancing lesions were seen on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain and spinal cord, the child’s neurologic symptoms resolved without any therapeutic interventions over the course of several weeks (Yeh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2004</xref>). Acute flaccid paralysis in a 3-year-old dually infected with HCoVs OC43 and 229E has been reported; it resolved after several weeks, but a definitive CNS or PNS origin could not be ascertained (Turgay et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2015</xref>). In adults, HCoVs 229E and OC43 have been associated with multiple sclerosis (MS), but these observations are not uniform across all studies (Burks et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1980</xref>; Stewart et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">1992</xref>; Arbour et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2000</xref>). A reliable model of coronavirus-induced demyelination is seen with MHV (Bergmann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>; Perlman and Wheeler 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2016</xref>). When inoculated with attenuated strains of John Howard Mueller virus (JHMV), mice initially develop a productive and transient encephalitis; as the immune response decreases viral titers, demyelinating lesions arise, and mice have increasing clinical symptomatology. Mice remain persistently infected with ongoing chronic demyelination, thus providing a model of human MS. When primates are inoculated with JHMV, both encephalomyelitis and demyelination are observed (Murray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1992a</xref>).
</p>
