<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">There are two major neurologic complications seen with coronaviruses in infants and children: febrile seizures and acute meningoencephalitis. Febrile seizures are events in association with fever, occurring in the absence of prior seizures, evidence of CNS infection, or systemic metabolic derangements (Carman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2019</xref>). In a recent multicenter study of 192 children with febrile seizures, HCoVs OC43 and 229E were identified in 6.9% and 3.4% of nasopharyngeal samples, most often in combination with other respiratory viruses (Carman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2019</xref>). While infrequent overall, HCoV-OC43 was the most common viral pathogen in infants under the age of 12 months. In children under the age of 6 with febrile seizures in Slovenia, 10% were associated with HCoVs (Pokorn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2017</xref>). Of 26 children hospitalized for coronavirus respiratory illness in Hong Kong, of 6 (23%) had febrile seizures, 4 with HCoV-NL63, and 2 with HCoV-OC43 (Chiu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2005</xref>). Another study from Hong Kong described febrile seizures in 5 of 10 (50%) hospitalized children with HCoV-HKU1, raising the possibility that this species may have greater than usual impact on the CNS (Principi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2010</xref>; Lau et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2006</xref>). Febrile seizures are uncommon with SARS-CoV; while not mentioned in some reports, a single infant with febrile convulsions is described in a series from Hong Kong (Hon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2003</xref>; Bitnun et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2003</xref>; Chiu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2003</xref>). In series of infants and children with SARS-CoV-2 currently available from China and Spain, there is no mention of febrile seizures, nor are any neurologic disorders described (Tagarro et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2020</xref>; Wei et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">2020</xref>; Lu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2020</xref>). Thus, HCoVs appear to contribute in minor part to febrile seizures in infants and children; when identified, they are usually continuously circulating and not epidemic species and are present both in isolation as well as accompanied by other, more common respiratory viruses.
</p>
