<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">High rates of neurologic phenomena have been reported in adults hospitalized with SARS-CoV-2 (Mao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>; Helms et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2020</xref>). In 214 COVID-19-related hospitalizations from Wuhan, manifestations were categorized as central, peripheral (included in this category were impairments in taste, smell, and vision), or musculoskeletal (Mao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). Central nervous system abnormalities were present in 25%, PNS in 9%, and musculoskeletal in 11%. The most common CNS manifestations were dizziness (17%), headache (13%), and impaired consciousness (7.5%). Of 58 hospitalized patients reported from France, 84% had neurologic manifestations; common abnormalities were also non-focal and included agitation (69%), confusion (65% of a subset of 40), and, on examination, diffuse corticospinal tract signs (enhanced deep tendon reflexes, ankle clonus, bilateral extensor plantar reflexes) in 67%. A small subset of French patients underwent brain MRI and CSF analysis; all 7 CSF studies returned negative reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) for SARS-CoV-2, despite leptomeningeal enhancement in 8 of 13 neuroimaging studies (Helms et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2020</xref>). Series of patients with SARS and MERS are similar with regard to commoner phenomena being potentially constitutional. Of 138 patients with SARS reported from Hong Kong, headache and dizziness were seen in 56% and 43% respectively; of 144 patients in Toronto, 35% reported headache and 4% dizziness (Lee et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2003</xref>; Booth et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2003</xref>). In 70 patients hospitalized with MERS in Saudi Arabia, headache (13%), confusion (26%), and seizures (9%) were reported; in 23 MERS patients from Korea, 9% had headache and 22% confusion (Saad et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">2014</xref>; Kim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2017</xref>).
</p>
