<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">A less common, but well-documented complication of all the epidemic coronaviruses is stroke, either in the form of large artery cerebral infarction or intracranial hemorrhage (Umapathi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2004</xref>; Arabi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2015</xref>; Algahtani et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2016</xref>; Mao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>; Oxley et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>). In larger series, the overall prevalence of stroke is 5% or less; 2.4% in SARS patients from Singapore, 5.2% in COVID-19 patients from France, and 2.8% in COVID-19 patients from Wuhan (Mao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>; Helms et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2020</xref>; Umapathi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2004</xref>). Reported patients range in age from 33 to 70, and many lack other risk factors for stroke. Recently, cerebral infarction was described in a 14-year-old boy with COVID-19-associated multisystem inflammatory syndrome (Riphagen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2020</xref>). Patients with SARS-CoV-2-related strokes can present at any stage of viral infection, from otherwise asymptomatic to critical pulmonary disease. In China, it was observed that acute stroke is more common with severe illness, seen in 5.7% of those with critical illness and only 0.8% of those with less advanced disease (Mao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). However, in New York City, where European SARS-CoV-2 strains predominate, cerebral infarction was documented in young individuals with mild COVID symptomatology (Oxley et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>). Stroke may be related to coronavirus-associated coagulopathies. Elevated D-dimers, fibrin degradation products and thrombocytopenia are present in over 50% of those with severe COVID-19 and SARS disease, and in similarly high percentages of those with MERS; venous thrombosis and thromboembolism have also been described (Giannis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2020</xref>). However, not critically evaluated is how disseminated intravascular coagulopathy (DIC), or a microangiopathic coagulopathy closely resembling DIC, contributes to ischemic stroke in the absence of hemorrhage or underlying arterial lesions, as the strokes described are large vessel, high flow, arterial phenomena. Recently, antiphospholipid antibodies were detected in three patients with severe COVID-19 and stroke, raising the possibility that cerebral ischemia arises with vascular immunopathologies other than DIC and microangiopathy (Zhang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131">2020</xref>). Alternatively, there may be a direct role for viral infection of endothelia, as recent autopsy reports demonstrate viral particles in systemic and brain endothelium, with apoptosis and focal endotheliitis (Varga et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2020</xref>; Mondolfi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2020</xref>).
</p>
