<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RVFV can be transmitted by multiple species of mosquitoes, and their presence varies across Africa (
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In Mayotte, RVFV has never been detected in mosquitoes in the wild. However, 47 species of mosquitoes have been described, from which several could be potential vectors (e.g., 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae. circumluteolus</italic>, 
 <italic>Anopheles coustani</italic>, 
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic>, 
 <italic>Cx quinquefasciatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Cx antennatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Eretmapodites quinquevittatus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Mansonia uniformis</italic>) (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Each of these vectors may have specific bioecology and population dynamics. While future research should aim at collecting such data, in their absence, we used rainfall as a proxy for the presence of RVF vectors, as it was found to be associated with the occurrence of RVF outbreaks (
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). We assumed a 14-d lag between rainfall and its impact on vector abundance based on previous modeling studies on RVF vector population dynamics (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). This resulted in a maximal value of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>s,t</italic>
 </sub> of 1.9 (95% CrI [1.5–2.5]), which is in line with previous estimations of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> (
 <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr"/>–
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), and assuming a 21-d lag, at the most, delayed the epidemic peak by 1 wk. Temperature above 26 °C may also promote RVFV transmission (
 <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 <xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr"/>–
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). However, with the average annual temperatures in Mayotte varying between 25 and 35 °C (
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), we assumed that in this specific setting temperature would not be a major driver for viral transmission. In areas with cooler temperatures, such as South Africa (
 <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), temperature may need to be taken into account (
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).
</p>
