<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous RVF models parameterized the transmission rate from livestock to humans by direct contact as an input parameter at 1.7 per 10,000 persons per day (
 <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The epidemiological investigations conducted in this epidemic assessed whether human cases reported a direct contact with animals or their tissues. By combining this information with data on the fraction of people in contact with livestock in the population (30%), this allowed disentangling and estimating both RVFV spillover to humans by direct contact and by vector transmission from epidemic data. These estimated transmission rates can be used as a benchmark for further modeling work. The model predictions showed that 55% of human cases resulted from vector transmission, and 45% from direct contact. The main route of RVFV transmission to humans reported to date, during epidemics, is the transmission by direct contact (
 <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr"/>–
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Here, while the proportion of vector-mediated infections decreased with the proportion of the farming population (to 42% if only 10% of the population have regular contact with animals), it remained high, suggesting that the vector-mediated transmission might have played an important role in this setting. During this epidemic, all those with dengue-like syndromes consulting a general practitioner (GP) were tested against RVFV by RT-PCR. The reported human cases therefore captured RVF cases from both exposed and nonexposed groups, giving confidence that our estimates on the direct contact and vector transmission routes had limited bias. In addition, the high diversity of potential RVF vectors present in Mayotte, as mentioned in the above paragraph, and their feeding preferences for livestock and humans [for example, 
 <italic>Cx pipiens</italic> and 
 <italic>Cx antennatus</italic> (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>)], might have also contributed to facilitate vector spillover transmission. In the 1977 epidemic in Egypt, the vector route is believed to have played an important role with 
 <italic>Cx pipiens</italic> being a major vector, and resulting in several thousands of human cases (
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). However, we acknowledge that the relative importance of vector transmission versus direct contact during an epidemic may vary across ecosystems. Yet, we provide quantitative information on the zoonotic transmission of RVFV.
</p>
