<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dengue fever has become a statutorily notifiable epidemic in China since September 1, 1989. In this study, the dengue epidemiological data from 1990 to 2017 were derived from the Public Health Science Data Center (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phsciencedata.cn/Share/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.phsciencedata.cn/Share/</ext-link>), covering the number, incidence rate, death, and mortality rate of dengue in 22 provinces, 4 municipalities, and 5 autonomous regions of mainland China. The data were proofread according to the “National Legal Infectious Disease Epidemic Situation” issued by the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhfpc.gov.cn/jkj/s3578/new_list.shtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nhfpc.gov.cn/jkj/s3578/new_list.shtml</ext-link>). The missing data for some provinces in 2018 to 2019 were derived from studies published by Web of Science (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.webofknowledge.com/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://apps.webofknowledge.com/</ext-link>), China National Knowledge Infrastructure (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kns.cnki.net/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://kns.cnki.net</ext-link>), PubMed (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/</ext-link>), and were verified by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention of the corresponding province. Data on age, gender, and occupation distribution of dengue from 2010 to 2017 were obtained from the Public Health Science Data Center. Altitude of provinces in China was retrieved from the 360 personal libraries (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.360doc.com/content/17/0211/22/193203_628331100.shtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.360doc.com/content/17/0211/22/193203_628331100.shtml</ext-link>). Besides, we retrieved the mean annual temperature of China from OSGeo China Center (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.osgeo.cn/map/m0401" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.osgeo.cn/map/m0401</ext-link>).
</p>
