<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Acral ischemia</italic> was initially observed in isolated cases of young and otherwise healthy individuals who presented with occasionally itchy or burning erythematous bluish macules or papules on solitary digits. Some of the patients remained healthy although SARS‐CoV‐2 positive, while others developed general symptoms of infection.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>44</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>45</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic>A new type of COVID‐19‐related vasculitis</italic> was suggested based on the large number of similar cases from Italy and France. Secondary microthrombosis caused by endothelial damage and vascular disorders was suspected, and vasculitis‐like changes were histologically confirmed.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>46</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic>Lupus erythematosus (LE)‐like chilblains</italic> of the feet associated with normal coagulation status were explained with microangiopathic changes as a result of early interferon (IFN)‐I response.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>47</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic>“Covid toes”</italic> was the term introduced recently for these pernio‐like lesions in the absence of previous exposure to cold temperatures.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>48</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic>Chilblain‐like lesions (CLL)</italic> “outbreak” was detected in Italy in a series of 63 otherwise healthy adolescents with occasional history of initial general symptoms. Cutaneous lesions were painful or itchy, stable, and mostly affected toes and soles in two different patterns: erythematous‐edematous and blistering type. Despite the low rate of laboratory‐proven SARS‐CoV‐2 infection, the authors supported the hypothesis of a delayed immune‐mediated reaction to the virus in genetically predisposed patients.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>49</sup>
 </xref> A retrospective nationwide study in France including 277 outpatients with median age 27 years (range 2–98 years) also detected high predominance of acral changes (
 <italic>n</italic> = 142, 80%) presenting mainly as CLL (
 <italic>n</italic> = 106/142, 75%). Among the 277 patients, 34 had a SARS‐Cov2 PCR test, of which 25 were positive (74%). Seven of these 25 (28%) had acral lesions. Additionally, 59 patients had isolated CLL, without associated extracutaneous symptoms. Histological examination of three CLL showed a lichenoid dermatitis with a perivascular and eccrine mononuclear infiltrate, and vascular microthrombi in 2 cases.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>50</sup>
 </xref> Another retrospective study from Spain reported 132 nonhospitalized patients with median age 19.9 (range 1–54 years) and predominantly acral involvement. Mild COVID‐19 symptoms preceded skin lesions in 16 patients, with a mean latency time of 9.2 days (range 3–30 days), and in three patients, their onset coincided. The average duration of the skin lesions was 8.7 days (range 2–24 days). Two main patterns of acro‐ischemic lesions were differentiated: chilblain‐like pattern in 95 (72%) patients and erythema multiforme‐like pattern in 37 (28%).
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>51</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic>Acute acral cyanosis</italic> in the absence of chilblains has also been seen in an unpublished observation. In contrast to the above‐mentioned young and asymptomatic cases, reports from Wuhan described acral ischemia of the lower limbs bilaterally and of solitary fingers of the hands in critically ill COVID‐19 patients.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>52</sup>
 </xref> Chinese patients, aged above 60, had multiple comorbidities and were hospitalized in the intensive‐care unit with severe COVID‐19 pneumonia. Hypercoagulopathy, elevated D‐dimers, and antiphospholipid antibodies (anticardiolipin IgA, anti‐β2‐glycoprotein I IgA, and IgG antibodies) in the course of severe infection could explain the presence of ischemic skin lesions.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>53</sup>
 </xref> The induced thrombotic events were difficult to differentiate from other causes of multifocal thromboses in critically ill patients, such as disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), heparin‐induced thrombocytopenia, and thrombotic microangiopathy.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>54</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
