<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0020">We then hypothesised three patterns of overall disruption to HIV services that might occur during the COVID-19 epidemic, incorporating all the individual elements reported above. These scenarios are described below and summarised in 
 <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Each scenario is cumulative in the sense that it incorporates the change described in all less severe scenarios. In the first instance, we assume the disruption begins in mid-2020 and lasts for three months, and that normal service resumes thereafter for all programs.
 <list list-type="simple" id="celist0002">
  <list-item id="celistitem0007">
   <label>1.</label>
   <p id="para0021">
    <italic>Managed pause</italic> (least severe):
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="simple" id="celist0003">
  <list-item id="celistitem0008">
   <p id="para0022">In this scenario, the expansion of services planned for this time is paused but all services are maintained at their current levels. This might occur, for instance, if there is very little actual disruption to the HIV programs, but opportunities to expand are not available due to it being impractical to run outreach services and persons not yet engaged with care postpone testing.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="simple" id="celist0004">
  <list-item id="celistitem0009">
   <label>2.</label>
   <p id="para0023">
    <italic>Managed disruption:</italic>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="simple" id="celist0005">
  <list-item id="celistitem0010">
   <p id="para0024">In this scenario, substantial pressure on the health system and social distancing measures combine to disrupt services, but these are sufficiently well managed that their worst impacts are mitigated and the supply of ART is maintained. In addition to the effects of the first scenario (‘Managed pause’) there is also a reduction in condom use, as might be caused by reduced supply of condoms and less opportunity to acquire them, and decreased viral suppression, as might be caused by a combination of persons being less inclined or able to present for routine viral load testing, viral load testing being less widely available (due to increased usage of laboratory equipment), and short-term fluctuations in the supply of ART drugs.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="simple" id="celist0006">
  <list-item id="celistitem0011">
   <label>3.</label>
   <p id="para0025">
    <italic>Interruption of supply</italic> (most severe):
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="simple" id="celist0007">
  <list-item id="celistitem0012">
   <p id="para0026">In this scenario, extreme pressure on the health system and/or strict interventions and stressed supply chains domestically and internationally combine to interrupt the supply of key medicines, with the result that a fraction of PLHIV on ART are temporarily forced off ART.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
