<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">Something similar happened during the current COVID-19 epidemic. At the beginning of the epidemic a novel coronavirus which was considered highly related to COVID-19 was identified in Malayan pangolin (
 <italic>Manis javanica</italic>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. It was proposed that the pangolins were potential natural intermediate hosts or even reservoirs of COVID-19,suggesting that these small mammals were a threat to public health
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Further studies, however, disproved this hypothesis. An analyzes of the genomes of the coronavirus identified in three sick pangolins found that the pangolin CoV is genetically related to COVID-19, but phylogenetic analysis and amino acid sequence on the S protein of COVID-19 did not support the hypothesis of the virus arising directly from the pangolin-CoV
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, the recent work of Damas et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup> examined ACE2 receptors from 410 vertebrates (fishes, amphibians, birds, reptiles, and mammals) to predict their ability to bind COVID-19 spike proteins. The vertebrates were classified as having 
 <italic>low</italic>, 
 <italic>medium</italic>, and 
 <italic>high</italic> score depending on the ability of their receptors to bind COVID-19 Spike proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. The 18 species predicted as very 
 <italic>high</italic> were all Old World primates and apes, which were identical to human in the 25 ACE2 receptor binding residues. Domestic cat scored 
 <italic>medium</italic>, dog and pig scored 
 <italic>low</italic>, while species scoring 
 <italic>very low</italic> included all pangolin species such as Chinese pangolin (
 <italic>Manis pentadactyla</italic>), Sunda pangolin (
 <italic>Manis javanica</italic>), white-bellied pangolin (
 <italic>Phataginus tricuspis</italic>), and masked palm civet (
 <italic>Paguma larvata</italic>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
