<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">Moreover, it must be kept in mind that wet-markets are also places where a large number of domestic animals are held such as pigs, cattle, dogs, cats, chickens, and ducks. Most of the time, the animals are slaughtered directly at the market. This could constitute a possible factor of contamination of the meat products with biological material coming from wild animals such as bats, or from infected humans. In fact, in a survey conducted on 242 subject form six different animals species in 2005, two pigs were found positive to SARS-CoV, while the owners of the animals were negative to the test
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. The source of the SARS-CoV found in these pigs was most likely virus-contaminated animal food, since swineherds in rural areas often obtain leftovers from restaurants in the cities to be used for the pigs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. These findings might also explain the very recent COVID-19 outbreak in the biggest seafood market of Beijing, where over 100 people were found infected with the virus. All of them were workers of the Xinfadi market
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. The animal products in that market were tested positive with COVID-19, including the wooden boards where the workers cut the meat
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. The suggestion was made that the source of the infecting COVID-19 virus could have been imported salmon, that was keep frozen during the transport to Beijing, and could thus be contaminated with still alive virus. This new outbreak supports the hypothesis of contamination via animal products and not just via live animals. It is thus possible that crowded markets could function as boosting places for the pathogens. In fact, to go back to the 
 <italic>amplification effect</italic>, people working at the wet-markets could be sensitive hosts in constant contact with the source of the virus. Moreover, the same workers of the market might slaughter the bats on the same area where they cut the meat contributing to further contamination. It is well known that wooden board can keep biological material even after been washed. In this environment, the virus would have all the time to adjust to the new host, maybe causing small undetected outbreaks until it reached the human-to-human form. In this situation, human beings would become the intermediate hosts of their own species.
</p>
