<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0020">The association between cardiovascular diseases and the new viral agent severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has been a matter of debate since the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic began in Wuhan, China in December 2019. This issue has mainly concerned the prognosis and treatment of COVID-19 in patients with cardiovascular diseases (CVD) (
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">Tian-Yuan et al., 2020</xref>). On the other hand, several studies have suggested that SARS-CoV-2 might be an independent cause of myocardial damage in some patients through pathophysiological mechanisms that are not yet fully understood (
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>). Although the virus mainly induces lung injury, autopsy studies have confirmed that the heart, kidneys, vessels, liver, brain, and other organs may also be affected (
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Puelles et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Cizgici et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Hua et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Doyen et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Farina et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Inciardi et al., 2020</xref>). Viral infections are the major cause of myocarditis and pericarditis in developed countries and it is also evident that SARS-CoV-2 has cardiotropic properties. Most of the case reports published so far have investigated cardiac involvement in COVID-19 patients with severe respiratory tract infections (
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Cizgici et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Puelles et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Cizgici et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Hua et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Doyen et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Farina et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Inciardi et al., 2020</xref>). The case of a patient with acute pericarditis as the dominant manifestation of SARS-CoV-2 infection is presented here.
</p>
