<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding oxygen therapy, RV infection seems to be associated with lower oxygen requirement and duration. In a cohort of 455 infants with acute bronchiolitis described by Miller et al., RV infection was associated with a lower frequency of supplemental oxygen requirement than infants with other viral pathogens (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) [
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Moreover, Marguet and colleagues found that RVinfection decreased the risk of oxygen requirement compared to RSV-infection (OR 0.29, 95% CI 0.09–0.90 at the logistic regression) in a prospective multicenter study enrolling 209 infants [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Nevertheless, no significant differences emerged in the more recent and larger (486 cases), albeit retrospective, research of Petrarca et al. [
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Similarly, no differences among viral pathogens emerged concerning ventilatory support, intended as continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) and/or intubation requirement during the hospitalization [
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. These data resulted from the Multicenter Airway Research Collaboration (MARC), a program of the Emergency Medicine Network, which was responsible for the enrollment of the largest cohorts of hospitalized infants with bronchiolitis, prospectively studied in multiple sites in the USA. In 2012, Mansbach et al. analyzed data obtained from the enrollment of 2207 patients during three winter seasons. They found a viral pathogen in 2068 of cases and compared single-RV to single-RSV infection, as well as co-infections, without discovering significant differences in terms of CPAP/intubation requirement [
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In more recent years, a similar study was performed, also in Finland. In 2015, Jarttiet al. collected data from both the enrolled American and Finnish cohorts, amounting to 2615 children &lt;2 years of age, of whom 694 documented RV infection. To the best of our knowledge, this study was the only one to investigate the relationship between RV viral load and severity of the disease, and no significant differences emerged in CPAP or intubation requirement [
 <xref rid="B29-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Similarly, Hasegawa et al. compared enrolled American (1016 patients, of which 197 were RV-infected) and Finnish (408 patients, of which 109 were RV-infected) cohorts of infants. Here, they specifically identified also the RV-A, RV-B, and RV-C types responsible for the collected bronchiolitis (47%, 6%, and 47% in the American group and 23%, 3%, and 74% in the Finnish group, respectively). No significant differences in terms of CPAP and/or intubation requirement emerged between the three different RV types in both analyzed cohorts [
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Finally, also in a prospective multicenter study focusing on 363 hospitalized infants with moderate-severe bronchiolitis, no significant differences appeared between RV infection—even when they considered viral types—and other single virus-infections regarding either oxygen requirement, ventilation need, or nasogastric feeding [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
</p>
