<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Furthermore, many studies have analyzed the hospital LOS as an index of bronchiolitis severity. Only one study has reported a longer LOS in RV bronchiolitis compared to RSV bronchiolitis: Paul and colleagues enrolled a cohort of 319 hospitalized children for acute bronchiolitis, focusing on single RV or single RSV infections (65 cases for the former, 162 cases for the latter). Analyzing the mean LOS as clinical outcome emerged a greater LOS in the RV group compared with the RSV group (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.032) [
 <xref rid="B32-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. More studies have observed instead a correlation between RV infection and a lower LOS when this virus is compared to other viral pathogens, especially RSV [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In the prospective single-center study conducted in 2010 (182 infants), Midulla et al. found that RV infection had a lower mean LOS than RSV-infection (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.05) [
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Jartti and colleagues came to comparable results on a cohort of 408 children comparing RV infections to RSV infections in terms of LOS shorter or longer than three days (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.03) [
 <xref rid="B26-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Similarly, Marguet et al. studied 209 infants considering the duration of LOS &gt; 5 days as an outcome, finding that RV infection decreased the risk of prolonged LOS compared to other viral infections, including RSV-bronchiolitis (OR 0.11, 95% CI 0.03–0.37) [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Finally, in 2019, Bergroth and colleagues analyzed once again a Finnish cohort obtained from the MARC protocol study, specifically focusing on the three RV types. They demonstrated a correlation between RV-A and RV-C (but not RV-B) infection and a lower LOS when compared to RSV-infection (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.003). This result appeared limited by the very low frequency of detected RV-B infection (3%) [
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. On the contrary, many other studies have not found significant differences in terms of LOS between RV bronchiolitis and other viral group-infection [
 <xref rid="B18-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
