<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Here. we found that the average number of neurotrauma consults differed significantly between March and April, likely secondary to South Florida being a destination for spring break, causing an influx of vacationers during that time frame. During the pandemic, however, travel restrictions in combination with less foot and vehicle traffic led to a decrease in all mechanisms of injury, except for GSW. Upon further investigation, we found that the relative proportion of mechanisms of injury also changed after the lockdown in April 2020. With fewer citizens commuting on the streets, the proportion of vehicular trauma decreased, as expected. Decreases in these types of traumas have been reported across the country, however, not in correlation with specific events such as initiation of lockdown protocols.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> The proportion of ground-level falls also decreased; however, this may have been secondary to patients unwilling to take the risk of going to the emergency department after minor accidents for concern of contracting the virus.
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> Importantly, some businesses were deemed “essential” and allowed to continue operating, of which some construction companies took advantage.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> This may explain the increase in the proportion of falls from height, in addition to people doing home repairs while “stay-at-home” orders were in place. With respect to increases in the proportions of assaults and GSWs during the pandemic, they may be secondary to the psychosocial effects of mandatory isolation.
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> Family and friends were forced to be in close proximity to one another, which had the potential to ignite conflicts and violence leading to assault.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> Finally, with prolonged confinement comes an increase in the risk of suicide, which may explain the increase in presumed self-inflicted PHBC and GSW.
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
