<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0010">During the designated COVID-19 period, SGH saw a 16.8% year-on-year reduction in the overall number of hospital admissions (from 19 589 to 16 300). Bed occupancy was also reduced, from 130 597 bed-days pre-COVID-19 to 113 449 bed-days during COVID-19. However, there was a 25.5% increase in the utilization of broad-spectrum antibiotics such as cefepime, piperacillin/tazobactam, carbapenems and vancomycin where defined daily doses (DDD) rose from 14.92 DDD per 100 bed-days to 18.72 DDD per 100 bed-days. Similarly, the utilization of antibiotics for the treatment of community-onset pneumonia increased from 48.74 DDD per 100 bed-days to 50.81 DDD per bed-days. This increase was most marked in February 2020 during the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic, with a notable rise in month-on-month DDD of ceftriaxone, co-amoxiclav, levofloxacin, moxifloxacin, azithromycin and clarithromycin from 47.4 DDD per 100 bed-days to 54.0 DDD per 100 bed-days (see 
 <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). The average monthly proportion of patients on antibiotics was also correspondingly higher (47.4% vs. 49.9%) during the COVID-19 pandemic compared with the same period of time the year before, with the highest proportion documented at the onset (see 
 <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> ). However, as the pandemic evolved, antibiotic use gradually declined, and the authors attribute this to: (a) increased understanding of COVID-19 as international data emerged, and medical teams were more judicious with antibiotic use thereafter (per communication with Dr S.J. Chung); (b) further restrictions in elective admissions with implementation of ‘circuit breaker’ measures in April 2020; and (c) a change in demographics of admissions for respiratory viral illness, where a significant proportion were young able-bodied foreign dormitory workers with mild COVID-19, who were paucisymptomatic or asymptomatic 
 <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, and antibiotics were not prescribed in this group of patients.
</p>
