<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">Genetic drift almost inevitably leads, during time, to amino acid mutations in proteins critical for virus replication and spreading, mostly generating an attenuated viral progeny [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Indeed, different epidemiological and clinical features of COVID-19 were found to be related to genetic changes of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The novel coronavirus has been found to evolve into two subtypes, L and S [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], with the former being more aggressive and spreading more rapidly than the latter [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Jin et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] compared the complete genome of 52 strains of SARS-CoV-2 and described a continuous evolution of the potential furin cleavage site of the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 till the latest isolate (ZJ01) derived from a patient with mild COVID-19. Further informatic analyses highlighted the relative high number of mutations of ZJ01 compared to the sequences of other strains of SARS-CoV-2 collected at the early stage of China epidemic. Mutations observed in ZJ01 had a direct negative impact on viral load and cytopathicity when infecting Vero E6 cells, leading the authors to hypothesize a potential change in evolutionary direction possibly promoting the appearance of a mild SARS-CoV-2 subtype. More recently, Yao et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] reported the functional characterization of 11 patient-derived viral isolates showing significant variation in cytopathic effects and viral load, suggesting that patient-derived mutations have an impact on SARS-CoV-2 pathogenicity. Interestingly, plaque purification of SARS-CoV-2 cultured in Vero E6 showed that a virus isolate contains a series of quasispecies which differ in their in vitro cytopathic activity and in vivo aggressiveness, with attenuated variants being characterized by deletions at the S1/S2 junction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Therefore, attenuated SARS-CoV-2 variants are already being circulating, at least as subdominant strains, in infected individuals. For this reason, investigating the pattern and frequency of mutations occurred in SARS-CoV-2 in more recently infected patients and in asymptomatic individuals is urgently needed.
</p>
