<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It was previously thought that ASFV could not induce neutralizing antibodies. Gomez-Puertas et al., found that p72, p54, and p30 proteins have neutralizing effects, p72 and p54 could inhibit virus adsorption, p72 and p30 could activate cytotoxic T lymphocyte (CTL) response, while p30 could inhibit virus internalization [
 <xref rid="B85-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Other envelope or endomembrane proteins of ASFV, such as CD2v, p12 and D117L, may also induce neutralizing antibodies and be involved in inhibiting viral invasion and release [
 <xref rid="B86-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Ruiz-Gonzalvo et al., used baculovirus to express CD2v and vaccinated pigs with Freund’s adjuvant. The pigs had dose-dependent protective effects against the attack of the homologous ASFV E75 strain without neutralizing antibodies, revealing that factors other than neutralizing antibodies played an additional role in ASFV protection, which may be associated with CD2v-induced antibodies that could inhibit erythrocyte adsorption and temporarily inhibit infection [
 <xref rid="B87-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Researchers used recombinant baculovirus-expressed ASFV p30 and p54 to vaccinate pigs, which could stimulate the body to produce neutralizing antibodies, and had a certain immunological protective effect against ASFV E75 strains [
 <xref rid="B88-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Subsequently, the similar outcome occurred in pigs vaccinated with the chimeric protein p54/30 expressed by recombinant baculovirus [
 <xref rid="B89-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. However, pigs vaccinated with a mixture of p30, p54, p72, and p22 expressed by baculovirus could not resist the attack of the virulent ASFV Pr4, though ASFV-specific neutralizing antibodies could be detected in the pigs with delayed clinical symptoms and reduced viremia [
 <xref rid="B90-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Neutralizing antibodies against these proteins are not sufficient to elicit antibody-mediated protection. Therefore, it brought on doubts about the relevance of p30, p54, and p72 in immune protection and debates about antibody-mediated neutralization protection. Recently, the ASFV serological determinants determined so far have recently been listed by an expert group, and a summary review has been published [
 <xref rid="B91-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. In 2011, Argilaguet et al. vaccinated pigs separately with pCMV-PQ, a plasmid encoding p30 and p54, two immunodominant structural viral antigens, and pCMV-APCH1PQ, a plasmid encoding p30, p54 fused with a single chain variable fragment of an antibody specific for a swine leukocyte antigen II (SLA-II). The experiments showed that both of the plasmids were not able to confer protection against lethal challenge with the virulent E75 ASFV-strain, and a viremia exacerbation was detected in each of the pigs correlating with the presence of non-neutralizing antibodies. The results clearly demonstrate that the adjuvant effect of SLA-II, which could enhance the immune response induced in pigs, and confirmed the critical role of CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in the response to ASFV [
 <xref rid="B92-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. In 2012, the group constructed the plasmid pCMV-sHAPQ, which fused the extracellular domain of ASFV Hemagglutinin/CD2v (sHA) with p54 and p30. After immunizing pigs with the expressed product, strong humoral and specific T cell responses in pigs was induced, which demonstrating the potential adjuvant properties of sHA, but no neutralizing antibody was detected and the pigs cannot resist the attack of virulent strains yet, which might be that the low levels of non-neutralizing and exacerbating antibodies in turn could counteract the protective effects of the specific CD8-T cells induced by the vaccine. Subsequently, the team designed a new recombinant plasmid pCMV-UbsHAPQ encoding three viral determinants (sHA, p54, and p30) of ASFV fused with ubiquitin to improve the presentation of MHC-I and enhance the induced CTL response while avoiding the induction of antibodies, and found that the recombinant plasmid could induce a strong CTL response in the absence of antibodies and protect 2/6 pigs from lethal challenge with ASFV E75 stains. Furthermore the protection may be associated with the proliferation of HA-specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells [
 <xref rid="B93-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Additionally, Lacasta et al. constructed a random DNA library containing 80 ASFV open reading frames (ORFs) fused with Ub, which indicating the presence of other determinants that induce protective CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and revealing the potential protective capacity of new ASFV antigens including CP312R [
 <xref rid="B94-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. The construction of expression libraries helps to thoroughly determine immunogenicity and virus-driven host immune regulatory factors.
</p>
