<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the mid-1990s, Kaliningrad, an enclave of Russian territory at the Baltic Sea between Lithuania and Poland was experiencing an explosive HIV-infection epidemic, which affected IDUs and their sexual partners. Only between June 1996 and April 1997 more than 1200 HIV cases were detected in Kaliningrad population of about half a million inhabitants [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Like in other IDU-associated HIV-infection epidemics in FSU at that time, the main mode of HIV transmission was syringe and needle-sharing but unlike them in Kaliningrad, the non-A6 subtype (CRF03_AB) established an epidemic. Our study suggests that the CRF03_AB clade originated in Kaliningrad region approximately in 1992 and showed a rapid initial growth from the late 1990s. Although the drug use has since then slowed the number of drug-related HIV infections in FSU increased since the late 1990s and have increased further since the beginning of 2000s [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. These historical records support our phylodynamic results and may explain the rapid initial dissemination of CRF03_AB by the introduction in this highly connected network. It should be noted that this demographic model appears to be similar to the A6 sub-subtype epidemic in the former Soviet Union, where injecting drug use was a key factor in determining the pattern of HIV epidemic growth. In comparison, «A6-like» epidemics also seem to have experienced a rapid expansion over the first years, followed by a decline in growth rate. Since then, the transmission patterns in FSU have gradually evolved from injecting drug use to heterosexual contacts [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In combination with the saturation of high-risk transmission network and the access to highly active antiretroviral therapy started in region this in mid-2000, this may have contributed to the reduction of the effective HIV-1population size [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. However, although heterosexuals are making a greater contribution to the epidemic now, the cross-risk group transmission via IDUs is still relevant for CRF03_AB (
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>); this partially explains why no clusters were detected among the high-risk groups. The phylogenetic analysis revealed the high level of CRF03_AB sequences intermixing from FSU countries, which provides the evidence against the existence of country-specific lineages. It may be possible that such a low level of geographic compartmentalization of the HIV-1 epidemic in FSU is associated with the continuous cross-border virus transfer between countries due to historical ties and intense human mobility.
</p>
