<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The phylogeographic reconstruction carried out in the present study supports the idea that the CRF03_AB clade could have been initially originated in Kaliningrad, with further spreading to the West (Lithuania, Belarus) and North (Saint-Petersburg) through short-distance transfers. The epidemiological links between these locations are not unexpected due to their geographical proximity and high level of people migration, which was constant at the end of the 20th century even after the USSR collapse. Although this results pointed to the Kaliningrad as the geographical origin of CRF03_AB, this clade might have arose elsewhere since no parental subtype A or subtype B strains have been reported in Kaliningrad [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Probably as previously reported [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], the original recombination event took place in Ukraine, where parental forms were found, and then the virus entered Kaliningrad and established the epidemic. Given this possibility as well as relative long period of asymptomatic infection, our early T
 <sub>mrca</sub> estimations for CRF03_AB clade (a 5–6 years before the first cases of CRF03_AB detection) do not seem surprising. Apparently, this recombinant was circulating in the region several years before its explosive spread among IDUs; previously, such a scenario has already been demonstrated for the HIV-1 A6 epidemic [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Unfortunately, with the data available, it is not possible to verify this hypothesis. Besides the northwest FSU territories, we have also found the migration movements of HIV-1 CRF03_AB recombinant from Kaliningrad to other Russian regions (Perm’, Ekaterinburg, Krasnodar etc.; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0241269.g003">Fig 3</xref>) as well as Central Asian countries (Kazakhstan and Tajikistan) which confirms its role as a local center of this recombinant spread within FSU. The scarcity of epidemiological data (regarding risk factors and human migration flows) made it impossible to clearly determine the driving-force behind the current CRF03_AB dissemination, but almost uncontrolled people migration between FSU countries and heterosexual contacts can greatly contribute to it. Hence, effective strategies aimed at the heterosexual active population, including the young people, are needed to reduce the future burden of HIV-infection.
</p>
