<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">
 <italic>E(Y</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t,i</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic>)</italic> represented the expected (number + 1) of new confirmed cases count on day 
 <italic>t</italic> in city 
 <italic>i</italic> where 
 <italic>i</italic> referred to different cities and 
 <italic>t</italic> was the day of the COVID-19 onset and was log-transformed into 
 <italic>log[E(Y</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t,i</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic>)]</italic> in Poisson regression automatically. α was the intercept. 
 <italic>Pollutant</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> denoted the daily moving average concentration of the compositive AQI and six pollutants (PM
 <sub>2.5</sub>, PM
 <sub>10</sub>, NO
 <sub>2</sub>, CO, SO
 <sub>2</sub>, O
 <sub>3</sub>) in single-pollutant models; β referred to the coefficients of those pollutants in the models. In addition, several covariates entered the model adjusting for potential confounding: (1) a smoothing spline of calendar 
 <italic>date</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> with 14 degrees of freedom (df
 <sub>1</sub>) per year controlled the potential long-term trend effect; (2) log-transformed new confirmed (cases + 1) on t-1 day entered the model controlling the serial correlation of the infectious disease (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020</xref>); (3) meteorological factors were controlled for the possible confounding effect, including a smoothing spline of mean 
 <italic>temperature</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t,i</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic>(°C)</italic> with 3° freedom (df2) and a linear term of mean 
 <italic>dewpoint temperature</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t,i</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic>(°C);</italic> (4) day of 
 <italic>week</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> was included as dummy variable to control for the week effect; (5) and 
 <italic>lockdown</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub>, effectively retarding the rapid spread of COVID-19, worked as categorical variable adjusting the national lock (since Jan 23rd, 2020) and unlock (until March 15, 2020) effect; (6) 
 <italic>city</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> variable adjusted for the fixed effects such as spatial correlation and population density. S (.) mean the smoothing spline to control for the non-linear relationship. Besides, relative risks (RRs) and 95% confidence intervals (95%CIs) were calculated by the coefficients and standard variances from GAMs models.
</p>
