<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The three arboviruses are transmitted by the two anthropophilic mosquitoes 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>. They are typical human-adapted arboviruses having lost the need for an enzootic cycle to trigger outbreaks [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Socio-economic changes affecting Tunisia these last decades have favored the rapid development of urban centers where conditions are met to favor the proliferation of domestic mosquitoes, multiple standing water as larval breeding sites and dense human populations as source for mosquito blood feeding [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Following the detection of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> in Algeria and Morocco in 2015, the Ministry of Health of Tunisia implemented a country wide mosquito survey from April 2015 to September 2018 in ports and airports [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> was detected in October 2018 in Carthage (20 km apart from the capital city of Tunis) facing the Italian islands of Pantelleria and Lampedusa where it was first identified in 2015 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In Tunisia, the most prevalent mosquito-borne virus is West Nile virus (
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>) with outbreaks reported in 1997 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], 2003 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], 2012 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Occasionally, Sandfly fever viruses (
 <italic>Phlebovirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Bunyaviridae</italic>) were detected [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] as well as Usutu virus (
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Therefore, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> may introduce a new chain of local transmission of DENV, CHIKV and ZIKV fostered by a high frequency of viremic travelers, high densities of competent vectors, and suitable environmental conditions. Tunisia is an open touristic country receiving each year 8 millions of tourists from all over the world and local population is immunologically naïve to the three arboviruses. Higher densities of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> in urban settings would be expected since the number of infested houses has increased in 2019 during the warm season (Bouattour A., com. pers) and as it is the case today in Algeria [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Thereby it seems critical to evaluate the susceptibility of a local 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> population to major arboviruses. Here we assessed the vector competence of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> Tunisia to CHIKV, DENV, and ZIKV using experimental infections to describe viral infection, dissemination and transmission.
</p>
