<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">SARS-CoV-2 belonging to 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> was first reported in 2019 in China, which has significant genetic characteristics distinguished from those of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV. The genome sequence of SARS-CoV-2 shares over 85% homology with that of bat SARS-CoV-like viruses (bat-SL-CoVZC45) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The infectious disease (COVID-19) caused by SARS-CoV-2 has similar clinical signs as SARS-CoV infection, including fever and respiratory symptoms, such as cough, sputum, shortness of breath, and breathing difficulties. Furthermore, COVID-19 patients present various digestive symptoms. However, reports on the incidence of gastrointestinal symptoms in COVID-19 patients vary widely. COVID-19-associated diarrhea occurrence has been reported at 3.0% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], 7.3% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], 10.1% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], 2.0% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], and 49.5% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] in different studies. A study from a single center in Wuhan on 305 patients reported approximately 22.2% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. In a large sample study of 1099 patients across China, the incidence of gastrointestinal symptoms was 3.8% for patients with diarrhea symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This discrepancy may be attributed to the different sample amounts of each study and the awareness of some mild gastrointestinal symptoms. In some cases, patients even presented with gastrointestinal symptoms alone at the early stage of onset, including anorexia, nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Thus, we should pay additional attention to mild GI symptom patients, and COVID-19 screening is strongly recommended for patients with GI symptoms in the epidemic region. The related gastrointestinal symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 may be associated with its receptor. The binding receptor in the human body for SARS-CoV-2 is ACE2, which is highly expressed in type II alveolar epithelial cells and esophageal epithelial cells, and high expression was also found in the ileum and colon [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The positive results of gastrointestinal tract samples provide evidence for enteric transmission. Elsewhere, the RNA test for the stool sample of the first COVID-19 patient in the United States showed positive results on day 7 after onset, suggesting the possibility of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in the digestive tract [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. A similar possibility was found in a study of sixty-two COVID-19 patients in China. There were two mild COVID-19 patients and two severe COVID-19 patients (6.5%) that showed positive results of the fecal RNA test, and only one of the four patients had diarrhea symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In another report, anal swabs from four patients were positive for RNA tests, of which two patients were positive for RNA tests for the esophagus, stomach, duodenum, and rectal mucosa samples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. These results indicate that SARS-CoV-2 has potential gastrointestinal transmission. In terms of pathological analysis, one autopsy report of a COVID-19 patient showed segmental dilatation and stenosis of the small intestine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Although autopsy and puncture tissue pathological samples are limited, pathological observations have shown that the mucosal epithelium of the esophagus, stomach, and intestine are degenerated, necrotic, and shed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. These studies suggest the possibility of SARS-CoV-2 directly affecting the intestinal mucosa and causing intestinal damage. Similar to the case for SARS-CoV, the detection results of different body part samples are not the same. It was reported that three patients with SARS-CoV-2 had a negative nucleic acid test on throat swab samples after treatment. However, their fecal nucleic acid test results were still positive [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], suggesting that in specimens from different sites, the nucleic acid conversion time is not synchronized and that the fecal nucleic acid positive duration may be longer. It tells us that there are some characteristics deserving attention in the diagnosis and quarantine of COVID-19 patients with gastrointestinal symptoms.
</p>
