<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The second wave of COVID‐19‐related dermatological publications was provoked by the concern to all patients with severe dermatological diseases who undergo treatment with biological agents or other types of immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory therapies.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Psoriasis vulgaris treated with biologics has already been reported to exacerbate from various infectious diseases like zika and dengue virus.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> Psoriasis was the first dermatosis during the COVID‐19 pandemic that drew the attention of dermatologists owing to the wide scope of cytotoxic or biological agents used for its treatment.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> Patients with hidradenitis suppurativa or other rare diseases who probably face similar problems were provided information on the necessary preventive measures and optional treatment regimens by the 
 <italic>European Reference Networks</italic> (ERN).
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Atopic dermatitis patients who demonstrate elevated risk of respiratory comorbidities were advised by the 
 <italic>European Academy of Dermatology and Venereology</italic> (
 <italic>EADV</italic>) task force on atopic dermatitis not to modify by themselves previously stable immune‐modulating or immunosuppressive therapies because of increased risk of relapses.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> Patients with autoimmune bullous dermatoses, especially those suffering from pemphigus and mucous membrane pemphigoid, were informed by the respective AIBD task force on the effects of systemic corticosteroids, steroid‐sparing agents, rituximab, and other treatment options during the COVID‐19 pandemic.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> Patients with connective tissue diseases on disease‐modifying antirheumatic drugs, biologics, or other immunosuppressive medications were advised to consult their rheumatologist and stop these drugs during an infection, while noninfected patients are required to continue their medication during the epidemic.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> Expert consensus‐based guidance was elaborated on the use of systemic immunosuppressive therapies for inflammatory skin diseases in children during COVID‐19 infection along with recommendations concerning the management of infantile hemangiomas.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> In the meanwhile, dermatologic surgeons and dermoscopists alarmed on the possible delay and risk of complications in diagnosing and treatment of nonmelanoma skin cancer, melanoma, and lymphoma.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> Reorganization of the work in dermatology units was proposed for maximum safety of both patients and staff.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus‐2 (SARS‐CoV‐2) took place among the streptococcal infections, varicella, measles, hepatitis B and C, and AIDS with which dermatologists are often in contact.
 <xref rid="ijd15189-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> Patient recommendations and guidelines on specific dermatological conditions during the COVID‐19 pandemic are detailed in Table 
 <xref rid="ijd15189-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
</p>
