<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Imaging investigations are vital for the management of COVID-19. Owing to the fast imaging speed and high-intensity resolution, chest CT, especially high-resolution CT, has become the preferred imaging modality for suspected COVID-19 cases or patients who have negative results on nucleic acid tests. Based on the lung imaging findings, COVID-19 can be divided into four stages. While there is overlap between the imaging manifestations of each stage, the findings in the critical stage are relatively specific [
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>]. In the early stage, diffuse subpleural GGOs or small nodular opacities can be found in both lungs, with interlobular septal thickening and fine grid-like shadows observed locally, with the lesions mostly located subpleurally in the lung periphery. In the progressive stage, the lesions undergo rapid progression and changes involving multiple lung lobes and spread from the periphery to the center of both lungs. Some GGOs will fuse into patches with a significant increase in intrapulmonary consolidation. In addition, the “crazy-paving” sign and air bronchograms can be observed, along with significant interlobular septal thickening that may be accompanied by fibrous cord-like shadows, often without pleural effusion. In the critical phase, lesions may increase by more than 50% within 48 h, and both lungs may show extensive or diffuse consolidation, even presenting with “white-out lung” in severe cases. Air bronchograms can still be observed locally and may be accompanied by a small amount of unilateral or bilateral pleural effusion; lymphadenopathy, meanwhile, is seldom observed. In the recovery stage, bilateral lesions are gradually absorbed and start shrinking, meanwhile, dispersed fibrous cord-like shadows can be observed, showing interstitial fibrotic changes. The imaging manifestations of the present case were consistent with those of previous reports. With respect to the above stages, the case reported here tended toward an imaging diagnosis of the progressive stage.
</p>
