<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> became the main vector of CHIKV following the selection of a single mutation (an amino-acid change at the position 226 in the E1 glycoprotein (E1-A226V); [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]). In Europe where 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> is established in 20 countries [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], this mosquito has been responsible since 2007, for local transmission of CHIKV, DENV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A prediction risk map based on vector competence data and vector distribution stresses the high risk of CHIKV epidemics in Europe associated with 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, more than with DENV and ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Collectively, European 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes require at least 2–3 days for viral transmission to occur after the infectious blood meal [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] as did mosquitoes from La Réunion with a maximum of 10
 <sup>3.3</sup> infectious viral particles at day 6 post-infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. When changing parameters such as the incubation temperature after the infectious blood meal or the CHIKV genotype used for mosquito infections [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], the outcome of infection became significantly different suggesting that the CHIKV transmission potential by 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> depends on the three-way combination of mosquito population, virus strain and temperature [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Indeed, when infected with the same CHIKV strain (06.21), transmission was higher for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> Tunisia than for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> from Morocco [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] but much lower when compared with mosquitoes from Cameroon [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] or Brazil [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. At 3 and 7 dpi, it has been demonstrated that a high CHIKV load in the midgut triggers viral transmission and not dissemination. The midgut seems to play a secondary role as a barrier compared to the salivary glands where active replication leads to a high transmission rate [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. In patients, CHIKV infections induce a high level of viremia ranging from 10
 <sup>4</sup>−10
 <sup>8</sup> RNA copies/mL [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and including the viral titer of the infectious blood meal used.
</p>
