<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ZIKV produced the first local cases in Europe (in France) in August 2019 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. This was unexpected as during the last Zika pandemic when hundreds of imported cases were reported in France in 2016 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], no autochthonous human cases were reported in France and more globally, in Europe. Three years later, in October 2019, while few active outbreaks of Zika were observed in the world, three autochthonous Zika cases were reported in the Var (France) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes from Europe require at least 7–14 days to excrete viral particles in saliva [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], which is consistent with our 10 days. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> Tunisia required less time to transmit ZIKV compared to 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> Morocco which needed 21 days [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Moreover, low relation was detected between viral loads in the three compartments, abdomen, head/thorax and saliva meaning that a threshold of viral loads was not the only condition required to trigger viral dissemination and transmission, at least in the pairing 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> Tunisia and Asian genotype of ZIKV. When infected with the Asian genotype of ZIKV, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes from France developed viral loads insufficiently high in midgut and salivary glands to trigger dissemination and then, transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. It has been shown that 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes from France transmit 10 to 20 times better the African genotype of ZIKV than the Asian genotype [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] stressing the specific outcome of each pairing mosquito population and virus strain [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Interestingly, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> from Cameroon transmit very efficiently the West African genotype of ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], a critical point that may contribute to increase opportunities for the West African ZIKV to be exported from the country 
 <italic>via</italic> viremic travelers as it happened with CHIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008475.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].
</p>
