<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0025">Patients with fever (oral temperature &gt; = 37.3 °C) or respiratory symptoms (cough, sputum, pharyngalgia, rhinorrhea, dyspnea, etc.) were advised to go to fever clinics for screening in Beijing. Peking Union Medical College Hospital (PUMCH) has a fever clinic for screening. Also, to strictly control the development of the epidemic situation of COVID-19, all patients with an epidemiologic history of COVID-19 (e.g. there was a history of travel or residence in Wuhan and its surrounding areas and communities with reported cases within two weeks before the onset of the disease; or within 14 days before the onset of the disease, contact with COVID-19 patients (with positive nucleic acid test); or within 14 days before the onset of the disease, contact with patients with fever and respiratory symptoms from Wuhan and its surrounding areas and communities with reported cases; or there was a clustering onset of disease) (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">National Health Commission of People’s Republic of China, 2020</xref>) were required to screen even though without fever or respiratory symptoms at PUMCH. Clustering onset was defined as two or more cases of fever and/or respiratory symptoms that were found in a small area such as family, office, school class, and other places within two weeks. Patient's medical records containing the symptoms, signs, epidemic history, etc., were taken by doctors. The epidemic history included
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0010">
  <list-item id="lsti0020">
   <label>(a)</label>
   <p id="par0030">contact with an epidemic area within two weeks before the onset of the disease;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0025">
   <label>(b)</label>
   <p id="par0035">contact with confirmed or suspected cases within two weeks before the onset of the disease;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0030">
   <label>(c)</label>
   <p id="par0040">contact with poultry, livestock or wild animals (especially dead animals) within two weeks before the onset of the disease;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0035">
   <label>(d)</label>
   <p id="par0045">clustering onset.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
