<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">Four human coronaviruses have been established as endemic: HCoV-NL63, HCoV-229E, HCoV-OC43, and HCoV-HKU1. These endemic strains have been identified as significant causes of acute respiratory infection and the common cold, causing 15% to 30% of respiratory tract infections each year.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Infection with endemic coronaviruses can be severe, and the first isolation of HCoV-NL63 and HCoV-HKU1 were from cases of bronchiolitis and pneumonia.
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Although these endemic coronaviruses have the potential to cause severe disease, which is largely associated with immunocompromising conditions or young age,
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> these viruses received scant attention because of their association with milder disease in immunocompetent individuals. The outbreak of SARS in China in 2002 to 2003 highlighted the potential of these and/or related viruses to cause outbreaks of severe disease, because more than 8000 cases were diagnosed with close to a 10% case fatality rate.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> This highly pathogenic strain that is thought to be transmitted to humans by direct contact with market civets
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> was controlled after the 2003 outbreak with no additional cases reported since 2004. In 2012, another highly pathogenic coronavirus, MERS-CoV, was isolated from a patient with fatal pneumonia in Saudi Arabia.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> This virus was traced to dromedary camels. Apparently, frequent transmission events of this virus to this Middle East species of camel have occurred.
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> This virus has affected 2494 individuals, with new cases being diagnosed every month, mainly from Saudi Arabia (WHO-MERS-CoV), with a case fatality rate higher than SARS-CoV (∼35%).
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> In December 2019, a novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) was first isolated from the city of Wuhan, China, and rapidly millions of cases were reported from almost every country in the world. This most novel coronavirus was characterized by extensive spread and apparently higher infectivity or more efficient human-to-human transmission. At the time of this submission (July 1, 2020), 511,860 deaths were associated with COVID-19 of a total of 10,501,482 confirmed global cases (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html" id="intref0010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html</ext-link>).
</p>
