<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Early diagnosis is vital for pregnant women with a hantavirus infection since it leads to early and more effective treatment, as well as a better clinical outcome. Accurate diagnosis usually relies on clinical manifestations and laboratory tests. Exploring the history of exposure in the epidemic area is also essential for a precise diagnosis. The typical clinical manifestations of HFRS are fever, hemorrhage, hyperemia, hypotensive shock and kidney damage accompanied by clinical symptoms, such as hematuria, proteinuria, and disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) (Lazzerini 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2017</xref>). Similar to the general population, the typical clinical course of HFRS in pregnant women is divided into the following: Fever period (3–7 days), hypotensive period (hours to 2 days), oliguria (3–7 days), polyuria (several days to weeks), and recovery period (2–3 months) (Vaheri 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2013</xref>; Latus 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2015</xref>; Connolly-Andersen 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2014</xref>). The clinical symptoms of HPS include flu-like symptoms in the prodromal stage (5 days), subsequent acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), bilateral diffuse interstitial pulmonary edema, respiratory failure, as well as non-cardiogenic shock (Duchin 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1994</xref>; Khan 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1996</xref>; Hallin 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1996</xref>; Macneil 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2011</xref>). Molecular, immunochemical, and serological examination contribute to routine laboratory tests (Zou 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2016</xref>). IgM/IgG antibodies against the Gn and Gc of hantaviruses are often used to aid the diagnosis (Hedman 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1991</xref>).
</p>
