<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Naked HEV particles possibly attach to target cells via heparin sulfate proteoglycans (HSGPs) [
 <xref rid="B59-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and heat shock cognate protein 70 (HSC70) [
 <xref rid="B60-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Integrin α3 has been described recently [
 <xref rid="B61-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] as a candidate receptor to mediate entry into the cells by dynamin-dependent, clathrin-mediated endocytosis, supported by the GTPases Ras-related proteins Rab5A (RAB5) and Rab7a (RAB7), which are necessary for quasi-enveloped particle internalization [
 <xref rid="B59-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Quasi-enveloped particles attach less efficiently to cells and likely enter the cell in a manner similar to exosomes [
 <xref rid="B63-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Not requiring HSGPs allows attachment in a non-cell-specific manner, possibly explaining HEV’s capacity to infect extrahepatic tissues [
 <xref rid="B63-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Following this, lysosomal degradation of the lipid membrane (in the case of enveloped particles) and subsequent viral capsid uncoating take place, followed by release of the genomic HEV positive strand RNA into the cytoplasm [
 <xref rid="B63-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The host cellular transcriptional machinery translates ORF1 polyprotein containing RdRp from HEV RNA. The polymerase transcribes the full-length negative-sense HEV RNA. From this negative strand, two RNAs are transcribed by RNA helicases and RdRp to form a full-length genomic RNA and a 2.2 kb bicistronic subgenomic RNA. These two capped and polyadenylated RNAs serve as templates for the translation of non-structural ORF1 polyproteins, ORF2 capsid proteins, and polyfunctional ORF3 proteins [
 <xref rid="B64-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].
</p>
