<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The subsequent steps are viral assembly and release. ORF2 and ORF3 and positive-sense genomic HEV RNA are known to form a complex in the ER–Golgi intermediate compartment and produce viral progeny particles [
 <xref rid="B65-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The particles of the progeny virus bind to the TSG101 protein and are secreted in a presumably basal fashion as enveloped particles [
 <xref rid="B47-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. When leaving hepatocytes from the apical part, the envelope is stripped as described above [
 <xref rid="B56-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. There are many significant gaps in the understanding of the HEV life cycle and virus–host cell interactions [
 <xref rid="B67-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], and further studies are urgently needed. Several in vitro systems exist to study the virus. Reverse genetics models based on infectious cDNA clones have been described for several genotypes. The most commonly used are the Sar-55-related genotype 1 clone [
 <xref rid="B68-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], the genotype 3a and 3c Kernow-C1- [
 <xref rid="B69-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], and 47832-related [
 <xref rid="B70-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] clones, respectively, both of which contain insertions in the HVR, and the genotype 4 TW6196 clone [
 <xref rid="B71-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. A recent presentation of a novel in vitro method to produce high viral titers, allowing study of the full HEV replication cycle in cell culture, has additionally created confidence that we may overcome our limited understanding of HEV pathophysiology [
 <xref rid="B72-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Although these systems are most commonly used in conventional cell culture systems, several animal infection models have been developed. Rhesus monkeys have been shown to be susceptible to HEV-1 through -4 [
 <xref rid="B28-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], while cynomolgous monkeys and chimpanzees have been used as models for HEV-1 and -2 [
 <xref rid="B68-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. As natural hosts for HEV-3 and -4, pigs can be readily infected by strains of these genotypes [
 <xref rid="B75-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Recent reports have also described successful infection of human liver chimeric mice with HEV-1 and -3 strains [
 <xref rid="B77-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Moreover, small animal and avian models exist for the study of animal HEV. Although animal infection models provide more physiological conditions than cell culture systems, limitations are also present. Neither non-human primates nor mice represent natural hosts of HEV, while pigs can only be infected with HEV-3 and -4. Experiments with primates also raise ethical concerns.
</p>
