<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0140">The fact that viral infection (including viral sepsis) 
 <xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref> remains the key driver of the pathogenesis of COVID-19 has fueled research exploring the efficacy of antiviral medications in patients with severe or critical illness. Taking into account the findings from 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>
 <xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0415" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0420" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref>, lopinavir/ritonavir, remdesivir, and chloroquine (previously intended for the treatment of Ebola virus or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infections) have been repurposed for combating SARS-CoV-2 infection. In a randomized clinical trial conducted in the early stage of the epidemic in China, patients with severe COVID-19 were assigned to receive standard-of-care alone or in combination with a 14-day course of treatment with lopinavir/ritonavir 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. Neither the duration from randomization to clinical improvement nor the mortality rate differed significantly between the treatment group and the control group. Subsequently, in another double-blinded clinical trial, patients with severe COVID-19 were randomly allocated to receive standard-of-care alone or in combination with 10 d of remdesivir 
 <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. Again, there was no significant difference in the time to clinical improvement, which was the primary endpoint of the study. Neither lopinavir/ritonavir nor remdesivir markedly reduced viral loads, as monitored dynamically throughout the two trials. Several reasons could have accounted for these negative findings. It was notable that patients entered the clinical trials after a median duration of 11–13 d, which could have diminished the efficacy as compared with earlier administration of the drugs. In fact, early administration of lopinavir/ritonavir (within 10 d of symptom onset) has been associated with a shorter course of viral shedding 
 <xref rid="b0415" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>. Moreover, both of these trials might have been underpowered for statistical analysis due to the emergency of the outbreak and the premature cessation of patient recruitment (there was difficulty in recruiting sufficient patients once the epidemiologic curve has flattened within Wuhan). Nevertheless, the results did not preclude the use of lopinavir/ritonavir and remdesivir for severe cases of COVID-19. Both trials indicated a numerically faster time to clinical improvement in the treatment group 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref> and, in a more recent clinical trial, administration of remdesivir for 10 d was associated with a faster time to clinical improvement and a lower mortality rate by 14 d, as compared with the placebo group 
 <xref rid="b0430" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref>. Furthermore, when administered in combination with IFN-β and ribavirin, lopinavir/ritonavir has been associated with a marked reduction in viral loads compared with usual care alone 
 <xref rid="b0435" ref-type="bibr">[87]</xref>. Therefore, combined antiviral medications might have a role in accelerating viral clearance in patients with COVID-19. Several other candidate medications have also been tested in clinical settings for COVID-19. The effects of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine on patients with COVID-19 remain under debate. While chloroquine effectively reduced viral loads and achieved negative conversion of viral assays in hospitalized patients 
 <xref rid="b0440" ref-type="bibr">[88]</xref>, the administration of hydroxychloroquine failed to increase the probability of achieving negative conversion of viral assays by 28 d in patients with mild-to-moderate COVID-19 
 <xref rid="b0420" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref>. In a pilot open-label study, favipiravir was shown to markedly shorten the time to viral clearance and increase the rate of improvement in chest imaging compared with a combination treatment with lopinavir/ritonavir plus IFN-α inhalation 
 <xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>. This finding added to the scientific evidence on candidate medications with potent antiviral activities.
</p>
