<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0170">Traditional Chinese medicine has been a treasure trove of complementary medicine. Efforts have been made to explore the effects of a panel of herbal formulas for the management of SARS and influenza. For example, Lianhuaqingwen (LH) capsule has been approved for the treatment of mild-to-moderate SARS 
 <xref rid="b0535" ref-type="bibr">[107]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0540" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>. Therefore, priority could be given to the development of LH capsules, because off label marketing medications would help reduce the time for research and development (R&amp;D) against other candidate medications in the pipeline. In an in vitro study, LH capsule yielded potent antiviral effects against SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="b0545" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>. Based on these observations, a multicenter randomized clinical trial was undertaken to determine the effectiveness of LH capsule plus usual care, versus usual care alone 
 <xref rid="b0550" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>. At Day 14, treatment with LH capsule was associated with a significantly higher rate of symptom recovery and a markedly shortened time to symptom recovery, although no differences in the viral loads were observed between the two groups. It is notable that these therapeutic effects might not be related to the antiviral effects because the serum concentrations of LH capsule were markedly lower than those reported in the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study in which the antiviral effects were potent 
 <xref rid="b0545" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>. LH capsules also exhibited anti-inflammatory and anti-oxidative effects via suppressing cytokine release, according to the results from an 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study 
 <xref rid="b0550" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>. These findings have resulted in the endorsement of LH capsules by the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China for the treatment of mild-to-moderate COVID-19 
 <xref rid="b0530" ref-type="bibr">[106]</xref>. Apart from LH capsules, other candidate herbal formulas such as Xuebijing injection and Liu Shen capsule have demonstrated antiviral activities against SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="b0555" ref-type="bibr">[111]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0560" ref-type="bibr">[112]</xref>. Multicenter clinical trials to determine the efficacy of these herbal formulas (i.e., Xuebijing injection for severe or critically ill cases with COVID-19) are now underway.
</p>
