<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">In early 1990s, HIV-1 Thai subtypes B′ and C were co-circulated among injection drug users (IDUs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] in Yunnan province in southwestern China bordering the ‘Golden Triangle’, leading to active inter-subtype recombination which generated CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC, and a large number of unique recombinant forms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In the initial period, drug trafficking activities were considered to be responsible for the rapid spread of CRF07_BC and CRF08_BC across China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. From 1978, as commercial sex activity increased across the country [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], the proportion of newly reported HIV infections/acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS) patients through heterosexual transmission increased dramatically. Nowadays, CRF07_BC and CRF08_BC have become the most epidemic strains in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and drug-driven epidemic has been shifting to sexually transmission-driven epidemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. There were other B/C CRFs reported in the last few years, such as CRF57_BC (identified in Baoshan, Western Yunnan) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], CRF62_BC and CRF64_BC (identified in Ruili/Dehong, Western Yunnan) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. However, there was scarce evidence that such B/C recombinant forms had spread to other areas. In 2016, we reported a novel B/C recombinant form, CRF85_BC, among heterosexually infected patients in southern Sichuan (Yibin city) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. CRF85_BC was then reported in Anhui [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], Yunnan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and Northern Sichuan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] (Guangyuan City). Due to lack of B or C epidemic history in the local high-risk population, the origin and the spread of CRF85_BC was still to be investigated.
</p>
