<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">In COVID-19, as medical staff, it is our undeniable responsibility and obligation to save patients, but this does not mean that medical staff need to make huge and unnecessary sacrifices. As Donatella Lippi once said, we had a great understanding of what infections were and the skills and technology to overcome them. However, doctors, and all healthcare professionals (reflecting the multidisciplinary nature of disease management) still took risks when dealing with pandemics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Also, the emergency medical professionals who were at the anti-epidemic frontline were confronting multi-faceted challenges from the unknown nature of the disease, highly-intensive line of work, family, external public opinion, patients and their families [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Under such special circumstances, monetary compensation is not of top priority, but rather the available of proven and effective protective gears and equipment. The government and hospitals have the responsibility to protect medical staff. Based on the resolution recommended by the COVID-19 expert group, the ED should be supplied with highest-level personal protective equipment. Medical staff in the ED need to be provided with a sufficient supply of medical protective masks, working caps, disposable isolation clothing, goggles, latex gloves and other protective equipment. To effectively relieve the psychological stress of emergency medical staff and ensure everyone's physical and mental health, PKUFH actively responded to the request of the NHC to integrate psychological crisis intervention into the overall deployment of epidemic prevention and control to alleviate the psychological stress caused by the epidemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. By providing emotional support and psychological intervention, the psychological stress of emergency medical staff was effectively relieved.
</p>
