<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Transmission is the central principle in biology and epidemiology of infectious diseases, and for many viruses, the transmission from animals to humans is one of the critical steps in the pathogenesis. SARS-COV-2 owns 96% ribonucleic acid similarity to the coronavirus isolated from 
 <italic>Rhinolophus sinicus</italic> in Yunnan province, China,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]
 </sup> with origins traceable to a local seafood wholesale market in Wuhan, China. Bats may be the original reservoir of the virus with animals sold on the market by the intermediate hosts,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]
 </sup> it is human and animal comorbidity ability remains exploration. The prime source of infection understood presently is patients with SARS-COV-2 infection, and those asymptomatic infected individuals may also become the source of infection. Transrespiratory droplet and contact transmission are the main routes of transmission. SARS-COV-2 has an S protein structure similar to SARS-CoV, which can bind to angiotensin-converting enzyme II (ACE2),
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
  <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
  <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]
 </sup> a cellular receptor in humans, to infect cells, it has been shown that ACE2 expression is especially abundant in lung and small intestinal tissues.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]
 </sup> On February 13, 2020, personnel from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention isolated 2 novel coronaviruses from the feces of confirmed patients, demonstrating that there was indeed a live virus in the feces, which further suggested that we had the possibility of oral transmission of SARS-COV-2. Whether aerosol or mother-to-child transmission is possible also needs to be further clarified. From the current dissemination rate to its interpersonal transmission ability, the population is generally susceptible. By further studying the affinity of SARS-COV-2 to ACE2, it may be possible to verify its transmission capacity. The first survey by the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention found that the average incubation period of this virus was about 5.2 days, with a maximum of fewer than 14 days, and the basic reproduction number was estimated to be 2.2,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]
 </sup> which predicted the infectivity of SARS-COV-2, which provided first-hand data for human understanding of the epidemiological characteristics of SARS-COV-2, but epidemiological data may be continuously updated based on the increase of patients and a series of national prevention and control measures. Continue to monitor the epidemiological characteristics of more patients, closely investigate the source of the virus and intermediate hosts, and pay attention to its future evolutionary direction, adaptability, transmission ability, and route, all of which play a considerable role in guiding the prevention and control of the epidemic.
</p>
