<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="FU2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIGURE 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Axial CT (
   <bold>A</bold>), fused FDG PET/CT (
   <bold>B</bold>), and FDG PET (
   <bold>C</bold>) images. On axial PET/CT fusion images, the FDG avidity was highest in the solid part of the mixed ground-glass opacities and consolidation lesions. The SUV
   <sub>max</sub> was measured at a maximum of 8.1 in the left lower lobe. A viral pneumopathy was suspected. Metabolic complete remission of the lymphoma was confirmed. The patient had no fever and no clinical symptoms suggestive of infection. She returned home with instructions to stay isolated and to call in case of fever or any other symptoms. Twenty-eight hours later, she had sudden high fever. She was admitted because of mild neutropenia (1.34 G/L) and severe lymphocytopenia (0.04 G/L). Nasopharyngeal swab was positive for COVID-19. She had no oxygen requirement. Fever resolved within 5 days. Chest CT scan manifestations of COVID-19 infections are well known with data on more than 2000 patients.
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–
    <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
   </sup> Most frequent patterns are ground-glass opacities, consolidation or combination of both. Interlobular septal thickening, reticular pattern, crazy paving, bronchial wall thickening, pleural thickening, pleural effusion, nodules, reversed halo sign, pericardial effusion, and lymphadenopathies are additional possible manifestations. PET/CT aspects are poorly known with only 5 cases reported in literature.
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
    <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
   </sup> Qin et al
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
   </sup> reported FDG PET/CT aspects of 4 patients with a COVID-19 infection. Ground-glass opacities were present in all patients; consolidation and interlobular septal thickening were present in one case each. Three patients also had FDG-positive lymph nodes localized in hilar, mediastinal, subclavicular, or supraclavicular regions. SUV
   <sub>max</sub> of the lung lesions ranged from 4.6 to 12.2. Zou and Zhu
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
   </sup> reported FDG PET/CT aspects in a febrile patient with suspicion of malignancy on a chest CT. SUV
   <sub>max</sub> of the lung lesion was 4.9. Paratracheal and hilar lymph nodes were noted. Although there is no indication for PET/CT in COVID-19–infected patients, our case shows this infection can be discovered incidentally on surveillance PET/CT. In the context of the COVID epidemic, avid FDG ground-glass opacities, consolidation or combination of both patterns, require investigations to identify a potential COVID-19 infection.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="rlu-publish-ahead-of-print-10.1097.rlu.0000000000003144-g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
