<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">Solar UV photons with wavelength in the range 200–290 nm (UV-C radiation) photochemically interact with DNA and RNA and are endowed with germicidal properties that are also effective on viruses (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Kowalski, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Rauth, 1965</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Kesavan and Sagripanti, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">McDevitt et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Walker and Ko, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Tseng and Li, 2005</xref>). Fortunately, UV-C photons are filtered out by the ozone layer of the upper atmosphere, at around 35 km (e.g. 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Walker and Ko, 2007</xref>). Softer UV photons from the Sun with wavelengths in the range 290–320 nm (UV-B) and 320–400 nm (UV-A), however, do reach the Earth's surface. The effect of these photons on single- and double-stranded RNA and DNA viruses (e.g. 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Lytle and Sagripanti, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Lubin and Jensen, 1995</xref>) and the possible role they play on the seasonality of epidemics (e.g. 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Martinez, 2018</xref>), are nevertheless little studied. In two companion papers, we present a number of concurring circumstantial pieces of evidence suggesting that the evolution and strength of the recent severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS-Cov-2) pandemic (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cobey, 2020</xref>) might have been modulated by the intensity of UV-B and UV-A solar radiation hitting different regions of the Earth during the diffusion of the outbreak between January and July 2020 (
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nicastro et al., 2020</xref>, submitted) and provide a measurement of the lethal UV-C dose for COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Bianco et al., 2020</xref>, submitted).
</p>
