<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Corona and dengue, both viruses are coexisting currently in the dengue‐endemic countries. Therefore, the coinfection of these viruses to the patients has been reported recently in different dengue‐endemic countries like Singapore, Thailand, India, and Bangladesh. As an extremely unique occurrence, Singapore at first confirmed two patients who were coinfected with both corona and dengue virus.
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> In Thailand, a man who also had dengue died from coronavirus infection.
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Also, an old patient with coinfection of dengue and corona died in India.
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, two patients from Bangladesh were coinfected with both corona and dengue and one of them died.
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> Hence, it can be speculated that coinfection cases may be increased in the upcoming days as peak dengue season. Coinfection poses a challenge for accurate diagnosis and treatment, particularly when symptoms such as fever and aches are similar for several viral diseases like COVID‐19 and dengue. The distinction can be made with disease progresses. In fact, the symptoms of these viral diseases begin with fever. Guan et al
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> in their recent study reported that fever, cough, and headache were observed as the most common symptoms for patients with COVID‐19
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> whereas fever, headache, and skin rash were observed for patients with dengue. Besides, patient with COVID‐19 could present with a rash that was mistaken for dengue.
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> The clinical and laboratory features of both dengue and COVID‐19 are quite identical, and therefore, it is difficult to distinguish. In Singapore, patient with COVID‐19 produced false‐positive dengue results in rapid serological test.
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> Thus, a new symptom of COVID‐19 was discovered where the patient was suspected of suffering from dengue. The report warned that patients with COVID‐19 were wrongly considered as dengue resulting a delay in diagnosis of corona infection and further spread of the virus.
 <xref rid="jmv26269-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
