<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">Perhaps due to persuasive findings in MHV models of demyelination, there have been more studies of coronavirus in the brains of patients with MS than for any other HCoV-associated neurologic syndrome (Burks et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1980</xref>; Stewart et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">1992</xref>; Murray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">1992b</xref>; Cristallo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1997</xref>; Arbour et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2000</xref>; Dessau et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2001</xref>). The first isolation of coronavirus from MS was reported in 1980, when 2 of 13 human brain homogenates inoculated into weanling mice produced either CNS disease (isolate SD) or cytopathic effects in cell culture (isolate SK) (Burks et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1980</xref>). Neutralizing antibodies to isolate SK were detected in CSF and sera of both patients, however, neutralizing antibodies were also detected in 85% of normal controls, albeit in lower titer than in individuals with MS (Burks et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1980</xref>). Isolate SD produced demyelination with intracerebral inoculation into primates, with detection of virus in the white matter, meninges, and choroid plexus, although the monkeys remained clinically asymptomatic (Murray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1992a</xref>). In 1992, coronavirus was identified in plaque and non-plaque regions of 12 of 22 brains with MS; 5 brains were reactive for HCoV-OC43 and none for HCoV-229E (Murray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">1992b</xref>). In another study, HCoV-229E but not HCoV-OC43 was detected in MS brain tissues (Stewart et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">1992</xref>). Neither study detected coronavirus in normal control brains. In the largest series, encompassing 39 brains with MS, 26 with other neurological diseases, and 25 controls, both species were detected with an overall prevalence of 44% for HCoV-229E and 23% for HCoV-OC43; however, viruses were identified in all patient groups, albeit with greater frequency in MS (Arbour et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2000</xref>). Both viruses have also been detected in CSF samples in patients with MS and other CNS disorders (Cristallo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1997</xref>). In contrast to these studies, HCoVs 229E and OC43 could not be reliably detected in a single study of 25 MS and 36 control human brains, using nested RT-PCR (Dessau et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2001</xref>). Thus, while variably present in the human CNS, HCoVs OC43 and 229E cannot be considered specific to demyelinating pathology, raising questions about what aspects of infection might be relevant to human neuropathogenesis.
</p>
