<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">There is also limited data on the neuropathology of the epidemic viruses (Gu and Korteweg 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2007</xref>). In 4 patients, SARS-CoV protein and nucleic acids were detected in neurons of an unspecified region of the cerebral cortex but not in the cerebellum; the authors estimated that fewer than 24% of cells demonstrated evidence of infection and did not further characterize brain histopathology (Ding et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2004</xref>). In a series of 8 brains, all demonstrated viral nucleic acid in numerous neurons of an again unspecified region of cerebral cortex, as well as in hypothalamus (Gu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2005</xref>). In this series, edema and selective neuronal necrosis were described in 6 of the 8 patients, and there was no mention of inflammatory infiltration. A 13th autopsied individual with SARS demonstrated edema and selective neuronal necrosis; staining for N protein in neurons as well as unspecified “glia” was reported, again in the absence of mononuclear or lymphoid inflammation (Xu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2005</xref>). Finally, an electron microscopic study of the brain of a single patient dying with COVID-19 has been published, demonstrating viral-like particles in endothelial vesicles and perivascular cell processes (Mondolfi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2020</xref>). While vascular localization of SARS-CoV-2 is consistent with the brain distribution of ACE2, it is hard to draw conclusions from a single case report. With regard to SARS-CoV, autopsy localization of virus in neuronal cytoplasm coupled with viral detection in the CSF from patients with seizures may suggest that in a subset of individuals, neuronal infection is a significant pathology—as it is in animal models. Recently, a manuscript has been deposited in medRxiv describing the microscopic findings in 20 brains from patients dying with COVID-19 disease (Bryce et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>). Widespread thrombi in microvessels with acute infarction was the most prominent finding, present in 30%; it is unclear if this pathology reflects the DIC-like syndrome often seen in terminal COVID-19 disease, or selective viral targeting of brain microvasculature (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Other findings included large parenchymal infarcts, hemorrhages, global anoxia, and, in general, sparse inflammation. Two brains with single foci of T cell infiltration were also described, but the significance of this was unclear, and the authors stressed the lack of evidence for meningoencephalitis. In contrast, a single case report describing infarcts, acute hemorrhages with axonal disruption, macrophage infiltrates, and ADEM, with regions of perivascular myelin loss accompanied by macrophages, has also been published in a patient dying with COVID-19 (Reichard et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2020</xref>). Neither of these reports of COVID-19 neuropathology entailed assays for CNS virus. Thus, as these viruses continue to evolve and emerge, their potential neurovirulence needs greater investigation, both in animal models and in their human hosts.
</p>
