<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Briefly, we conducted a search in Russian Science Citation Index (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.elibrary.ru/project_rsci.asp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.elibrary.ru/project_rsci.asp</ext-link>) and PubMed (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://https.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://https.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/</ext-link>) for a depth of 22 years. Search strategy in databases: (subtype *) &amp; (HIV) &amp; (recombinant *) &amp; (genotype *). Additionally, a search was carried out in Google. Scholar for the above search query, as well as manual search in bibliographic lists from the articles found. In total, 794 potentially relevant articles were identified from the search. These articles were then independently evaluated by two authors for compliance to the article review topics based on the title or abstract, duplicating etc. Published studies were enrolled if they were the following criteria: (i) articles included reports of HIV-1 subtypes in FSU; (ii) the studies included HIV-1 CRF03-AB positive people; (iii) subtyping method was clear and specific, using sequencing and phylogenetic tree analysis; (iiii) sample size of the study was more than 5 with clear and specific information for location of study (territory), material collection dates and reported prevalence of CRF03_AB. Reports of single specific subtype, duplicating publications and studies reporting conflicting data were excluded. Detailed information on the exclusion criteria is provided in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0241269.s001">S1 Fig</xref>. As a result, after removing the duplicates 637 articles remained. Of these, 535 articles were excluded after screening the titles and abstracts as not eligible, and 44 articles are not available in full texts; the full-texts were obtained for 58 articles. From these selected articles, 26 were also excluded (23 due to inconsistency with the subject of the review; 3 due to unsuitability of the data for analysis). Finally, 32 studies containing relevant data were included into the final study (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0241269.s006">S1 Table</xref>). At first, we conducted a systematic review and meta-regression analysis to CRF03_AB prevalence in Russia, for which all in-Russia studies were divided into 6 subgroups in accordance with the federal districts (Northwestern, Siberian, Far Eastern, Central, Ural and Volga). Then, we estimated the CRF03_AB prevalence in northwestern FSU countries, including northwestern federal district of Russia.
</p>
