<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Virus entry to the human cells is initiated by binding of the viral spike protein to the affected human cell particularly alveolar epithelial cells. After entering the cell, the viral genome causes an alteration in the genetic expression of the host cell so as to generate accessory proteins which help the coronavirus to further develop and spread to other host cells. Earlier similar viral epidemics like SARS and MERS affected the cells by binding to their Angiotensin-converting enzyme receptor-2 on the cellular membrane in case of SARS infection and dipeptidyl peptidase -4 enzyme receptor in case of MERS, which facilitated the entry as well as the propagation of the viral particles.[
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Viral RNA after entering the cell starts using host machinery in the cytoplasm to make new viral proteins. Genomic RNA is encapsulated and polyadenylated and encrypts various structural and non-structural polypeptide genes. These polyproteins are fragmented by proteases that display chymotrypsin-like activity.[
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] The resulting complex drives (-) RNA production through both replication and transcription to encoding structural proteins.[
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Virions are formed by the combination of the viral nucleocapsid as well proteins which are synthesized by the host cell (which in COVID-19 is the alveolar epithelial cell). They enter the endoplasmic reticulum from where the virions bud off the cytoplasm of the host cell by exocytosis and are released into the bloodstream. These virion particles later infect other organs like the liver, kidney, intestine, and other parts of the respiratory tract.[
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] COVID-19 has a higher rate of transmission as compared to the MERS and SARS infections as the former shows a higher replication rate (R0) which leads to its faster spread in the human population.[
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Recently, it has been suggested that a spillover of the viral particles from Bats with Pangolin as an intermediate host has led to the viral outbreak in the human population. This depends upon the ACE2 receptor similarity in these animals and some resemblance to the human population.[
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]
</p>
