<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A healthy 27-year-old Egyptian woman, Ms A, worked as a translator for two Chinese managers of a Japan-based designer brand whose manufacturing capacity is in China. The first manager was a 54-year-old female, Ms B, with business duties in multiple African countries. The second manager was a 36-year-old male, Mr C, with responsibility for the Egyptian market. Both managers and Ms A travelled on business to China from 5 to 18 January 2020 (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1</xref>). Ms A and Ms B were in Guangzhou while Mr C went to Wuhan. The three travellers reunited on 18 January in Guangzhou for their return trip to Egypt. On 19 January, Mr C went to his workplace in Cairo with severe influenza-like symptoms, including fever and cough. Despite his obvious illness, Mr C worked in the office the whole day, sharing a workspace with three employees, including Ms A and a third Chinese manager, Mr D, age 37 years. On 20 January 20, Mr C was still ill with respiratory symptoms and fever and he isolated himself, given his history of recent travel to Wuhan. Ms B shared the same dwelling as Mr C and Mr D, but all three occupied different rooms. Ms B secured a service to disinfect the home and change the furniture, given the illness of Mr C. On 24 January 24, Ms B developed a fever, cough and sore throat, suggesting a respiratory illness. Mr D then fell ill with respiratory disease on an unspecified date. Ms A remained asymptomatic. In late January there were no coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) diagnostic tests available in Egypt. Ms B and Mr C returned to Guangzhou on 4 February 2020. Mr C recovered completely but Ms B suffered from persistent cough and was confirmed as a COVID-19 case on 11 February based on a reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction test in China. It seems likely that both Mr C and Ms B were the first COVID-19 cases in Egypt, although they were never registered in Egypt as cases, given their return to China.
</p>
