<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is no specific treatment as of now for the novel coronavirus infection. Usually, the symptomatic patients are given supportive care with adequate hydration as well as the use of antipyretics for fever. Severe cases need mechanical intubation and ventilation so that the regular supply of oxygen is maintained in debilitated lungs affected by the coronavirus. Clinical trials for the possible drugs have also begun in many countries for regulatory approval. Some researchers also link to a promising co-relation between Bacillus Calmette-Guérin vaccine and its beneficial effect on increasing immunity against coronavirus however, WHO has yet to verify this claim. Research is going on related to many antivirals that can prove effective in tackling coronavirus like- remdesivir, lopinavir, ritonavir, favipiravir, etc., Trials are also going on regarding hydroxychloroquine in the treatment of coronavirus affected patients. Recently in China, a randomized human trial was carried out in relation to remdesivir, which failed to improve the condition in many patients.[
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] FDA, as well as other regulatory agencies, are still working on the development of a vaccine for the general public against this virus.[
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] Plasmapheresis is also being carried out for using the convalescent serum antibodies of the coronavirus healed patients and providing it to serious patients, which has met with some success rate in a few nations.[
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] It is extremely important that different types of pneumonia as well as respiratory distress, for example, associated with influenza, bacteria's as well mycoplasma, etc., are also differentiated from coronavirus acute respiratory distress syndrome since the treatment for them will be entirely different which is vital for the physicians especially working in intensive care units. For handling coronavirus epidemic all the medical health professionals should be aware of proper barrier technique as well they should be equipped with rapid diagnostic methods which have high specificity as well as sensitivity since it has been reported that around 40% of cases are asymptomatic who turn out to be positive later on but are infectious in the early stages also. It is imperative to understand the importance of pathogenesis and modes of transmission of coronavirus before treatment is devised. This review presented important points that will help in diagnosing and in turn handling serious as well as susceptible patients in a better manner by our primary health care officials who are facing this crisis in the frontline. As of now human trials for a vaccine for COVID-19 is still in progress, it will be all the more critical to reduce the morbidity as well as mortality associated with this disease by early diagnosis and quarantine. It is also important to keep in mind about the comorbid conditions of the elderly since those make them vulnerable to the viral attack and subsequent mortality. This article also provides a clue to the replication rate as well as genomic know-how of this particular virus which is important in assessing the community spread of the outbreak as well as the importance of polymerase chain reaction, which currently is the only technique that is providing a specific result using CoV genomic sequences and describes the relation between other similar outbreaks of SARS and MERS, which will help the frontline medical professionals in developing treatment strategies in similar lines to these epidemics which happened in the past.
</p>
