<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0270">If a fragment of a fragile and loosely held carbonaceous meteorite carrying a cargo of trillions of viruses/bacteria and other primary source cells (for the cosmic replication of the COVID-19 virus), may have entered the mesosphere and stratosphere at high speed ~ 30 km/s, its outer, loosely-held envelope carrying a biological cargo may have got dispersed in the mesosphere stratosphere and troposphere. Indeed, a much larger original meteoroid could easily have been fragmenting and dispersing its contents before the ignition of the fireball event. A reasonable assumption is that the fireball which struck 2000 km N of Wuhan may have been part of a wide tube of debris the bulk of which was deposited in the stratosphere to fall over Wuhan. The fall time through the atmosphere of 1–10 μm-sized solid particles could range from a few months to well over a year on the basis of straightforward calculations (e.g., in the Appendix of 
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Hoyle &amp; Wickramasinghe, 1979</xref> “Diseases from space”). Because dispersal at ground level depends on the vagaries of meteorology and precipitation the deposition of virus at ground level is expected to be patchy in regard to both time and place. This is certainly consistent (thus far) with what has happened in relation to the new COVID-19 coronavirus epidemic between November 2019 and the present day (February 15, 2020). Following the initial deposition of infective particles in a small localized region (e.g., Wuhan, Hubei province, China) particles that have already become dispersed over a wider area in the troposphere will fall to ground in a higgledy-piggledy manner, and this process could be extended over a typical timescale of 1–2 years until an initial inoculant of the infective agent would be drained. This accords well with many new strains of viruses including influenza that have appeared in recent years (
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Wickramasinghe et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
