<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">The wide variety of clinical symptoms characterizing COVID-19 patients makes extremely difficult to establish a genotype-to-phenotype link. This knowledge is crucial for understanding infectious mechanisms used by SARS-CoV-2 and directing the strategy for drug and vaccine development. Therefore, studying the mutational impact of viral isolates in vitro becomes fundamental to this aim. The high viral load detected in nasopharyngeal swab obtained lately in the Italian epidemic has allowed, for the first time to our knowledge, to isolate SARS-CoV-2 from an asymptomatic subject and to conduct in vitro experiments to study its replicative features. Experiments were performed on Vero E6 cells since they are fully susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection and provide a valuable substrate to avoid as much as possible constraints to the virus due to the absence of the interferon response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] to which SARS-CoV-2 is highly sensitive [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Surprisingly, the novel SARS-CoV-2 GZ69 isolate did not induce any cytopathic effect on Vero E6 cells despite a high viral load in the culture supernatant. The viral load continued to be sustained, at levels usually reached by cytopathic viruses, even when cells were passaged several times. This finding attests for the unprecedented ability of the novel isolate to manipulate cell machinery to circumvent cell death and demands for further studies to understand the molecular mechanisms underlying its persistent infection. Nidovirales and, among them, coronaviruses are prone to establish persistence both in vivo and in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. It is well admitted that persistence results from adaptations of both the host cell and the virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and that mutations in the viral genome concur to the persistence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. This has been clearly demonstrated also for SARS-CoV, the phylogenetically closest virus to SARS-CoV-2, where a point mutation is stabilized during the establishment of persistence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], suggesting that even a single but crucial amino acid change may be advantageous for virus adaptation. In this paper, we have highlighted that SARS-CoV-2 GZ69 and cytopathic SARS-CoV-2 AP66 display some amino acid differences. These variations allowed us to categorize SARS-CoV-2 GZ69 and SARS-CoV-2 AP66 in different phylogenetic subgroups and suggest that SARS-CoV-2 GZ69 may have evolved, during time, from the B1 genetic group where SARS-CoV-2 AP66 and many other Italian strains are classified.
</p>
