<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">The other differences between SARS-CoV-2 AP66 and SARS-CoV-2 GZ69 reside within the N gene, where 2 consecutive amino acids (203-204) were replaced. These substitutions are located in the N2a linker domain which is uniquely tolerant of mutations, in keeping with its likely structural role as a disordered linker between the RNA-binding N1b domain and the N2b dimerization domain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. In agreement with this, mutations observed in the N gene are not unique of GZ69 viral strain being already detected in other SARS-CoV-2 isolates worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. However, no relationship between the presence of these substitutions and viral pathogenicity has yet been assessed. In this context, it is worth to note that, in SARS-CoV, these residues are part of putative phosphorylation sites and that this epitope is involved in interaction with different cellular enzymes such as cyclin-dependent kinase (CDK) and glycogen synthase kinase-3 (GSK3) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Furthermore, mutational analyses involving residue 204 have provided substantial evidence that the N protein of the SARS-CoV binds and inhibits the activity of the cyclin-CDK complex, resulting in the down-regulation of the S phase gene products and the subsequent inhibition of S phase progression in human cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The mutational events occurred in SARS-CoV-2 GZ69 at 203-204 residues may reduce the anti-proliferative properties of N protein, favouring cell survival and, eventually, viral persistence. The recent availability of an infectious cDNA clone of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] makes possible reverse genetics attempts to determine whether replacement of the above described amino acid residues within a well characterized SARS-CoV-2 molecular clone may drastically alter the viral aggressiveness.
</p>
