<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is a lung disease caused by a novel coronavirus first detected in late 2019, which has a significant impact on the regional environment [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and human health [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Many scholars discussed the clinical manifestations [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] of COVID-19 and the risk factors of death and its detailed clinical course [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], providing an important basis for the rapid and accurate diagnosis of COVID-19 patients. Airborne pollutants with diameters less than or equal to 2.5 microns are known as PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> or fine particles. Due to the characteristics of small diameter, large-area coverage, strong activity, easy bonding with toxic substances, PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> can be suspended in the atmosphere for a long time, severely impacting on the regional environment and Earth’s biological cycle [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-07664" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Furthermore, they are prone to provide carriers for toxic substances, e.g., absorbing harmful gases such as polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) from industrial exhaust gas and polluted microorganisms, which then enter the human body through breathing, causing harm to the immune system, respiratory tract, cardiovascular and cerebrovascular system, and nervous center system of the human body and causing a series of diseases. With the prevalence of the internet of things (IoT), artificial intelligence (AI) and cloud computing, the spatiotemporal big data, e.g., location-based service (LBS) and place of interest (POI) data, that derived from navigation and positioning, location and trajectory, online car-hailing order, social media network, and macro national economic, are increasing rapidly. The rational and effective use of spatiotemporal big data will play a positive role in understanding influence factors of PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> concentration, and quantitatively assessing the population exposure and health risks of PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> during COVID-19.
</p>
