<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">Ambient air pollutant, a mixture of chemicals, including carbon oxides (CO), nitrogen oxides (NO
 <sub>x</sub>), ozone (O
 <sub>3</sub>), sulfur oxides (SO
 <sub>x</sub>), and particular matters (PM), has been proven that can increase the probability of respiratory infections, by prolonging the aerosol transmission of viruses (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2010</xref>), or enhancing the ability of viruses to invade airway epithelial cells (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Cruz-Sanchez et al., 2013</xref>). Exposure to ambient air pollutants may also aggravate respiratory symptoms by inhibiting the expression of key inflammatory mediators (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Popovic et al., 2019</xref>), as observed in previous studies. Several studies have indicated that the diffusion dynamic of COVID-19 supposed be shaped by socioeconomic and health status, such as living conditions, migration scale and occupation (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bao and Zhang, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Kaiser and Stathopoulos, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Khalatbari-Soltani et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Lau et al., 2020</xref>), and air pollution seems to play a role in aerosols transmission of SARS-CoV-2. Van Doremalen et al. has shown that SARS-CoV-2 could remain viable in aerosols for several hours, making airborne transmission plausible (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">van Doremalen et al., 2020</xref>). Fattorini and Regoli examined the association between COVID-19 spread and long-term exposure to air pollution, suggesting that chronic exposure to atmospheric contamination may represent a favorable context for the spread of SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Fattorini and Regoli, 2020</xref>). Zhu et al. have investigated the association between short-term exposure to air pollutants and Covid-19 infection in 120 cities in China, finding that air pollution can be an important factor in COVID-19 infection (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>). Thus, it is reasonable to speculate that ambient air pollutants might affect the transmission of SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
