<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the reporting of early symptomatic cases was urged by the Egyptian Ministry of Health from the very start of the pandemic, unidentified cases—either symptomatic or asymptomatic—contributed substantially to further SARS-CoV-2 spread nationwide and abroad.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
 </sup> At a time of no local testing capacity, COVID-19 cases were imported to Egypt from China through global air travel.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> Eventually the COVID-19 pandemic led to cessation of most international flights between afflicted countries, although it was too late to prevent global viral spread.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup> Egypt, Algeria and South Africa represented the highest importation risk of COVID-19 from China to Africa according to one modelling study of global travel patterns.
 <sup>7</sup> Egypt stopped all flights in late March through 1 July and applied a night-time curfew to limit the spread in social groups. Despite early, aggressive and restrictive control measures, Egypt has experienced a transition from its first few cases to a severe upward spike with cumulative cases of &gt;70 000 (as of July 2020) after mass gatherings for festivals and loosened enforcement of physical distancing.
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> More cases are emerging in Africa and the Middle East and these will burden underresourced hospitals and health systems, representing a special risk for the elderly and persons with pre-existing medical conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
  <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
  <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
  <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 </sup> The global community was not prepared for a pandemic respiratory disease threat on the magnitude of COVID-19, or novel influenza strains, least of all low- and middle-income countries.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
