<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Acute bronchiolitis is the most frequent lower respiratory tract infection in children, especially in preterm infants, and represents the leading cause of hospitalization in infants, accounting for 18% of all pediatric hospital admissions in the United States [
 <xref rid="B7-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Various definitions of bronchiolitis have been proposed [
 <xref rid="B7-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Bronchiolitis is defined by the American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) as a constellation of signs and symptoms, including a viral upper respiratory tract prodrome, followed by increased respiratory effort and wheezing in children under the age of two [
 <xref rid="B9-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].In Europe, by contrast, the term bronchiolitis is generally referred to as a first episode of acute lower airway infection in infants younger than one year [
 <xref rid="B7-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Clinically, it is characterized by few days of rhinorrhea, fever, and cough, which precede the signs of lower respiratory distress associated with wheeze and/or crackles on chest auscultation. Most children with bronchiolitis have an uneventful course. Hospitalization is required in about 3% of cases, and admission to a Pediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU) in approximately 2–6% of the hospitalized cases [
 <xref rid="B11-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. According to the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) guidelines, indicators for hospital admission are respiratory rate over 60 breaths/minute, marked chest wall retractions, apnea, an oxygen saturation (SpO2) lower than 92%, central cyanosis, poor oral fluid intake, inability or indifference to eating due to breathlessness [
 <xref rid="B10-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Even if the diagnosis of bronchiolitis is mainly based on history and clinical findings, and the treatment is primarily supportive, the identification of the causative organism should improve the understanding of the disease and open avenues for precision medicine.
</p>
