<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preventing and decreasing COVID-19-related SSEs necessitates the decryption of the mechanism through which SARS-COV-2 spreads through super spreader individuals, for example within healthcare facilities (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Healthcare facilities are essential for prevention and control of SSEs (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). SSE prevention may enable us to even overcome initial low COVID-19 virus infectiveness. The capability of the virus to produce SSEs troubles the epidemiological attempts to restrict viral spread only by isolating individuals at high risk and performing obsolete isolation at home for the general population as carried out in countries such as Greece (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). During the SARS epidemic in China (Beijing) and Singapore, the vast majority of infected individuals were barely infective and only 6% of the population was highly infectious, in contrast to many published SARS models (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Other ways of potential coronavirus transmission between hosts may provide explanations for enormous outbreaks (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). It should not be disregarded that coronaviruses cause both respiratory and intestinal infections and share common evolutionary roots with hepatitis viruses (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Passing the cross-species barrier and genetic adaptation within hosts may promote virulence of coronaviruses in humans (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). This, prompts to specifically identify potential super spreader groups within populations through targeted diagnosis. Some of these groups are listed in 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. For this purpose, a usual infection must be distinguished from a super spread infection (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). During SARS epidemic, the coronavirus infectiousness mostly occurred in the late stages of infection (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), whereas in COVID-19, viruses are transmitted even in pre-symptomatic stages (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). As with Influenza A virus subtype H1N1 transmission (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), accurate diagnosis of COVID-19 in potentially asymptomatic super spreaders may help contain the magnitude of large outbreaks (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). 
</p>
