<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On the other hand, improper understanding of how COVID-19 spreads resulted in societal imbalance due to arbitrary restriction of social and religious life including Holy Communion Cup. It has been consecutively demonstrated by expert research that the Holy Cup (Chalice) and the Holy Cloth are not sources or pathways, for potential spreading of infectious diseases including Human Immunodeficiency virus (HIV) (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), Hepatitis B virus (HBV) (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>) as well as other communicable pathogens (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Specifically, a review (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>), considered other 129 relative studies. In this review, the possibilities that the shared communion cup can act as a vehicle for indirect transmission of human immunodeficiency virus, since it was detected in the saliva of infected individuals, was investigated. It was emphasized that although for bacterial contamination, the alcoholic content of the wine, the material that the cup is made of, or the practice of partially rotating the cup, cannot stop the occasional transmission of microbes, the microbial transmission was considerably reduced by the intervening use of a cloth to swab the lip of the cup between communicants. Notably, it was emphasized that transmission means not an obligatory inoculation or infection. Furthermore, it was also emphasized that out of the epidemiology of microbes transmitted via saliva, particularly for the transmission of the herpes viruses, the indirect transmission is rare, and indeed transmission is highly possible by other means than by the saliva. It was also emphasized that neither hepatitis B virus nor human immunodeficiency virus infection can be transmitted by saliva, rendering their indirect transmission also less likely by inorganic objects. Finally, the study concluded that no episode of disease transmission has ever been reported as a result of the shared communion cup use, and that there was not any scientific evidence that the communion cup practice should be abandoned due to the possible risk of spreading of any infection (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Likewise, Kingston et al. (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), by considering 44 relative papers, also concluded that there is no evidence that the Holy Communion Cup spreads infections. Moreover, more recent estimations also demonstrated that no infections have ever been observed as a result of religious rituals including Christian Common Communion chalice practice (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>); whereas, data of previous studies implied that saliva could play a role in HBV transmission, are likely to be trivial (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Similarly, recent evidence indicate that, although HBV DNA and HCV RNA can be discovered in the saliva of infected patients, they seem unlikely to transmit infection (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). It should be noted that, as in the case of coronavirus (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>), HBV also exists in many body fluids including saliva, nasopharyngeal fluid or tears by measures of qualitative and PCR methods (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). 
</p>
