<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>Many experimental SARS-CoV-1 vaccines have been formulated from whole inactivated viruses, due to their advantage of large-scale production, multiple epitope presentation and high conformation stability (</bold>
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>
 <bold>). One such vaccine uses viruses from AY71A217 strain of SARS-CoV-1, which are double inactivated using formalin and UV irradiation, the so-called double-inactivated virus (DIV) vaccine (</bold>
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
 <bold>). Although DIV had initially been demonstrated to induce neutralizing antibodies and to protect against SARS-CoV-1 viral replication, both in tissue culture and in young mice, it soon became apparent that older mice suffered from vaccine-induced immune pathologies, including failure to contain viral replication, augmented clinical disease and associated symptoms, and increased inflammatory response and eosinophilic influx (</bold>
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
 <bold>, </bold>
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>
 <bold>). In this respect, there is </bold>
 <bold>an overlap between the immunopathologic responses connected with coronavirus disease and vaccination, and the role of T helper (Th) 17 cells in immune augmentation and eosinophilic lung immunopathology; host Th17 polarized inflammatory reactions portray an important role in the pathophysiology of COVID-19 pneumonia and edema</bold> 
 <bold>(</bold>
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>
 <bold>, </bold>
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
 <bold>).</bold>
 <bold> Eosinophilic pathology, indicating increased pathogenesis and disease severity in the elderly, has been attributed to the nucleocapsid (N) protein, despite the incorporation of multiple SARS-CoV-1 antigens in the DIV (</bold>
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>
 <bold>, </bold>
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
 <bold>). This is on grounds that the N protein is a strong modulator of innate immunity, also acting as an interferon antagonist, and therefore, it has the capability to induce inflammation with subsequent immune pathology in situations of heterologous viral challenge or in immune senescence, where patients fail to mount effective immune responses against the disease (</bold>
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
 <bold>, </bold>
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>
 <bold>). The route of transmission is important to be established for SARS COV-2. As seen with other important infectious diseases of a) air borne transmission such as tuberculosis (</bold>
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>
 <bold>), b) orofecal transmission such as HEV (</bold>
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>
 <bold>) and c) blood transmission such as HBV and hepatitis D virus (</bold>
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>
 <bold>), even if efficient vaccination is established, understanding of SSEs is still important. Recent research data on the immune receptors used by coronaviruses, which reflect their ability to propagate in the human population, imply that complex immune reactions are responsible for a cell to cell transmission. In addition to ACE-II receptor, as is the case with SARS-COV, MERS-COV (</bold>
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>
 <bold>) and possibly for SARS-COV-2 (</bold>
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>
 <bold>, </bold>
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>
 <bold>), viruses use complex receptor recognition systems common to immunopathology damage mechanisms in coronavirus-infected individuals, which clearly define the clinical outcome (</bold>
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>
 <bold>). Therefore, application of vaccines that may interfere with antibody-mediated infection by coronaviruses (</bold>
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>
 <bold>) without true epidemiologic containment of coronaviruses, to restrict genetic adaptation events and inevitably producing an SSE, may be a miscellaneous attempt. However, synergy of SSE prevention measures with proper vaccination can provide a robust attempt for disease containment. </bold>
</p>
