<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The typically recognized 20–80 rule or the so-called “Pareto rule”, states that 20% of efforts lead to 80% of results (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). More specifically, this comprises a principally convenient state when tackling infectious diseases and is applied to investigate infection transmission, and initially among cattle farms. In this regard, Woolhouse et al. (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) reported that targeted actions concerning disease control and prevention in 20% of the farms that mainly supplied the basic reproduction number (R
 <sub>o</sub>) decreased spread by 80% (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Focusing on the COVID-19 virus, R
 <sub>o</sub> is a sign of virus transmissibility, denoting the average figure of novel infections caused by an infectious individual in a totally naïve population. For 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0 </sub>&gt; 1, the number of infected people tends to increase, whereas for 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0 </sub>&lt; 1, transmission is likely to stop; R
 <sub>o</sub> represents a chief model in the epidemics, signifying the risk of an infectious mediator with regard to epidemic spread (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Recent data indicate that the estimated mean R
 <sub>o</sub> for COVID-19 is almost 3.28, with a median of 2.79 and the interquartile range (IQR) of 1.16, which is substantially higher than WHO’s estimation of 1.95. However, due to biased methodology, R
 <sub>o</sub> for COVID-19 is expected to be about 2–3, which is approximately consistent with the WHO estimate (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). SSEs appear to be a main limitation of the R
 <sub>o</sub> concept. R
 <sub>o</sub>, when calculated as a mean or median value, does not include the heterogeneity of transmission between infected individuals (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>); two infective agents with equal R
 <sub>0</sub> estimates might have noticeably diverse patterns of transmission. Moreover, the goal of a Health Care System is to achieve R
 <sub>o</sub> &lt;1, which is probably only phenomenally feasible in certain conditions without scheduled prevention, recognition, and response to SSEs (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Naturally, epidemics follow the aforementioned 20 / 80 rule (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Specifically, in human population, due to heterogeneous exposure to infectious agent, the 20% core population may transmit the disease, widely. For SARS, the rate might have been even lower than 20% (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The increased infectious potential of a small population subgroup seems to be related to immunodeficiency, such as in hemodialysis, cancer, immunosuppressive therapies (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Additionally, facilitation of disease spread and transmission due to vector exposure has been investigated in relation to cockroaches (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Possible mechanical transportation by rats and cat (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) and air transmission (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) in SARS-COV-1 have also been studied. Other animals capable of being SARS-COV-2 carriers (excluding mice and rats), like pigs, ferrets, cats, and non-human primates have recently been introduced (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), and contamination of sewage with SARS-COV-2, has probably preceded COVID-19 outbreak in France (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). All these agents may contribute to a minimum of 80% of the total transmission potential (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), maybe even more (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). 
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> displays possible super spreader groups; thus, indicating screening targets to prevent SSEs. SARS epidemic taught us that control programs were inefficient in controlling the epidemic within a population, and failed to identify and provide a targeted infection diagnosis in groups causing potential SSEs (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). On the other hand, SARS-COV-2 having the ability to cause a pandemic rather than an epidemic, resulted in an increased number of cases and deaths; albeit having a lower mortality rate than SARS coronavirus (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). SSEs during COVID-19 may involve not only one city, but also a whole country or many countries, requiring investigation of their effects on a national or international level (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). 
</p>
