<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The NHP genera and species studied here are distributed along with the Atlantic Forest and Cerrado biomes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], the biomes from which NHP carcasses were sampled. 
 <italic>Alouatta</italic> spp. has been described as extremely sensitive to YFV infection, developing severe and fatal disease [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, specimens of 
 <italic>Alouatta</italic> presenting antibodies against YFV shows that howler monkeys can survive from YF [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Indeed, high rates of howler monkeys presenting protective or neutralizing antibodies against YFV were described in studies conducted in different regions of Panama (50.7% out of 203 individuals) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and Brazil (25.5% out of 192 specimens) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. There is little information regarding the susceptibility of 
 <italic>Callicebus</italic> spp. to YFV infection. However, humoral immunity against YFV was demonstrated in 28.6% of 14 specimens investigated by Kumm and Laemmert (1950) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], in Brazil. In the present study, 
 <italic>Callicebus</italic> and 
 <italic>Alouatta</italic> presented similar proportions of YFV-infected carcasses with similar low median Cqs in RT-qPCR. These results might indicate the high sensitivity to YFV of 
 <italic>Callicebus</italic>, as 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>nigrifrons</italic> and 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>personatus</italic>. The YF surveillance and animal conservation programs should consider this information since some of those species are threatened (
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>nigrifrons</italic>) and vulnerable (
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>personatus</italic>) with decreasing population trends [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Similarly, species within 
 <italic>Sapajus</italic> genus present population decreasing trends with some already considered critically endangered [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Here, only two specimens were sampled, and one carcass was YFV-positive. Although 
 <italic>Sapajus</italic> specimens may develop severe disease, they have been considered less susceptible to YFV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Our results and previous studies [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] showed YF outbreaks causing thousands of deaths of NHP, which lives in one of the most threatened ecosystems of the world, the Atlantic Forest [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
