<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite many marmoset carcasses received (mostly from urban areas), the overall positivity for YFV in 
 <italic>Callithrix</italic> was lower than 
 <italic>Alouatta</italic> and 
 <italic>Callicebus</italic>. Due to their ability to adapt and survive in degraded and secondary habitats [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], free-living marmosets frequently inhabit urban green areas inside Brazilian cities, close to human populations. The proximity of 
 <italic>Callithrix</italic> to the anthropic environment and its wide occurrence in urban areas could increase the chances of dead marmosets to be found in a good preservation status. However, we observed a strong negative correlation for detection of YFV in urban marmosets and higher median Cqs compared to 
 <italic>Callicebus</italic> and 
 <italic>Alouatta</italic>, suggesting lower genomic viral loads in those urban marmosets. Previous studies showed similar data when 
 <italic>Callithrix</italic> presented higher Cqs (lower viral loads) than 
 <italic>Alouatta</italic> during the recent YFV epizootics in Brazil [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. On the other hand, we did not observe a difference among rural NHP (
 <italic>Callithrix</italic>, 
 <italic>Alouatta</italic>, and 
 <italic>Callicebus</italic>), which presented median estimates of genomic viral loads of 10E+6 times higher than 
 <italic>Callithrix</italic> from urban and urban-rural transition areas. When only marmosets were evaluated, we detected a higher positivity in rural areas and a decreasing gradient towards urban areas, consistent with the sylvatic pattern of YF. In that way, the lower overall positivity for YFV could result from the lower exposure to YFV-infected sylvatic vectors in urban areas. 
 <italic>Haemagogus</italic> spp. is highly competent and considered the primary vector of YFV in Brazil [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], including the recent outbreaks in the country [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. These mosquitoes are primatophilic species, being found in the tree canopy [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, some species as 
 <italic>Haemagogus leucocelaenus</italic> and 
 <italic>Haemagogus janthynomis</italic> can disseminate through great distances [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and may adapt to modified environments, as urban-rural interface [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and urban green areas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008658.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
