<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">The 2019 novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic started in December 2019 in the city of Wuhan, Hubei province in China. It is a highly contagious zoonosis (with a reproductive number of 2.8, which means that under preexisting conditions one case generates 2.8 new cases) produced by a beta coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) that spreads from human-to-human, largely by respiratory secretions and occasionally by feces [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The infection spreads predominantly (87%) in people with 30 to 79 years of age [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Usually it remains asymptomatic (81%) or produce only mild symptoms, but 15% cases require hospitalization while some(3 to 4%) require respiratory support in an intensive care unit (ICU) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The death rate has been calculated between 0.39 and 4%, but this depends upon patient’s age and is much higher in above 70 year patient’s [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The first reported physician fatality related to COVID-19 in Wuhan, China was that of an otolaryngology physician on 25 January 2020 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In Wuhan epidemic statistics, 3.8% of the infected cases were health workers, among which 14.8% had severe disease, and the overall mortality rate was of 0.6% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In COVID-19 patients with known respiratory disease, protective measures are usually followed by surgeons. However, a significant number of patients do not have fever or respiratory symptoms (13–30%), so surgeons should apply respiratory protective strategies in all patients. The classical symptoms of the infection are fever, dry cough, and shortness of breath. The symptoms rarely resemble a classical “cold” or with a runny nose that helps distinguish it from the common viral flu. Nonetheless, precautions must be taken for all patients with flu-like symptoms. Recent reports from around the world have shown that anosmia and dysgeusia are significant symptoms associated with the COVID-19 pandemic. Anosmia, in particular, has been seen in patients testing positive for the coronavirus with no other symptoms. For this reason, the American Academy of Otolaryngology (AAO-HNSF) has proposed that these symptoms be added to the list of screening tools for possible COVID-19 infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. All procedures that have the potential to aerosolize aerodigestive secretions, such as nasolaryngoscopy, endotracheal intubation, noninvasive ventilation, endoscopic surgery, and high-speed handpieces or ultrasonic instruments, increase the risk of infection and should be avoided or employed only when mandatory [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. There is no information regarding any potential risk for electrocautery smoke or transoral laser resection generated smoke but it would be reasonable to take appropriate precautions in these settings too. Due to the characteristics of the virus, the standard protective measures of daily workflow do not prevent the infection, and specific masks (N-95 or FFP2 or higher) or powered air-purifying respirator (PAPR), other personal protective equipment (PPE) and dedicated sterilization measures should be implemented to avoid the infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].
</p>
