<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Supposing the role of viral pathogens in asthma development, in 2011, Koponenet al. followed-up a cohort of 205 infants hospitalized for bronchiolitis at &lt;6 months of age. Here, 81% of these patients received a control/telephone interview at 5–6 years of age, focusing on the presence of current asthma during the preceding year [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Current asthma was defined in case of a continuous maintenance medication for asthma, doctor-diagnosed wheezing, or prolonged (at least 4 weeks) cough apart from infection. The viral etiology of bronchiolitis was demonstrated in 97% of cases: RSV 70.5%, RV 12.7%, others 16.9%. At the adjusted multivariate analysis, non-RSV bronchiolitis resulted as an independent risk factor for preschool asthma (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.01). Although this study did not find a direct link between RV and asthma, the strong correlation between previous non-RSV bronchiolitis and the risk to the development of asthma led to focus the attention on RV, the second viral pathogen responsible for bronchiolitis [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In 2014, Midullaet al. published data on a cohort of 313 infants hospitalized for bronchiolitis who underwent yearly follow-up up to three years from the time of discharge. They examined the correlation between viral pathogens (RSV in 73.9% of cases, RV in 14.9% of cases, other viral agents in 21.6% of cases) and the recurrence of wheezing. They observed that RV was the only virus associated with recurrent wheezing (defined as ≥2 episodes in a year for three years) at multivariate analysis (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.03). Moreover, they confirmed the lack of association between RSV bronchiolitis and wheezing [
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. On the contrary, the study of Amat and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] on a cohort of 154 hospitalized infants for bronchiolitis did not find any difference between the kind of respiratory virus (RSV in 76% of cases, RV in 28.6%, other viruses in 70.1% of cases) and the subsequent development of recurrent bronchial obstruction (intended as ≥3 respiratory symptoms documented in ≥2 times). However, the same study demonstrated that RV + RSV co-infected bronchiolitis was associated with the risk of sensitization to aeroallergens at three years at the multivariate analysis (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.02) [
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
