<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Once again, the cohorts enrolled in the context of MARC’s studies have given results also in terms of the correlation between RV bronchiolitis and the development of asthma [
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In 2019, Bergroth and colleagues analyzed the use of asthma control medication four years after hospitalization for bronchiolitis in 349 children. They found that RV infection compared to RSV infection was associated with higher use of asthma control medication in the last year (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Moreover, they genotyped RV, finding RV-A type in 24% of RV cases, RV-B in 3% of cases, and RV-C in 73%. At the multivariable analysis, RV-C was specifically associated with a higher risk for the use of asthma control medication four years after severe bronchiolitis (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), more than RV-A type (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.03). The authors supposed that specific RV-C risk genes, such as cadherin-related family members 3, could predispose to the development of asthma after infection with this RV type [
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In 2020, Mansbach and colleagues analyzed the American MARC’s cohort of 673 hospitalized infants for bronchiolitis, attending two years of follow-up after discharge. Collecting nasopharyngeal aspiration three weeks after the discharge, they focused their attention on the hypothesis that a delayed viral clearance or a sequential infection may be related to the presence of recurrent wheezing by the age of three. Recurrent wheezing was defined as having ≥2 corticosteroid-requiring exacerbations in 6 months or ≥4 wheezing episodes in a year that last ≥1 day and affect sleep. They found that infants with RV bronchiolitis at hospitalization, followed by a new RV infection, had the highest risk of recurrent wheezing (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.01). This result was limited by the small number of considered patients (eight infants); however, the authors suggested that it could indicate a specific role by subsequent several RV genotype infections in the genesis of wheezing [
 <xref rid="B49-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
