<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0049">Early, continuous, and professional psychological interventions can prevent physical and mental harm. Patients endure stress during an epidemic and may experience physical and mental reactions (
 <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Matua and Van der Wal, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Mohammed et al., 2015</xref>). The stressors of the patients noted in this study were the disease itself, the treatment regimens in quarantine, and concerns regarding family health, resulting in changes in mood, diet, sleep, and behavior. The emotional experience of patients during the early stages of the disease included anger, anxiety, and concern. Quarantine also led to loneliness, anxiety, helplessness, and depression, consistent with previous reports of other epidemic diseases (
 <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">James et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mak et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Shultz et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Hossain et al., 2020</xref>). This, therefore, appears to represent a general psychological stress response during epidemic disasters. Mak 
 <italic>et al</italic>. found that 30 months after SARS, the prevalence of psychological and mental illness in survivors was 33.3%, of which 25% of patients had PTSD and 15.6% suffered from depression (
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mak et al., 2009</xref>). In addition, a prolonged 4-year study demonstrated that 44.1% of SARS survivors developed PTSD and retained psychological distress disorders with weakened social function (
 <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Hong et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Bo et al., 2020</xref>). Most clinically stable COVID-19 patients experienced PTSD prior to discharge from hospital (
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Bo et al., 2020</xref>). As such, timely psychological guidance is important (
 <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Yoon et al., 2016</xref>;
 <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Hossain et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Holmes et al., 2020</xref>). Where psychological interventions could not be performed face-to-face due to epidemic prevention and control, online interventions were performed, surveys finding that half of the patients developed a positive attitude towards the online crisis mental health services (
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Bo et al., 2020</xref>). Patients have also expressed concerns regarding recurrence, physical and mental states, and social interactions after discharge. As such, physical and mental rehabilitation, continuous care, and social support after discharge represent key factors (
 <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Nuriddin et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al.,2020b</xref>). Personal psychoneuroimmunology precautions against COVID-19 lead to improvements in environmental health and must be taken seriously by healthcare professionals (
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2020b</xref>).
</p>
