<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0050">Culture can significantly impact psychological adjustments and the social support of patients. Self-adjustment plays a significant self-help role and family and social support are key to the support of patients with infectious diseases (
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang, et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">Schwerdtle et al., 2017</xref>). A large number of patients in this study used Chinese cultural idioms while battling the disease, including “The house of goodness will have more celebration.” and “If you don't die, you will have blessings.” This indicated how traditional cultures can promote psychological adjustments. In addition, the majority of patients believed that the robust social support was related to the Chinese cultural notion of "difficulty in one party, support in all directions" and the emphasis on collective education. The concept of family in Chinese traditional culture attaches additional importance to respect for one's parents, elders, and ancestors (
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Park and Chesla, 2007</xref>). Ensuring patient care is a moral responsibility of family members (
 <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Wong and Pang, 2000</xref>) and promotes the social support of patients. Simultaneously, China's ethics of medical professionals highlights the treatment of each patient as a loved one (
 <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Wong and Pang, 2000</xref>). Medical staff spared no efforts when fighting the pandemic, imparting a strong sense of support and security. In a study of 1,738 respondents from 190 Chinese cities, high confidence in healthcare workers was a protective factor (
 <xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020b</xref>). Conversely, cultural factors may increase the psychological burden. In a survey of 1,210 ordinary individuals from 194 Chinese cities, 75.2% were concerned about family members infected with COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020a</xref>). In Chinese culture, interpersonal harmony is key to the maintenance of patient mental health (
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Hsiao et al., 2006</xref>). The failure to fulfil family responsibilities results in lower levels of self-esteem and increased stigma (
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Hsiao et al., 2006</xref>). As such, the influence of cultural factors on the mental health of patients during an epidemic should not be ignored.
</p>
