<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0051">Active guidance on a patient's psychological growth can improve physical and mental recovery. Patients not only experienced a stressful physical and mental response, they gradually obtained positive elements brought about by the pandemic, which may be related to psychological resilience (
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">Schwerdtle et al., 2017</xref>). Disasters cause psychological stress to individuals which can affect their health. Recognizing protective factors during a disaster can improve the quality of life of the victims (
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Cherry et al., 2018</xref>). In the present study, patients displayed gradual positive emotions, including ease and calmness following acceptance of the disease, and happiness and excitement prior to discharge, rarely mentioned in other studies. This may be related to the interview style and conductance of interviews across various disease stages that permitted the collection of dynamic datasets. Active situation-based responses are an important determinant of resilience after a disaster (
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Cherry et al., 2018</xref>). The patients assessed in the present study expressed gratitude for their support, and in some cases were grateful for the disease itself. The patients cherished life and recognized their positive qualities, including courage and tenacity. Gratitude and social support can reduce PTSD and increase post-traumatic growth (PTG) (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>). Gratitude may also affect PTG through conscious reflection (
 <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Wu, 2015</xref>). The type and level of rumination and meditation also directly affects the psychological adjustments of individuals following trauma. Patients displayed rumination behavior, accompanied by fear and guilt. Studies have shown that invasive rumination mediates the effects of fear and guilt during PTSD and PTG, with active ruminant guilt influencing PTG, mediating the influence of invasive ruminants on PTG (
 <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020c</xref>). Reducing intrusive rumination through psychological interventions and promoting deliberate rumination are significant for psychological adjustment (
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">García, et al., 2016</xref>). Ultimately, psychological techniques can guide the self-awareness and internal growth of patients, which should be recognized and promoted in the clinic to enhance physical and mental recovery.
</p>
