<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0052">Previous studies have shown that the highest risk of COVID-19 disease occurs in those aged over 50 years with a history of chronic diseases such as hypertension, heart disease, and diabetes (
 <xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>). In the present study, 62.50% of the subjects were young and middle-aged (10\16), whilst 37.50% were old and middle-aged (6\16). Critically ill patients accounted for 12.50% (2\16). Those with a confirmed history of chronic disease accounted for 37.50% (6\16). COVID-19 related complications accounted for 25.00% (4\16) of all cases.. Following analysis of the interviews, young patients demonstrated a more positive attitude towards the disease which may be related to their absence of underlying disease and ease of access to up-to-date and accurate information (
 <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al., 2020</xref>). In contrast, older, critically ill patients and those with comorbid diseases showed greater mood fluctuations, were more pessimistic about the disease during the early and middle stages, and showed higher levels of anxiety regarding recovery in the later stages, consistent with previous studies (
 <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al., 2020</xref>). In this study, 56.25% of the patients were males and 43.75% were females. All close contacts of the patients were quarantined for medical observation, and 56.25% of the contacts were confirmed to have COVID-19 (9\16). Gender, physical symptoms, poor self-assessed health status and confirmed COVID-19 cases amongst relatives lead to high levels of stress, anxiety, and depression (
 <xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Vindegaard and Benros, 2020</xref>). In the present study, female patients were more likely to express emotions and anxiety. In comparison, men repressed their emotions, anger being the most prevalent response. Some male patients refused diagnosis and treatment which was accompanied by aggressive language. All patients expressed guilt and concern for their relatives, particularly those with COVID-19. As such, the personalized psychological experience of each patient with their different characteristics should be monitored during the process of clinical diagnosis and treatment.
</p>
