<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Table 7</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Knowns, uncertainties and unknowns about COVID-19, as of May 2020</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor</td>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Available information</td>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease spectrum</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Many different estimates:</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Initially, it was estimated that among infected, 30% remained asymptomatic, 55%–80% had mild/moderate disease, 10%–14% had severe disease, and 5%–6% became critically ill.
        <xref rid="R73" ref-type="bibr">73 90–92</xref>
       </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Very variable estimates for remaining totally asymptomatic (estimated 5%–80%
        <xref rid="R93" ref-type="bibr">93–96</xref>).
       </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>What determines that an infection remains asymptomatic?</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Quasi-absence of disease in children: why?</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case fatality rate (CFR)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Initial estimates CFR: 2%–3%; comparisons: influenza 0.1%; common cold: 0%; SARS: 9%–10%; MERS: 30%.
        <xref rid="R97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>
       </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Calculated infection fatality rates (cIFR) and calculated CFR (cCFR) on the Princess Diamond were 1.3% and 2.6%, respectively (for all ages combined), and projected cIFR and cCFR for China were between 0.6%–0.66% and 1.2%–1.38%, respectively.
        <xref rid="R90" ref-type="bibr">90 98</xref> In Gangelt, Germany: cCFR of 0.37%.
        <xref rid="R99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>
       </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>CFR is influenced significantly by age; male sex; comorbidities; body mass index and/or fitness; and adequacy of supportive treatment, mainly oxygen therapy.
        <xref rid="R100" ref-type="bibr">100 101</xref> Also, as in certain other viral diseases such as measles, possibly influenced by the dose of virus in initial infectious inoculum (see 
        <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="B3">Box 3</xref>).
       </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>CFR and IFR vary depending on population distribution. March 2020, estimated IFR UK: 0.9%, Italy: 1.14%–6.22% initial estimate which increased to 9.26%, Spain: 6.16%, France: 4.21%.
        <xref rid="R102" ref-type="bibr">102 103</xref>
       </p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication/treatment options</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Treatments being used: hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine, remdesivir, azithromycin, convalescent plasma and other antivirals.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>At the time of writing (May 2020), no proven effective treatment. Many clinical trials ongoing.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Oxygen therapy most essential component of case management. Low oxygen saturation a dominant feature of COVID-19, curiously dissociated from dyspnoea. In most cases, oxygen can be administered through a facial mask. In very advanced disease, oxygen administered through artificial ventilation, requiring sophisticated equipment and highly skilled personnel.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
