<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The local outbreak from exposure to the above wholesale food market marks the first phase. From the first case in December 2019 the epidemiological analysis showed that already at this early stage, the person-to-person transmission had taken place through close contact. The second phase began on 13 January, characterized by the rapid expansion and spread of the virus within hospitals (nosocomial infection) and by family transmission (transmission by close contact). As of January 23, 29 provinces of China, plus six foreign countries, had reported a total of 846 confirmed cases, an increase of about 20 times since the first phase. The third phase started on January 26, which is characterized by the rapid increase in cases of conglomerates.[
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Li and his colleagues described the first 425 cases found in Wuhan, which was the epicenter of this outbreak and defined the earliest known detailed clinical and epidemiological description about the spread of COVID-19. In this study, it was found that the elderly population who are above 60 years of age and had other comorbid conditions were more seriously affected than the younger and healthier population with severe breathlessness being most common. Surprisingly children who were less than 14 years of age were less affected with only mild symptoms which would, later on, affect the balance ratio of population between young and old people in a community.[
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Italy suffered from significant mortality with a rate of not less than 8–9% due to this disease, and another reason is that it has the second largest population of older people, who generally have weaker immunity and others associated pathological conditions, such as heart disease, hypertension, diabetes, cerebrovascular disease, etc., While in comparison, China, where the disease actually started, suffered only 2–3% of mortality. Most countries suffer from the shortage of medical staff, ventilators, and personal protective equipment, which also contributes to the increased mortality and morbidity of this viral disease. The countries affected by it suffer a total block; therefore stage III (person-to-person contact) is controlled to interrupt the viral load chain in their population.
</p>
