<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">Coronaviruses as a cause of seasonal respiratory tract diseases are largely restricted to the 4 endemic human coronaviruses. To date, 3 epidemics have been caused by 3 novel highly pathogenic coronaviruses. The approaches for the initial characterization of these viruses varied. SARS-CoV was first identified by growing the virus in cell culture and using a random amplification polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay to amplify a 300-nucleotide region. A diagnostic RT-PCR assay was developed based on the obtained sequence.
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> A full genome was available shortly thereafter
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> and multiple specific nucleic acid amplification diagnostic assays were developed.
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> Conventional and molecular approaches were used for the classification of SARS-CoV as a member of 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> about 6 weeks after the Hong Kong outbreak in mid-February 2003.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> In 2012, the identification of MERS-CoV, which caused severe pneumonia and death of a 60-year-old man, was performed by a pan-CoV PCR assay after cell culture followed by amplicon sequencing.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> An assay panel was developed for the detection of the N nucleocapsid and the upstream sequence (up) to the E envelope (
 <italic>upE</italic>) genes, which has become the recommended test for the diagnosis of MERS-CoV by WHO.
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref> Eighteen years after the SARS-CoV outbreak, a novel coronavirus was recognized as a cause of another epidemic of severe respiratory infection that started in Wuhan, China. Shortly after the outbreak, clinical specimens were tested both by a pan-CoV PCR assay and NGS. Subsequently, a specific RT-PCR was developed. The SARS-CoV-2 whole genome was available on January 10, almost 1 month after the first report of pneumonia of unknown origin. This process was accelerated compared with SARS-CoV, of which a complete sequence was available in April 2003, a few months after the outbreak started late in 2002. The history of identifying novel epidemic coronaviruses highlights the great impact of using advanced metagenomic NGS (mNGS; discussed later) not only for rapid identification but also for the epidemiologic tracing of the viral reservoir and for elucidating the transmission dynamics.
</p>
