<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An epidemic of HEV was reported in 1955 in Delhi, India, with about 29,000 cases of icteric hepatitis [
 <xref rid="B21-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. After this epidemic, several waterborne outbreaks were reported throughout India, and most of these cases were non-A and non-B, leading the disease to be described as enteric non-A non-B hepatitis (ENANBH) [
 <xref rid="B21-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In addition, a major water-related epidemic outbreak in the Kashmir Valley was reported at the end of 1978, with 52,000 cases and 1700 deaths [
 <xref rid="B22-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The symptoms of these cases were similar to hepatitis A but were negative for both hepatitis A and hepatitis B and were therefore confirmed as ENANBH [
 <xref rid="B22-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In 1981, hepatitis occurred in a Soviet military camp in Afghanistan. To investigate this situation, a doctor in the Russian army, Mikhail Balayan, voluntarily ingested a pooled filtrate of stool samples from the infected soldiers, and he subsequently developed acute hepatitis [
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The serum of Dr. Balayan was negative for hepatitis A virus (HAV) and hepatitis B virus (HBV), suggesting that a new pathogen was responsible for this infection. Immunoelectron microscopy identified 20–30 nm non-enveloped virus-like particles in stool, confirming a novel ENANBH virus [
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In 1990, this novel ENANBH was partially cloned and sequenced and was henceforth called the hepatitis E virus (HEV) [
 <xref rid="B25-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. It was initially indicated that hepatitis E infection spreads via contaminated water and is limited to resource poor countries. Later, however, increasing reports of sporadic cases emerged in non-endemic industrialized countries with high seroprevalence in a few areas of the United States [
 <xref rid="B27-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The reason for this high prevalence was not understood, and it was speculated that undetected non-pathogenic or less pathogenic HEV strains were circulating. In 1998, genome sequences confirmed that human HEV were similar to that of HEV in pigs, suggesting zoonotic transmission pathways [
 <xref rid="B28-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Overall, these studies led to the identification of a broad spectrum of HEV strains that are either restricted to humans, animals, or infect both.
</p>
