<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Female sex workers (FSWs) are a key population in the sub-Saharan African HIV epidemic as they have a high prevalence of HIV, engage in unprotected sex and have multiple partners. While there is some regional variation, the estimated HIV prevalence in the FSW population is 10-fold to 20-fold higher than in the general population.
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> In Rwanda, the HIV prevalence among FSWs is estimated to be approximately 50%.
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> In response, in the last two decades, Rwanda has developed a strong national response to control its HIV epidemic, including the FSW population.
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> It has made impressive achievements in HIV care through progressive treatment guidelines and reduced the number of new HIV infections by 50% and the overall number of AIDS-related deaths by 78% from 2004 to 2014.
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> In Rwanda, the estimated number of new HIV infections in 2019 is 4409 (1846 male and 2563 female), and the estimated number of AIDS-related death in the same year is 2939 (1399 male and 1539 female).
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The national prevalence of HIV has been stable at 3% as of 2013.
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> However, the country still faces challenges with high concentrations of HIV in the FSW population. Forty-six per cent of these women are estimated to be HIV positive
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>; HIV incidence among this population is 3.5 per 100 person-years (95% CI 1.6 to 5.4), compared with the general population incidence rate (0.27 per 100 person-years, 95% CI 0.18 to 0.35).
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 8</xref> In Rwanda, it has been reported that only 25.0% (95% CI 16.4% to 28.3%) of FSWs have used condoms consistently in the last 30 days.
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Given that FSWs are more likely to have multiple sex clients too, interventions targeted for this high-risk group may yield important public health benefits.
</p>
