<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pathological changes form the basis of imaging in diagnosis. Biopsy samples taken from the lungs of patients with COVID-19 infection show diffuse pulmonary alveolar damage. The inflammatory lesions revealed alveolar edema and hyaline membrane formation, which are associated with acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) [
 <xref rid="b13-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The pathological findings of COVID-19 are similar to those previously reported in severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and Middle Eastern respiratory syndrome (MERS) coronavirus infections [
 <xref rid="b14-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="b15-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, gross anatomical observations showed that pulmonary fibrosis and consolidation in COVID-19 patients were not as severe as those reported in SARS patients, but the exudation response in COVID-19 is more obvious [
 <xref rid="b16-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The pathological findings are consistent with the image changes. At the early stage of COVID-19 infection, a wide range of pulmonary interstitial inflammation with numerous infiltrating plasma cells and macrophages may be the pathological basis for ground-glass opacities (GGOs) [
 <xref rid="b17-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. With the progression of the lesions, a large amount of inflammatory exudate accumulates in the alveolar cavity, which increases the alveoli and interstitial edema. Cellulose-like exudate connects the alveolar and form consolidation. Type II pneumocyte hyperplasia and inflammatory cell infiltration of the alveolar wall lead to reticular interlobular septal thickening in CT examination [
 <xref rid="b18-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Pathological findings provide new insights into the pathogenesis of COVID-19 infection, which can be useful in developing novel therapeutic strategies aimed at reducing the mortality rate.
</p>
