<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several laboratory parameters, including low hemoglobin, low platelets, high white cell counts, and high HIV-1 viral loads, were also significantly associated with mortality. Anemia is a risk factor for HIV infection, and has previously been associated with shorter survival in HIV-infected patients.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]
 </sup> The severe anemia in the individuals who died may be a result of the more advanced HIV disease and advanced KS. Thrombocytopenia has previously been reported in KS patients and supposedly results from platelet sequestration in the abnormal KS tumor vessels.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]
 </sup> Therefore, advanced disease with numerous KS lesions possibly explains why individuals who died had lower platelet counts. At the time of admission, patients who eventually died also had higher white cell counts above the upper limit of normal. Our findings are consistent with previous studies that have reported high white cell and neutrophil counts to be associated with a poor prognosis in the form of death or KS disease progression.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
  <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]
 </sup> Higher white cell counts may reflect a higher degree of chronic inflammation or may be a sign of sepsis in individuals who died. HIV viral load was 500-fold higher at baseline in individuals who eventually died than individuals who were discharged. HIV viral load is a marker of HIV disease control.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]
 </sup> In addition, poor control of HIV infection predisposes to KS development and progression.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]
 </sup> In our study cohort, individuals who died had a history of poor compliance to ART compared to those who were discharged from hospital. This may have contributed to the advanced disease presentation, high HIV viral load, and poor outcome. However, CD4 counts were not predictive of mortality.
</p>
