<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Putting this all together, our model is a useful mathematical tool to study different epidemic scenarios and shifts in epidemic suitability for other regions on the island, other than the south coast region, where Funchal is located. The model temperature seasonality was parameterized using the observed temperature of Funchal; however, the results can be extrapolated to other regions on the island. The near term projection (i.e. for 2016–2035) for seasonal temperature variation for the region of Madeira island (i.e. the North Atlantic, Europe, and Mediterranean region), predicts a warming of ~2°C in annual mean temperature, with summer months of June, July and August (JJA) temperatures warming up to ~2.9°C [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008679.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008679.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Given our results, we can speculate that the north coast and inland regions of the island, where current annual mean temperatures suggests limited or no epidemic suitability (e.g. Santana, a municipality in the north region with annual temperatures of 16.7°C) could have an increased potential to support transmission in the near future. The south coast region would continue to support transmission, with possible higher epidemic suitability. To reiterate, most of the simulated temperatures are very unlikely to occur on the island, except for sporadic extreme summer temperatures and heatwaves. Such sporadic extreme events have been documented, with recent abrupt changes in temperatures on the island [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008679.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008679.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Hence our simulations provide an estimate of epidemic suitability in the likelihood of these extreme temperature conditions. Also, our results can be applicable to other islands, within the Macaronesia ecoregion with similar climatic conditions as Madeira. For example, the island of Santiago, located in the archipelago of Cape Verde, with similar 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> populations. Our results can provide insights into epidemic suitability shifts and a potential outbreak of dengue on this island. It is important to note that in real life, these projected shifts in epidemic suitability will also be influenced by other factors like rainfall, humidity, and anthropogenic activities. Thus, seasonal temperature variation must be considered jointly with these factors.
</p>
