<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">Although 2019-nCoV is a new, rare, and highly contagious virus, it does not necessarily indicate that healthcare professionals could not draw experience and references from earlier times of crises. For example, SARS, SARS-CoV, a highly contagious coronavirus that inflicted great harm on humanity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. MERS, first reported in Saudi Arabia in 2012, was also caused by a novel coronavirus at the time, MERS-CoV.[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Ebola is an acute viral hemorrhagic disease endemic to West Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. These aforementioned viruses were new viruses completely novel to humanity when they were first discovered. However, through infection prevention and control (IPC), a scientific approach and practical solution were designed to prevent harm caused by infection to patients and health workers, the harm caused by SARS, Middle East Respiratory Syndrome, and Ebola virus to humans has been greatly reduced [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Such strategies, which have been tested several times based on infectious diseases, demonstrated the key role of IPC. Blocking the chain of infection, an important part of IPC, is constituted of Disease Microorganisms (Agent), Reservoir, Mode of Escape, Mode of Transmission, Mode of Entry, and Susceptible Host. It will stop the transmission of the infectious agent by breaking a link anywhere along the chain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. As the emergency department of a large comprehensive hospital, the ED team can choose to block the chain of infection on three aspects: source of infection, transmission routes, and susceptible populations. Our study also proved that for the emergency department, the strategy of blocking the chain of infection (including controlling the source of infection, cutting off the transmission route, and protecting susceptible populations) could effectively prevent and control COVID-19, and maintain normal operation of the emergency department as well as the safety of patients and medical staff during the epidemic to a maximum extent.
</p>
