<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0010">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) is threatening billions of people. We described the clinical characteristics and explore virological and immunological factors associated with clinical outcomes.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>297 COVID-19 patients hospitalized in Guangzhou Eighth People's Hospital between January 20 and February 20, 2020 were included. Epidemiological, clinical and laboratory data were collected and analyzed. Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) RNA in respiratory tract, blood samples and digestive tract was detected and lymphocyte subsets were tested periodically.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Result</title>
  <p>Among the 297 patients (median age of 48 years), 154 (51.9 %) were female, 245 (82.5 %) mild/moderate cases, and 52 (17.5 %) severe/critical cases. 270 patients were detected for SARS-CoV-2 RNA in anal swabs and/or blood samples, and the overall positive rate was 23.0 % (62/270), higher in severe/critical cases than in mild/moderate cases (52.0 % vs. 16.4 %, P &lt; 0.001). The CD4/CD8 ratio on admission was significantly higher in severe/critical cases than in mild/moderate cases (1.84 vs. 1.50, P = 0.022). During a median follow-up period of 17 days, 36 (12.1 %) patients were admitted to intensive care unit (ICU), 16 (5.4 %) patients developed respiratory failure and underwent mechanical ventilation, four (1.3 %) patients needed extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO), only one (0.34 %) patients died of multiple organ failure. Detectable SARS-CoV-2 RNA in anal swabs and/or blood samples, as well as higher CD4/CD8 ratio were independent risk factors of respiratory failure and ICU admission.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Most of COVID-19 patients in Guangzhou are mild/moderate, and presence of extrapulmonary virus and higher CD4/CD8 ratio are associated with higher risk of worse outcomes.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
