<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Before the COVID-19 outbreak, in 2014, Drexler 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] presented a general view of the obtainable studies on bat CoVs, then conducted a comprehensive phylogenetic analysis of the genera AlphaCov and BetaCov and compared the available data on CoV pathogenesis in bats including SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV and HCoV-229E. In 2015, Lu 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] summarized the advance which has taken place in the past decade in understanding the cross-species transition of SARS- CoV and MERS-CoV by centering on the features of the surface-located spike (S) protein, its receptor obligated characteristics and the cleavage process involved in priming. In 2015, Lee 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] discussed some issues which raised the possibility that inhibitor recognition specificity of MERS-CoV papain-like protease (PLpro) may differ from that of SARS-CoV PLpro. In 2017, Yuan 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] presented high-resolution structures of the trimeric envelope spike (S) proteins of MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV in its pre-fusion conformation by single-particle cryo-electron microscopy.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>After the COVID-19 outbreak, in 2020, Ashor 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] discussed the structure, genome organization and entry of CoVs into target cells and provide insights into SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV and COVID-19 outbreaks. Cai 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] compared the clinical and pathological features between COVID-19 and SARS patients. Al-Tawfiq 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] discussed the asymptomatic coronavirus infection through a comparison between MERS-CoV and COVID-19. Gorbalenya 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] explained the classifying and naming of the novel COVID-19 epidemic among other coronaviruses. Liu 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] provided a brief introduction to the pathology and pathogenesis of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV and extrapolate this knowledge to the newly identified COVID-19. Ou 
   <italic>et al.</italic> [
   <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] studied the spike glycoprotein (S) characteristics of virus entry and its immune cross-reactivity in the case of SARS-CoV and COVID-19.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
