<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0050">In this large study, two elements are particularly noteworthy. First, in our geographical area the temporal distributions of infections by all coronaviruses are comparable. Thus, all five viruses exhibit a bell-shaped incidence curve, and their circulation stopped in the spring, suggesting that this is the natural SARS-CoV-2 epidemic pattern. Hence, we can speculate for temperate countries, including Europe, that SARS-CoV-2 could reappear seasonally during winter and circulate epidemically until spring. Alternatively, SARS-CoV-2 might disappear in the absence of an asymptomatic human chronic carriage, like SARS-CoV-1 (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Raoult et al., 2020</xref>). Second, the age distribution of SARS-CoV-2 cases largely spares children, which is radically different from other coronavirus and respiratory virus infections. Thus, SARS-CoV-2 is the only one we analyzed that does not significantly affect children. Therefore, its epidemiology cannot be predicted based on previous knowledge of viral respiratory diseases. The simplest explanation for this difference is that a substantial proportion of children, particularly those under five years of age, may have acquired immunity to endemic coronaviruses that infect young children with high frequencies (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Raoult et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2013</xref>). Indeed, there is evidence that part of the population exhibited immune responses against SARS-CoV-2 before the epidemic, supporting the hypothesis of cross-immunity between endemic coronaviruses and the new coronavirus. Thus, in the US, circulating SARS-CoV-2-specific CD4+ and CD8+ T cells were detected in ≈20−60% of unexposed individuals sampled in 2015–2018 (
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Grifoni et al., 2020</xref>). In the UK, IgG to SARS-CoV-2 were detected in 15% of SARS-CoV-2-uninfected patients with recent HCoV infection and in 10% of SARS-CoV-2-uninfected pregnant women (
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Ng et al., 2020</xref>). Also, we detected IgM to SARS-CoV-2 at titers ≥1:100 in 9/50 patients with endemic coronaviruses (
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Edouard et al., 2020</xref>). It is also worth noting that the coinfection rate observed here with SARS-CoV-2 and another coronavirus was very low (0.1%) and that SARS-CoV-2-positivity was significantly lower among patients positive than negative for an endemic coronavirus, which supports the hypothesis of a protective cross-immunity.
</p>
