<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0070">“
 <bold>Great Depression</bold>.” Stories about the Great Depression since the 1930s shot up to the highest level ever since the Great Depression itself. The peak percent of articles with “Great Depression” in them may seem small, only 0.35%, or about one article in three hundred, but one must reflect on the huge number of articles or news clips people are exposed to, and actually remember. These depression narratives were often stories about the hardships people faced then, along with comparisons that suggest it may be happening again now. People have never forgotten the legend of the Great Depression, and that it led to immense social antagonisms that led to World War II. Note by comparison that there was no unusual activity in the Great Depression narrative during the second-longest economic expansion 1991–2001, or in the contraction 2001–2003. The perennial Great Depression narrative mutated when there was a run on the Northern Rock Bank in the U.K. in 2007 and in the U.S. on Washington Mutual (WAMU) in 2008, when the narrative took on a superficial resemblance to current events. During the 2008–2009 financial crisis politicians around the world warned of the risk of an imminent depression in a bid to win acceptance of aggressive stimulus policies, which also generated higher contagion of the Great Depression narrative. The fears engendered by this new Great Depression narrative epidemic were precisely the kind of fear that Franklin Delano Roosevelt referred to in his 1933 statement “the only thing we have to fear is fear itself.” This latest episode of intense attention to the Great Depression follows a nice hump-shaped epidemic curve, as for example in the Kermack McKendrick SIR model with a high contagion parameter at first and low recovery (forgetting) parameter. The slow-at-first upward path of consumption expenditures corresponds roughly to the downward path in the narrative as people gradually forget it.
</p>
