<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">NNRTIs are not considered preferred first-line therapies, but are still included in at least some regimens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. In the current study, K103N/S, which confers high-level or intermediate cross-resistance to the NNRTIs efavirenz, nevirapine and delavirdine, was the most prominent NNRTI TDRM (4.2%) and more prevalent in HIV-1 subtype B carriers, as previously reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. As current guidelines permit the use of efavirenz among women of childbearing potential, this rather frequent TDRM should not be disregarded. The polymorphic E138 was the most frequently mutated NNRTI site. This naturally occurring polymorphism that blocks the NNRTI-binding pocket, is known to affect rilpivirine binding and may cause lower susceptibility to this drug [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. A systematic review that assessed the prevalence of rilpivirine-related TDRMs in 65 countries, already reported an association between E138 mutations and HIV-1 subtypes C (6.1%), and A (3.3%) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In the current study, it was identified in 5.6% of all women, irrespective of the viral subtype. As rilpivirine-based dual therapy is still considered a legitimate treatment option, resistance testing in all patients prior to rilpivirine therapy should be performed. The most prominent NRTI accessory non-polymorphic mutated site was A62V (5.6% prevalence), which influences replication fidelity and viral fitness in the context of multi-drug resistance mutations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. A62V, which was reported to be widespread in subtype A viruses in the FSU [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], was also significantly more prominent in HIV-1 subtype A in the present analysis. However, according to current guidelines, A62V does not interfere with therapy.
</p>
