<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">This study has some limitations that need to be considered. Firstly, samples from 2016–2018 were collected in two reference hospitals in Kinshasa, which cannot be fully representative of the situation in a city and even more at a country-wide level
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup>. However, the inclusion of all 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences from LANL collected in the country over more than 4 decades, from the general population and risk groups, provides a good overview of the huge diversity of the country. A second limitation is the length of recovered 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences, which differed across samples, complicating bioinformatic analysis. A third limitation is that some reports in the DRC did not submit sequences to databases, and they were not available in LANL (Sup. Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). These reported HIV-1 variants could therefore not be reevaluated by new PhyML analysis to be included in the temporal tend analysis of HIV-1 variants. Thus, we encourage the necessity of sequence submission in all HIV epidemiology studies worldwide before publication, and the inclusion of the sampling year in all submitted sequences, absent in 214 (8%) of 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences downloaded from LANL in that country. The lack of routine resistance testing during clinical follow-up of HIV-infected subjects in the DRC limits the 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences availability in the DRC. Furthermore, the lack of complete epidemiological information from subjects involved in transmission or recombination clusters limits full understanding of a cluster´s origin. Finally, 51.5% of DBS did not yield any viral sequences, possibly due to the low viral load (40–1000 HIV-1 RNA copies/dot) in more than half of specimens and to the low plasma volume in the 2 dots used for HIV-1 RNA extraction, limiting the ability to get positive PCR amplifications of HIV in these samples.
</p>
