<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p8500">The COVID-19 pandemic has now engulfed almost all parts of the globe inhabited by human beings. Confirmed cases are approaching 9 million and confirmed global deaths as June 22 are 468,589. We have updated our analysis here as the pandemic further unfolded. These analyses are now in several papers which have been published (or under-submission) since this paper was drafted. The most important developments are covered in the new citations in the reference list (and below), particularly our discussion on the progress of the major explosive outbreaks following the original epidemic in Wuhan through December-January 2020. Initially, in February, this appeared to go from China across the Pacific to the US West Coast (
 <xref rid="bb9625" ref-type="bibr">Wickramasinghe et al., 2020b</xref>), but it then became apparent the putative viral-laden meteorite dust clouds moved along the north 40° latitude band heading in a westerly direction from China towards Europe (
 <xref rid="bb9630" ref-type="bibr">Wickramasinghe et al., 2020c</xref>). We speculate this transportation took place mainly in the Stratosphere and upper Troposphere, and this helps explain in part the major explosive outbreaks of COVID-19 in the temporal order, Tehran/Qom, Italy/Lombardy, Spain then New York City all on the north 40° latitude band. The genetic sequence of the virus has been analyzed where available in each of the major explosive locations, particularly Wuhan and New York City (Steele &amp; Lindley, 2020). Contrary to a widely held perception that the COVID-19 is a hypermutating contagious virus it is still the case, at the time of writing, that the most vulnerable at risk of death through respiratory complications are the co-morbid elderly. Further, the virus does not hypermutate, it appears to a use a riboswitch-mediated haplotype variation strategy which could be associated with the ethnic-genetic background of the subjects infected. Thus the genetic sequence of the virus in Wuhan/China, West Coast USA (February, 2020), Spain and New York City is essentially ≥99.98% identical apart from a small set of key variant putative riboswitch sites (ranging from 2 to 5 on average across the length of the 29,903 nt RNA genome) which define a given haplotype. Thus, there is much haplotype homogeneity in China, but considerable haplotype diversity in New York City. The virus appears to adapt to new host genetic backgrounds by switching putative haplotype presumably allowing superior RNA replication in that cellular environment. The only factor we cannot explain then is why the super explosions of the viral epidemics in certain locations and not others. One likely factor would be the infective dose of the virus which we predict was far greater at these epicentre locations because it came in as a high dose in-fall in meteorite dust from the upper atmosphere.
</p>
