<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0200">At the time of writing, the case incidence of this newly discovered Coronavirus is passing through 60,000 and &gt; 99.99% of all cases, almost exclusively, are Chinese. From reports of cases that exited Wuhan by aircraft in late January to other countries, say to Australia, the disease does not spread in a sustained way easily person-to-person. But there are clearly apparent cases of person-to-person spread elsewhere (say in United Kingdom and Europe, 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref> ). But there is no doubt this disease is centred on China. The Johns Hopkins University COVID-19 case density maps are extremely informative. These are in 
 <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> .
 <boxed-text id="b0010">
  <label>Box 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Summary of United Kingdom cases (N.C. Wickramasinghe email report to Edward J. Steele).</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="p0010">
   <list list-type="simple" id="l0010">
    <list-item id="u0010">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0015">January 21, 2020</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="p0020">CDC confirms 1 case of transmission between person who returned from Wuhan, and a person who shared accommodation in the United States.</p>
  <p id="p0025">Via a ski resort in the French Alpine town of Les Contamines-Montjoie, near Switzerland, late last month,
   <list list-type="simple" id="l0015">
    <list-item id="u0015">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0030">January 28, 2020</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="p0035">
   <italic>A cluster linked to an Alpine chalet</italic>
  </p>
  <p id="p0040">A British man (Mr. Walsh) from Brighton, was found to have the virus when he returned to the UK (London Gatwick Airport) from Geneva on January 28 on an EasyJet flight. A total of six people in Britain, including Mr. Walsh, and Britons in France who have the virus have been staying in two apartments in a ski chalet in the Alpine resort area near Mont Blanc when they were visited by Mr. Walsh on January 24 
   <italic>who had attended a</italic> business 
   <italic>conference at the Grand Hyatt Hotel Singapore, where he Is believed to have contracted the virus.</italic>
  </p>
  <p id="p0045">Mr. Walsh is 
   <italic>thought</italic> to have passed the virus onto eleven confirmed cases while he was at the Ski resort. But he is thought to have come into contact with scores of people after leaving Singapore and no others have yet succumbed.
  </p>
  <p id="p0050">All the supposed transmissions of the virus from Mr. Walsh to the others were while they occupied the Chalets in France.</p>
  <p id="p0055">Four are from Brighton and Hove. They are Dr. Greenwood and three men, one of whom is a healthcare worker. He also passed it to one other person in the United Kingdom, one person who is now in Mallorca and five United Kingdom nationals in France—one of which is Dr. Greenwood's husband Bob Saynor and another their 9-year-old son. None are said to be in a serious condition.</p>
  <p id="p0060">So far, the places in Brighton and Hove being quarantined are:
   <list list-type="simple" id="l0020">
    <list-item id="u0020">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0065">County Oak Medical Centre, where Dr. Catriona Greenwood worked one admin day last week, and its branch surgery at Deneway.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0025">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0070">Grenadier Pub in Hangleton, which was visited by Steve Walsh on February 1.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0030">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0075">Cornerstone Community Centre, where a yoga teacher came into contact with Steve Walsh on February 3. No other people have been advised to self-isolate.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0035">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0080">Easyjet flight EZS8481 to Gatwick from Geneva on January 28, which is believed to be the flight Mr. Walsh took back to the United Kingdom.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0040">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0085">Bevendean Primary School, where a staff member has been in close contact with someone who has been advised to self-isolate (but is not themselves diagnosed).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0045">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0090">Portslade Academy, which told parents on Friday one of its pupils has been advised to self-isolate for a fortnight after coming into contact with the Hove father. It's believed pupils at other schools have been given the same advice.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0050">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0095">Patcham Nursing Home, which has closed its doors to all visitors after being visited by one of the medics now confirmed as having the virus.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="p0100">The cluster associated with Mr. Walsh could have been coinfected from a common source, with Mr. Walsh showing symptoms first.</p>
  <notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="al0060">
   <p>Alt-text: Box 1</p>
  </notes>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
