<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">Porcine coronaviruses, such as porcine transmissible gastroenteritis virus (TGEV), porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV), and swine acute diarrhea syndrome coronavirus (SADS-CoV), are classified as genus 
 <italic>Alphacoronavirus</italic>, while porcine deltacoronavirus (PDCoV) belongs to genus 
 <italic>Deltacoronavirus</italic>. These porcine coronaviruses can infect piglets of all ages by invading the GI tract, with clinical signs of diarrhea, vomiting, and anorexia, resulting in dehydration, metabolic acidosis, and hyperkalemia and eventually leading to death. Scattered intestinal epithelial cell necrosis and villus damage are the primary pathological manifestations of porcine coronavirus infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. There is a higher incidence of porcine coronavirus infection during winter and spring; piglets are particularly more susceptible than adult pigs to porcine coronavirus, with a higher mortality rate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In addition, mixed infection of these four porcine coronaviruses is common among infected pig herds. Current evidence indicates that porcine coronaviruses can be transmitted through the fecal-oral route and infect small intestinal epithelial cells due to resistance to low pH and proteolytic enzymes, causing osmotic diarrhea in infected pigs and even death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition to fecal-oral transmission, PDCoV can also be transmitted through the respiratory tract and induce pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Etiological treatment with additional nutrient supply should be followed to lower mortality, which is caused by secondary infection and dehydration due to diarrhea. It is essential to maintain water and electrolyte balance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition, probiotics, such as Lactobacillus, are reported to be effective in treating porcine coronavirus diarrhea [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].
</p>
