<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A recent meta-analysis of all published HIV-1 subtyping data in FSU countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] showed that subtype A6 is still responsible for almost three quarters (75.6%) of HIV-1 infections. The prevalence of HIV-1 A6 subtype is the highest, accounting for 70.0–99 90.0% of infections in Russia, Ukraine, Belarus, Latvia and Armenia [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. However, along with this, the prevalence of recombinants is steadily increasing. HIV-1 CRFs accounts for about 17.6% of infections with the highest prevalence in Central Asian countries, where 51.7% of all HIV-infection cases caused by recombinants are observed. During the last few years, AG recombinants (CRF02_AG/CRF63_02A1) had quickly overtaken A6 subtype in Central Asia and Russian Siberian region and to date determines the HIV-1 epidemic there (88.4% of all recombinants) [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In contrast, the HIV-1 CRF03_AB recombinant likely represents the second most prevalent genetic form (5.2%) after subtype A6 and reaches a high prevalence (3.0%-12.0%) in Belarus, Russia, and Lithuania [
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241269.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, little is known about the evolutionary history and epidemic potential of the CRF03_AB recombinant that have expanded in the FSU countries. The objective of the present study was to summarize the literature data on HIV infection in FSU with regard to the prevalence of CRF03_AB as well as to examine the evolutionary dynamics and dispersion patterns of this recombinant in the region using the phylodynamic approaches.
</p>
