<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the first report on dengue in Lao PDR, limited data have been published on DENV serotypes/genotypes circulating at the country level [
 <xref rid="B22-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Nevertheless, recent studies suggest a complex and dynamic dengue virus circulation countrywide, but without reference to DENV-4 [
 <xref rid="B22-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. This study is a first step in filling this gap by providing genetic and epidemiologic information on the first DENV-4 epidemic recorded in Lao PDR. The progressive increase of DENV-4 burden occurred in a context of the co-circulation of different DENV serotypes previously described and maintained over the eight years of surveillance (i.e., 2012–2019) [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Since 2009, DENV-4 circulated sporadically in the country [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Sporadic cases or small clusters of grouped cases were observed in Vientiane Capital between February 2014 and August 2015. Subsequently, the proportion of DENV-4 cases gradually increased among the samples tested by the arbovirus surveillance network in Vientiane Capital and became predominant in 2016 at the country level until October 2018. Since then, DENV-2 has overcome DENV-4 in Vientiane Capital and at the country level [
 <xref rid="B33-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, DENV-4 still circulated at a significant level in 2019 (13%; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00728-f002">Figure 2</xref>). These data reveal a circulation of DENV-4 during at least six years (2014–2019) in Lao PDR and could be correlated with an insufficient immunity protection of the Lao population against this serotype as suggested by the impact of DENV-4 in the different age groups.
</p>
