<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous phylogenetic studies showed the recent circulation of two DENV-4 genotypes (Genotype I and II) in Southeast Asia [
 <xref rid="B18-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Both genotypes were detected in Lao PDR, but in two different and independent types of patients, i.e., Lao native autochthonous cases and imported cases by foreigners. All autochthonous cases recorded at the country level investigated here belonged to DENV-4 Genotype I. The first evidence of the presence of DENV-4 Genotype I in Lao PDR came from a strain that was first identified in Saravane Province isolated in 2009 [
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Our serial investigation suggests that this genotype has spread and circulated at least since 2013 at the country level. The genetic difference (2.7% of nucleotide divergence) between the former strain and the recent isolates could be the result of several introductions of DENV-4 Genotype I in Lao PDR since 2009 from different Asian countries. The composition of the different clusters and the circulation of the Lao isolates over several years are a signature of successful consecutive emergences of those independent introduction events. DENV-4 Genotype II was only detected in two imported cases from Thailand/Malaysia in 2014 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00728-f005">Figure 5</xref>). Interestingly, the predominant circulation of the DENV-4 Genotype I in Lao PDR contrasted with some results obtained in South East Asia. Indeed, in the Philippines, a genotype turnover from Genotype I to Genotype II was observed before 2013, and this seemed to match with a high DENV-4 circulation in the country between 2012 and 2016 [
 <xref rid="B39-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The results found in the Philippines were consistent with those from Malaysia in 2001 that showed the circulation of the DENV-4 Genotype II [
 <xref rid="B40-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, both introductions of DENV-4 Genotype II were recorded in February 2014, the dry season in Lao PDR (October–April) and a decrease of vector density. This context, associated with the abnormal lack of rainfalls until August 2015, could explain the non-emergence of DENV-4 Genotype II in Vientiane Capital. However, these dramatically unfavorable conditions for DENV transmission did not hamper the maintenance of a sufficient inoculum of a mixt population of DENV-4 Genotype I isolates at the origin of the rapid spread-off since September 2015. Hence, the genotype selection could impact the epidemiology of DENV emergence and expansion of the virus. Indeed, as previously described in India, China, or the WHO Pacific region, a DENV genotype switch could increase the risk of dengue outbreak [
 <xref rid="B41-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. This selection of DENV genotype could be influenced by several factors, such as serotype-specific herd immunity, viremia titer in humans, and the ability of local mosquito populations, such as 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, to transmit the virus under the influence of environmental and climatic conditions [
 <xref rid="B44-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. These factors need to be investigated for DENV serotypes and genotypes, which circulated in a specific geographical context to improve the knowledge on DENV epidemiology and to prevent DENV outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B50-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
