<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The entomological results demonstrate the presence of both 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in Vientiane Capital with an increase of vector density during the rainfall season as previously described in Asia. The dynamic of DENV transmission in human population follows the trend of the dynamic of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> vectors [
 <xref rid="B51-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Moreover, predominance of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> was highlighted since 2016 in Vientiane Capital. Vector competence of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> from Lao PDR was investigated for DENV-1 and showed that 50% of the females orally exposed to the virus could transmit DENV-1 [
 <xref rid="B52-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. These data indicate a high efficiency of transmission of this serotype by 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> from Lao PDR compared to other 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> populations from the Pacific region (3–37% transmission efficiency), from French Guiana (&lt;10% transmission efficiency), and from Florida (33% transmission efficiency) in the USA [
 <xref rid="B53-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. DENV transmission ability appeared to be a specific interaction between the mosquito population and a virus strain [
 <xref rid="B49-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Vazeille et al. [
 <xref rid="B54-pathogens-09-00728" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] suggested a possible competition between serotypes at the midgut level in co-infected mosquitoes leading to a drastically different transmission potential and, in this case, favoring the competitive displacement of DENV-1 by DENV-4. Thus, the ability of Lao vectors for DENV-4 must be investigated to determine how this factor could influence the onset of new dengue epidemics in Lao PDR.
</p>
