<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0002">We tried to explore the potential psychological problems among the public in Wuhan city and the whole country of China, by using their online searching behaviors. According to the 2019 Chinese search engine user behavior study report released by China Internet Network Information Center Reports, there are 695 million searching engine users in China as of June 2019. The user penetration rate of Baidu search exceeds 90%. Being the largest searching tool in China, Baidu offers Baidu Index Service (BIS), allowing the registered users to harness data on particular keywords being searched. Being one of the functions of BIS, Baidu Search Index (BSI) is calculated by weighting the searching frequency of each keyword in Baidu search according to the searching volume of internet users and the keywords. A series of papers on surveillance and prediction of psychological and suicidal problems by searching behaviors have been reported (
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Bach and Wenz, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Morch et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Rivas et al., 2020</xref>). The retrieval process was as follows: terms being used for searching included combination of “depressed” and “sad” for depressive symptoms, “panic” and “fear” for anxiety symptoms, “insomnia” for sleeping-related problems, “Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD)” and “psychological counseling”. The retrieved areas covered the whole country, with Wuhan as the epicenter of China. For each searching term, BSIs were compared between the same period by Chinese lunar calendar in 2019 and 2020 to explore the potential impact of COVID-19 epidemic on psychological health. The retrieval period covered one month both in 2019 and 2020. In 2020, the searching period was from Jan 24, one day after the lockdown announcement of Wuhan, to Feb 22. Nonparametric Mann–Whitney U test was used to compare the BSIs for the keywords being searched between the same periods of the two consecutive years.
</p>
