<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0004">Data on online searching behaviors indicated that the public were more likely to develop anxiety symptoms as panic and fear than depressive symptoms and insomnia in the early stage of COVID-19 epidemic. However, BSIs for depressive symptoms were decreasing compared with the same period of the previous year. The result also presented different in terms of the psychological problems among medical staff with the prevalence of depressive symptoms ranking higher than anxiety (
 <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020</xref>). This may be due to the fact that medical staff have been in the front line of the battle and with higher risks of exposure to COVID-19. BSIs for psychological counseling had also been on the rise comparing with the same period of the previous year. The result also echoed Liu's findings that online psychological counseling services had been gradually developed and implemented in China (
 <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020</xref>). Online searching behaviors can reflect psychological activities or psychological needs of the public (
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Bach and Wenz, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Morch et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Rivas et al., 2020</xref>). However, it is far from enough to just provide passive psychological services. With prevailed online services and well-developed network, we suggest that it is imperative to build network-based systems throughout the country which include active monitoring, early warning and intervention of potential psychological problems, to better serve the public, especially during public health-related emergencies. There were limitations in this study as we only discussed the short-term psychological impact of the epidemic among the public but the long-term psychological involvement will depend on the control of COVID-19. Again, we only offered insight on the “potential psychological problems” through keyword searching behaviors, rather than “disease diagnosis”. Hence, extrapolation of the conclusion needed to be cautious.
</p>
