<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Our study shows that during the 29-day epidemic period, most of the patients were diagnosed within the first three weeks after the first identified imported case. In the early period, imported cases were predominant in the epidemic. In the later period, local cases were more common, and 77.1% of the patients showed clustering, mainly in families. Cluster outbreaks were also found in Guangzhou patients in Lin’s study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. These findings suggest increasing transmissibility of the virus during the spread [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and, hence, a great challenge in overall prevention and control. However, the local cases did not lead to continuous community transmission, as reflected by the short epidemic period (29 days). This may be attributed to the strict isolation and prevention measures implemented throughout the country and the effective implementation of prevention and control policies by Hainan (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The measures included establishing fever clinics for screening suspicious patients, designating hospitals to focus on treating patients with COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and raising the level of emergency response to COVID-19 prevention and control to the first level promptly at day 4. At the same time, other measures also worked well in blocking the routes of transmission and reducing the chance of infection. Examples include encouraging the public to wear face masks, wash hands more frequently, and stay at home unless necessary and activating joint prevention and control mechanisms and cross-sector control for traffic control at the community level. Moreover, delaying the resumption of work and school and implementing work-from-home policies for employees and online teaching for students were adopted to reduce the probability of clusters [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The reported estimated incubation time of SARS-CoV-2 was based on limited data. Zhong reported that the median incubation period was four days in 291 cases in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Xu et al. found that there is no observable difference between the incubation time for SARS-CoV-2, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV), and middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV), with a mean of 4.9 days for SARS-CoV-2, 4.7 days for SARS, and 5.8 days for MERS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. To avoid the risk of virus spreading, all potentially exposed subjects were required to be isolated for 14 days, which is the longest predicted incubation time. Our epidemiological investigation of 53 patients from Wuhan found that the median time of symptom onset was five days, with a range of one day to 34 days. The patient with the longest incubation period, who was a male in their 70s, flew from Wuhan to Hainan on January 2, 2020 and had no contact with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 patients. He occasionally went to the farmers’ market near his residence to buy vegetables, but there were no confirmed COVID-19 patients associated with the market. He developed symptoms on February 5 and was diagnosed on February 7, 2020 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. This particular case indicates that the longest incubation time may be more than 34 days.
</p>
