<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">Most clinical microbiology laboratories do not offer testing for targeted detection of highly pathogenic HCoVs in house, and, in outbreak situations, suspected specimens are sent out to either local public health laboratories or the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) (see 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This work flow is challenging because of hurdles associated with specimen packaging and shipping in addition to prolonged turnaround times and their associated delay in making decisions related to patients’ isolation. In response to the recent outbreak of COVID-19, several groups nationally and internationally attempted to develop diagnostic assays that could be available for all clinical laboratories, and multiple diagnostic providers within the United States have been striving to receive EUA from the FDA. This response was secondary to the quick spread of the disease, but it was also largely facilitated by the availability of the virus genomic sequences very quickly early in the pandemic. RT-PCR assays developed by the Chinese National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, the University of Hong Kong, and the CDC (which received the EUA by FDA on February 4, 2020) were distributed on a large scale, followed by a very quick expansion in the number of the molecular EUA-approved tests. More than 100 assays are currently authorized for SARS-CoV-2 diagnosis, which are largely RT-PCR based. Other technologies have also received FDA authorization, including the CRISPR (clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats)-based assay SHERLOCK (specific high-sensitivity enzymatic reporter unlocking) assay, which combined CRISPR with isothermal amplification as well as the COVIDSeq assay from Illumina (San Diego, CA), a targeted NGS-based assay. Globally, fast implementation of molecular diagnostics in Europe was remarkable,
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> and several international commercial groups have quickly developed assays as well. These assays include a microarray panel developed by Veredus Laboratories (Singapore), which is an amplification-based array method for the quick detection of SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2 (VereCoV detection kit), in addition to RT-PCR kits that were developed by Amoy Diagnostics (Xiamen, China), Altona Diagnostics (Hamburg, Germany), BGI group (Beijing Genomics Institute, Guangdong, China), among others. A list of all the EUA molecular SARS-CoV-2 assays is available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19-emergency-use-authorizations-medical-devices/vitro-diagnostics-euas" id="intref0015" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19-emergency-use-authorizations-medical-devices/vitro-diagnostics-euas</ext-link>.
</p>
