<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the main site of replication for HEV is the liver, non-hepatic replication has been shown in the brain, kidney, placenta, and others [
 <xref rid="B180-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. This may explain a series of different extrahepatic manifestations that can occur in infected patients. Neurological manifestations include Guillain–Barré syndrome and neuralgic amyotrophy, while kidney disorders such as cryoglobulinemia and hematological conditions have also been described in association with hepatitis E [
 <xref rid="B181-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>,
 <xref rid="B186-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>,
 <xref rid="B187-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>]. In addition, deaths due to fulminant hepatitis have been reported in 0.5 to 4% of patients, and this percentage is known to be higher in people with pre-existing liver disease [
 <xref rid="B188-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>] and among young children [
 <xref rid="B189-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>]. HEV superinfection could additionally influence the outcome and progression of HBV-related liver diseases [
 <xref rid="B190-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>]. Furthermore, severe disease outcomes may occur in pregnant women infected with HEV-1 with studies describing maternal mortality rates &gt;30% within the third trimester, mainly due to fulminant hepatic failure [
 <xref rid="B17-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In immunocompromised persons such as solid organ and hematopoietic stem cell transplant recipients, HEV infection may persist. Patients with chronic hepatitis E will often rapidly progress to liver cirrhosis and have an increased mortality rate [
 <xref rid="B158-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. There is no approved drug against HEV infection. If initial reduction of immunosuppression does not lead to HEV clearance, off-label treatment for chronic hepatitis E is indicated with ribavirin. Non-responding liver-transplant patients can be further treated with pegylated interferon alfa-2a and pegylated interferon alfa-2b [
 <xref rid="B168-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>]. Several molecules with in vitro antiviral activity against HEV have been described. Repurposed antivirals include 2′-C-methylcytidine (2-CMC) [
 <xref rid="B191-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>], NITD008 and GPC-N114 [
 <xref rid="B192-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>], ciprofloxacin and IFN-λ [
 <xref rid="B193-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>], and sofosbuvir [
 <xref rid="B194-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. Compound screening studies have revealed plant ethanol extracts from 
 <italic>L. mauritiana</italic> [
 <xref rid="B195-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>] and 
 <italic>L. platyphylla</italic> [
 <xref rid="B196-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>], as well as zinc [
 <xref rid="B197-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>], and the small molecule 66E2 [
 <xref rid="B198-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>] as potential antivirals. An FDA-approved drug, deptropine, a histamine H1 receptor antagonist used in asthma treatment, showed anti-HEV activity in cell culture and synergized with ribavirin [
 <xref rid="B199-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>]. Target-guided approaches include peptide conjugated phosphorodiamidate morpholino oligomers (PPMO) [
 <xref rid="B200-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>] and proteasome inhibitor MG132 [
 <xref rid="B201-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>,
 <xref rid="B202-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>] in HEV-1 cell culture, the cyclic peptide CP11, which inhibits interaction of HEV with the ESCRT [
 <xref rid="B203-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>], several inhibitors of nucleotide synthesis, including mycophenolic acid [
 <xref rid="B204-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>], Brequinar, and Leflunomide [
 <xref rid="B205-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>], and the natural compound silvestrol [
 <xref rid="B206-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>]. However, only silvestrol [
 <xref rid="B206-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>] and the hepatitis C virus polymerase inhibitor sofosbuvir [
 <xref rid="B194-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>] advanced to in vivo studies. Unfortunately, sofosbuvir monotherapy failed to prove its potency to reduce HEV viral loads in a phase II pilot trial [
 <xref rid="B207-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">207</xref>]. Finally, the only developed vaccine against HEV, Hecolin
 <sup>®</sup>, is thus far only approved in China [
 <xref rid="B20-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, several other candidates based on the HEV capsid protein are currently being developed using different expression systems, such as baculovirus-infected insect cells [
 <xref rid="B208-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>], prokaryotic systems [
 <xref rid="B209-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">209</xref>], expression in yeast [
 <xref rid="B210-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">210</xref>,
 <xref rid="B211-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>], vectored vaccines [
 <xref rid="B212-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>], and chimeric vaccines [
 <xref rid="B213-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>,
 <xref rid="B214-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. So far, apart from Hecolin
 <sup>®</sup>, only two candidates have entered clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B215-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>,
 <xref rid="B216-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>]. An effective vaccine is an important step in preventing severe hepatitis E-related liver disease in risk populations such as pregnant women and immunocompromised patients.
</p>
