<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The terrain of China is high in the west and low in the west. The coastline of the eastern and southern continents exceeds 18 400 kilometers. East China is plains and hills, with an area of more than 2 million square kilometers and an elevation of less than 1000 meters. The southern part of the “Qinling-Huaihe” has a subtropical tropical climate, with an average annual temperature of more than 15°C, and a daily average temperature of more than 20°C in summer and autumn.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]
 </sup> In recent years, dengue cases have increased dramatically in many provinces of mainland China, and many epidemics have occurred in some provinces, such as Fujian, Guangxi, Hainan, and Yunnan provinces.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]
 </sup> These provinces are distributed in the southeast, with high temperature, abundant rainfall, and busy trade exchanges with neighboring southeast Asian countries.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]
 </sup> According to 2014 epidemiological data in Guangzhou, the outbreak of dengue fever is also positively correlated with land type, daytime land surface temperature, nighttime land surface temperature, population density, and Gross Domestic Product (GDP) (correlation coefficients were 0.48, 0.61, 0.70, 0.71, and 0.21, respectively).
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]
 </sup> In response to the outbreak of dengue, on September 1, 1989, dengue became a disease that should be regularly reported in China, which helped to reduce the huge economic burden of the national economy, the health care sector, and people's lives.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
  <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]
 </sup> However, due to the uneven development of different regions, diverse climate characteristics, and differences in medical and health conditions, there are some differences in the epidemiological characteristics of dengue in different provinces in China.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]
 </sup> In this study, we describe the scale and distribution of dengue in mainland China according to the notifiable reporting data, focusing on the time and geographical patterns from 1990 to 2019, comparing the seasonal and monthly distribution of dengue between Guangdong Province and mainland China, and analyzing the age, gender, and occupational distribution of dengue during the period from 2010 to 2017, to identify high-risk areas, months, and populations to help prevent and control dengue.
</p>
