<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0160">
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0010">
  <list-item id="lsti0050">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0070">Apart from any notion of contact, systematic screening for asymptomatic forms in children in the community is useless, because of the weak transmission role of children.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0055">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0075">Any child exposed in his or her home to a COVID+ person must be tested before returning to the community. If the child is asymptomatic, he or she may return to the community if the test result is negative. This return must not compromise the isolation of infected persons in the home.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0060">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0080">Any symptomatic child of at least 6 years of age or adolescent (with cough, and/or fever, and/or digestive disorders) must be screened before returning to the community unless a diagnosis of another infectious disease is made with certainty (e.g., scarlet fever, streptococcal tonsillopharyngitis, clinical enteroviral entities such as herpangina or foot hand mouth syndrome, urinary tract infections, etc.).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0065">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0085">In symptomatic children under 6 years of age (nurseries/daycare centers and kindergartens), the high frequency of viral infections during the autumn and winter, combined with the low transmissibility of COVID-19 by young children, should reserve the indications for COVID PCR to:
    <list list-type="simple" id="lis0015">
     <list-item id="lsti0005">
      <label>∘</label>
      <p id="par0090">patients requiring hospitalization or those severe enough to warrant further investigations;</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0010">
      <label>∘</label>
      <p id="par0095">children who have had contact with a COVID+ proven case;</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0015">
      <label>∘</label>
      <p id="par0100">children in contact at home with persons considered at risk for severe forms of COVID-19;</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0020">
      <label>∘</label>
      <p id="par0105">children whose symptoms do not improve within the usual timeframe for respiratory infections (e.g., more than 3 days for fever).</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0070">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0110">Screening of an entire class is only warranted if one teacher in the class is COVID+ or if at least two children in the class are symptomatic and COVID+. The rarity of child-to-child transmission does not justify initiating a whole class screening based on an isolated case of symptomatic or asymptomatic children.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
