<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding the different RV types, few studies have focused on their clinical impact, probably because of the recent introduction of molecular detection methods. Infection with RV-C has been associated with more-severe lower respiratory tract illness in the pediatric population compared to RV-A [
 <xref rid="B40-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]; however, this finding has not been consistent across studies [
 <xref rid="B38-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Regarding acute bronchiolitis, RV-C seems clinically similar to RV-A and RV-B [
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In 2014, Selvaggiet al. genotyped 40 RV-infected patients, discovering a frequency of 45% of RV-A subtype and 55% of RV-C type [
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Skjerven and colleagues in 2016 similarly reported a higher prevalence of RV-C type in their 122 RV-infected patients (71.3% vs. 28.7% of RV-A/B types) [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In both studies, no significant differences in terms of hospital LOS and the level of supportive care emerged among the viral types. Similarly, Hasegawa et al. genotyped both the American and Finnish cohorts without discovering significant differences in terms of LOS, PICU admission, and CPAP/intubation requirement between the three different RV types [
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Bergroth and colleagues genotyped their 101 RV patients and specifically compared them with RSV-bronchiolitis. They found that RV-A and RV-C infections (but not RV-B infection) were associated with lower LOS than RSV-infection (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.003) [
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Nevertheless, the extremely low frequency of detected RV-B type (only three cases) prevents to draw conclusions about the role of this viral species on this matter.
</p>
