<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para390">We hypothesised that community-based HIV testing, ART initiation, monitoring, and resupply would increase the proportion of individuals living with HIV who reach viral suppression. This theory was based on observational evidence that community health-care worker-led HIV interventions increased suppression.
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> Barriers to care include standard opening hours, stigma, unfavourable perceptions of clinics and staff, cost of transport, and lost wages.
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Men might experience additional barriers such as gender norms that inhibit men from seeking care.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> As a result, many individuals do not initiate ART at conventional facilities.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> After ART initiation, guidelines might require that clients show retention in care for 12 months and viral suppression before accessing decentralised ART refills.
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> Requiring multiple clinic visits contributes to loss to follow-up over the first year of ART.
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> If clients are transferred to ART refills outside the clinic (eg, decentralised dispensing, adherence groups, community, and home) compared with clinic ART, they remained virally supressed.
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Offering convenient locations and times after hours and on weekends, being flexible to meet travel or mobility needs, offering quarterly refills, and streamlining monitoring and resupply had better viral suppression outcomes, especially for men.
</p>
