<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0015">There are now many observational studies from several countries, models, or meta-analyses that allow us to assert the low transmitter status of children compared with adults. In Irish schools, no secondary cases were found among the 1,001 children who came into contact with three pediatric cases (10–15-year-old children) and three adult cases 
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. In England, national surveillance following the reopening of educational settings in June and July 2020 showed that only 70 children were affected out of more than 1 million children attending preschool and primary school 
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Only 0.01% of open educational settings had an outbreak. Importantly, staff members had an increased risk of SARS-CoV-2 infections compared with students in any educational setting, and the majority of cases linked to outbreaks were in staff 
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. In Guangzhou (China), a retrospective study of 195 intrafamily clusters showed that the lowest risk of infection was in contacts under 20 years of age (OR = 0.23 [0.11–0.46]) compared with contacts over 60 years of age. Transmission was highest during the incubation period 
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In Switzerland, the evaluation of 111 intrafamily contacts around 40 cases of infected children under 16 years of age showed that a pediatric case was suspected to be the first intrafamily case in only 8% of cases 
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. In Australia, testing of contacts linked to 12 children and 15 adults in 15 schools (children aged 6 years and older) and 10 kindergartens/nurseries (children aged 6 weeks to 5 years) showed a child-to-child attack rate of 0.3%, a child-to-adult attack rate of 1%, an adult-to-child attack rate of 1.5%, and an adult-to-adult attack rate of 4.4%. Only one daycare center experienced an outbreak with six adults and seven children infected out of 35 contact cases; transmissions were adult-to-adult and adult-to-child 
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. In France, 80 schoolchildren were tested in three classes attended by a 9-year-old infected boy. No secondary cases were observed 
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. In Korea, the reports for contacts of 5706 index cases were analyzed. Children between 0 and 9 years of age represented only 29 index cases (0.5%) and those between 10 and 19 years of age only 124 index cases (2.2%). The number of infected people was much higher in the home than outside the home (11.8% vs. 1.9%, respectively). The rate of cases linked to the index case was the lowest among children aged 0–9 years (5.3% at home vs. 1.1% outside the home). This rate was high among adolescents aged 10–19 years (18.6% at home vs. 0.9% outside the home). However, it was not known whether the index case, defined as the first identified case, was actually the transmitter 
 <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In Rhode Island, strict surveillance was implemented after the reopening of 666 communities for children (0–12 years), with adults wearing masks. Reports of infections were rare: 25 situations with one case without secondary transmission; four situations with possible secondary transmission 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.
</p>
