<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A large number of studies have demonstrated that virus vectored vaccine can induce strong specific antibody-mediated humoral responses and IFN-γ secreting cellular responses in pigs, which can provide partial effective protection against ASFV challenge [
 <xref rid="B96-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. In 2019, as shown in 
 <xref rid="vaccines-08-00531-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, Lokhandwala’s group evaluated the immune response and protective effect induced by two recombinant adenovirus combinations, Ad-ASFV-I (A151R, B119L, B602L, EP402R∆PRR, B438L, K205R, A104R, pp62, and p72) and Ad-ASFV-II (p30, p54, pp62, p72, and pp220), by intranasal challenge of ASFV-Georgia 2007/1 on the basis of previous studies. Vaccination of pigs with Ad-ASFV-I in combination with BioMize0226 adjuvant revealed that although strong ASFV antigen-specific IgG responses were induced, vaccinated pigs were not able to resist the challenge of the virulent strain Georgia 2007/1 and developed an enhanced immune-response dependent disease. Thus, which factors play a role is unsolved, while high levels of antibodies seem to have some contribution. Additionally, two adjuvants (BioMize0226 and ZTS-01) were used to evaluate Ad-ASFV-II in this study, interestingly, in the presence of BioMize0226 adjuvant, ASFV-II induced much higher antigen-specific antibody response, but 8/10 vaccinated pigs died from virulent strain challenge. In contrast, the antibody response induced by ZTS-01 preparation was even weaker, paradoxically, 5/9 vaccinated pigs could resist the attack of homologous virulent strains, and survivors showed mild clinical symptoms and no viremia (non-statistical significance). The contradictory results in this study show that immune-induced antibody responses are not necessarily proportional to protective immunity, highlighting the complexity of the role of antibody responses in anti-ASFV, and also reflecting that different adjuvants may induce different innate immune responses, which require further study and evaluation of the efficacy of neoantigens formulated in appropriate adjuvants [
 <xref rid="B99-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Moreover, Murgia et al. discovered that the strategy enhanced with natural attenuated strain OURT88/3 could broaden the recognition of ASFV epitopes, but its protective efficacy needs further verification [
 <xref rid="B100-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. In Hubner’s group, the rapid evolving genetic manipulation platform based on CRISPR/Cas9 provides a new method for screening potential immune protective antigen for more effective development of ASF virus-vectored vaccines [
 <xref rid="B101-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. 
</p>
