<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">In the ART-naïve cohort, there were significant associations between HIV patients with CRF01_AE and lower baseline CD4+ cell count at diagnosis, as well as higher mortality, compared with CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC, and other genotypes. A previous study showed that the baseline CD4+ cell count in CRF01_AE patients was lower than that in non-CRF01_AE patients for men who have sex with men
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Our study further demonstrates that CRF01_AE patients have a lower CD4+ cell count than those with CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC, or other genotypes at initial diagnosis in a large population with different transmission routes. Previous studies have suggested that CRF01_AE is associated with faster AIDS progression (defined as CD4+ T-cell counts decreasing to &lt; 200 cells/μl or &lt; 350 cells/μl) compared to that with non-CRF01_AE
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. We demonstrate for the first time that patients with CRF01_AE exhibit a significantly higher mortality compared than those with CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC, and other genotypes, in a large observational cohort study. Some studies have described that a lower baseline CD4+ cell count is associated with a risk of higher mortality compared to a higher baseline CD4+ cell count in HIV patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. The CD4+ cell count and immune status are intermediate variables between genotypes and deaths from the perspective of epidemiological causality. To further avoid bias caused by different genotypes with heterogeneous baseline CD4+ cell counts, we performed sensitivityanalysis using a multivariate Cox model grouped by CD4+ cell count and obtained consistent results. It has been suggested that the CRF01_AE genotype is an independent risk factor for mortality in ART-naïve patients, compared with the CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC, and other genotypes. The entry of HIV into immune cells is highly dependent on the interaction of the viral envelope (R5 tropism and/or X4 tropism) with its target co-receptor (CCR5 and/or CXCR4)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>, and an accelerated CD4+ cell count decline appears to be driven by an elevated proportion of CD4+ cells expressing CXCR4
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Researchers have shown that CRF01_AE has a higher degree of X4 tropism than non-CRF01_AE in patients infected via sexual transmission
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
