<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">In the ‘after ART’ cohort, our analyses revealed no significant difference in mortality among HIV patients with different genotypes, in either univariate or multivariate Cox models. In this study, the 6-year follow-up mortality of HIV patients after ART was an average of 3.8 deaths per 100 person-years, which is slightly higher than the mortality rates of some developed countries, such as England and Canada
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies have shown that there is no significant difference in immune recovery between CRF01_AE and B strains in a combined ART cohort
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Recently, researchers found that compared to that with CRF07_BC, CRF01_AE is associated with a lower CD4+ cell count recovery and a slower rate of immune recovery in combined ART
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. Our study is the first to show that there is no difference in the therapeutic efficacy of combined ART among patients with CRF01_AE, CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC, and other genotypes, using death as the endpoint. Previous studies have shown that AZT exhibits a higher efficacy against viruses with R5 rather than X4 tropism. This might be explained by the fact that CCR5-expressing activated memory T cells demonstate a high efficiency in the activation of reverse transcriptase inhibitors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Some nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitors, like 3TC, are activated equally in both CCR5 and CXCR4 of target cells, and drugs do not require activation, such as the protease inhibitor ritonavir, show equal activity against both CCR5- and CXCR4-specific variants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
