<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">On the occasion of World Hepatitis Day in July 2019, the WHO called on all states to ‘invest in eliminating hepatitis’. A total of 124 countries out of 194 have developed plans to reach this goal, but over 40% of national plans do not have dedicated budget lines to support the actions aimed at achieving elimination [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Furthermore, globally, less than 5% of people with chronic viral infection know their status (unknown infection) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Against this background, screening for HCV infection can be considered a useful pathway for revealing unknown infected people. In 2013, the CDC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] considered screening for adults born between 1945 and 1965 (baby boomers). These individuals must be tested at least once for HCV infection (without prior assessment of HCV risk factors). The anti-HCV test was also recommended for drug users, for those who have always used drugs by injection or for those who have used drugs a few times in previous years, people who received concentrations of coagulation factors produced before 1987, those subjected to long-term haemodialysis or those with persistently abnormal levels of ALT or HIV infection. Screening for HCV is also recommended for individuals who have received previous transfusions or organ transplants, including people who have been informed that they received blood from a donor who later tested positive for HCV infection or who had received a blood transfusion, blood components or organ transplant before July 1992. The CDC recommended performing the HCV test following skin or mucous membrane exposure to needles or sharp objects contaminated with HCV-positive blood. Moreover, for people who may have been exposed to HCV within the last 6 months, the execution of the HCV RNA test or follow-up for HCV antibody is recommended. In 2017, the American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases and the Infectious Diseases Society of America [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] instead recommended performing the HCV test for people born between 1945 and 1965 (ascertained by the country of birth) without a risk assessment. It was recommended that all other people be screened for HCV infection risk factors and that a one-off test be performed for all people with associated changes, conditions and circumstances and risk of HCV infection. According to them, all people with active HCV infection must be referred to a service that can ensure complete management of the disease.
</p>
