<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mostly coronavirus causes respiratory and enteric diseases in human beings. SARS and MERS caused major outbreaks in the human population in the years 2003 and 2012 respectively which had mortality rates between 10 and 40%. Current coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) has a lot of genomic similarity with the main SARS virus but the former has a higher spread.[
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] The disease starts when a human inhales the viral particles through infected droplets or fomites and the virus travels down to lower respiratory airways. In the respiratory system in order to enter the alveolar epithelial cell, the virus binds to the cell through ACE2 enzyme receptors.[
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Virus alters the normal respiratory cell and induces a massive cytokine release which induces inflammatory damage and it also activates other inflammatory chemokines from surrounding vascular endothelial cells of the alveolar capillaries, which then continue this inflammatory damage cycle. This excess of inflammation causes lung damage through severe pneumonia and spreading to involve other organs with time leading to multi-organ failure.[
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Researchers also found out that the novel coronavirus originated from wild bats, which was also responsible for the SARS epidemic. Modes of transmission include a person-to-person transmission especially respiratory droplets due to sneezing or coughing by an infected individual as well as fomites where coronavirus can persist for a few hours to few days.[
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Even in hospitals, person-to-person transmission can occur easily leading to the spread of this infection.[
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Social distancing as well as washing hands with soap or using hand sanitizers having around 70% concentration of alcohol prove to be effective in controlling the spread of this infection. For health professionals; adequate masks, gloves as well as personal protective equipment are essential.[
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Researchers like Huang 
 <italic>et al.</italic> conducted a study on 41 confirmed COVID patients. The major clinical features which were visible in patients were fever, myalgia, dyspnea, dry cough. The uncommon symptoms noticed were anosmia, cough with sputum production, headache, and diarrhea. Chest X-ray showed opacities bilaterally in the lung region which could be further persuaded in computed tomography (CT scan). CT scan was also helpful in detecting early cases which were not evident in chest X-ray. The serious cases ended up in septic shock, acute respiratory distress syndrome, kidney damage, etc.[
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Therefore, the categorization of COVID-19 was based on the severity of infection from asymptomatic, mild, moderate, and severe viral infection.[
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] It was also dependent on CT scan findings which denoted the level of severity of spread in the lungs resulting in mild to severe pneumonia cases [
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>]. Another study carried out by Chen 
 <italic>et al.</italic> inferred that older people with other co-debilitating conditions like diabetes, hypertension, cardiovascular diseases, etc., were more susceptible to a serious form of COVID-19 disease due to less immunity.[
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]
</p>
