<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The migration of individuals, especially intercity migration, plays a core role in the spread of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Wuhan is a metropolis with a population of more than 11 million and is also one of the transportation hubs in China. During the Spring Festival in 2019, 5 million people set off from Wuhan to other cities in China. Large-scale migration greatly enhanced the spread of COVID-19 from outbreak areas to other cities in China. Therefore, the intercity migration data is also an important indicator for describing and predicting the spread of the virus. Here, daily intercity migration data for 367 cities in China are collected and utilized to construct intercity migration networks. Further, a model established by combining complex network theory and the classic SEIR model can be used to describe how COVID-19 spreads from Wuhan to other cities in China. This dynamic model has more than 1800 unknown parameters to be determined from the historical data. The inference of model parameter values from rare historical time-course data can be reformulated as an optimization problem and is still one of the most challenging tasks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Evolutionary algorithms have outstanding performance in solving nonlinear optimization problem [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Hence, it is worth developing evolutionary algorithms, which should be robust against noise, efficient in computation, and flexible enough to meet different constraints for estimating these 1800 unknown parameters. In this article, a novel pseudocoevolutionary simulated annealing algorithm is proposed to solve this problem [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Results show that the proposed algorithm successfully identified optimal parameter sets of this epidemic spreading model. Also, the model can fit the number of infected, recovered individuals, and the death toll of each city with a minor error.
</p>
