<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0290">Thioridazine possesses anti-EBOV (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Johansesn et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2018</xref>), HCV (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chamoun-Emanuelli et al., 2013</xref>), SFV (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Pohjala et al., 2011</xref>), and RVFV (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Filone et al., 2010</xref>) activity. In the case of EBOV comparison of the results obtained by 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Johansesn et al. (2015)</xref> show that fluphenazine, prochlorperazine, and thioridazine strongly inhibit EBOV entry into the host cells. Moreover, thioridazine was more cytotoxic towards host cells than fluphenazine and prochlorperazine. 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chamoun-Emanuelli et al. (2013)</xref> show that thioridazine is less potent towards HCV than fluphenazine but more potent than chlorpromazine and prochlorperazine. It can be explained by the chemical structure of the phenothiazines, which is presented in 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Piperazine ring phenothiazines are more potent than those without it (prochlorperazine and fluphenazine &gt; chlorpromazine), also the presence of a propanol group on the piperazine ring and a trifluoromethyl group at position 2 (fluphenazine) increases the anti-HCV potency. Noteworthy the thioridazine concentration caused by anti-HCV activity is in the range of therapeutic human plasma concentration. It makes thioridazine a possible candidate for effective HCV treatment. The results obtained by 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Pohjala et al. (2011)</xref> show that chlorpromazine, perphenazine, and thioridazine decrease entry and replication of SFV. Moreover, the obtained IC
 <sub>50</sub> for SFV replication showed that thioridazine inhibits the viral replication a little bit stronger than chlorpromazine and about 2 times stronger than perphenazine.
</p>
