<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">It spread through contact in four different stages. In stage-1, there is transmission of disease from animal to human or it can invade nearby area by migration of infected people. As in China human got the infection from animals and because of their migration it invaded to other counties too. In stage-2, infection is transmitted through contact from one person to another which is known as local transmission. Till stage-2 it is easy to control the infection but as infection crosses the border of stage 2 and enters stage 3 which is quite difficult to control because it affects the large community. In stage 3 one infected person spread infection to a community depending on the reproduction number of the disease. Its reproduction number is 3 then an infected person is communicable to 3 other healthy person. It finally stops at stage-4 which is termed as epidemic stage with the heavy loss of life (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We must create awareness to prevent stage 3 to come. A small ignorance can lead to epidemic condition. Initially the concern was limited to China but very soon Italy has surpassed the cases of corona and condition soon became very critical. On 19 March 2020, 475 deaths have reported in Italy while China has never reported over 150 death. This is enough to explain the effect of epidemic nature of COVID-19. Till the end of March 2020 the condition has flipped the situation, the China has controlled its condition but became uncontrollable in USA and Italy. By the mid of April 2020, Spain, France, Germany, UK soon included in the list whereas Iran and Turkey are also on the way to exceed the condition of China. The condition of the cases in these countries are well defined by their reproduction number as mentioned in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Anavaibility of vaccine or defined treatment has suggested to take prevention than to wait for cure. The most effective method included in this series is social distancing. This has brought about lockdown in whole world.
</p>
