<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HEV belongs to the genus 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus</italic>, containing four species, namely 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus A, B, C,</italic> and 
 <italic>D</italic> with 
 <italic>A</italic> containing the genotypes HEV-1 to HEV-8 [
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The genotypes that infect humans include HEV-1 to -4, -7, and 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus C</italic>, casually termed rat HEV [
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. HEV-1 and -2 infect only humans and cause large waterborne outbreaks due to contaminated drinking water in endemic regions of South and Southeast Asia, Africa, and Mexico [
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. HEV-3 and -4 infect both humans and animals, cause sporadic cases in developed countries, and are mainly spread through consumption or close contact with contaminated animal products [
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. HEV-7 and rat HEV infections are rarely reported. HEV-1 is mainly transmitted via the fecal–oral route, but also by vertical transmission from mother to child, from person to person, and by blood transfusions [
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. HEV-2 is transmitted via the fecal–oral route and human-to-human [
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In contrast, HEV-3 and -4 are transmitted by transfusion of contaminated blood products, consuming contaminated shellfish, contact with infected animals, environmental contamination by animal manure run-off, and consumption of raw or undercooked meat [
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-09-00856" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Hepatitis E is not a sole health burden of the developing world, however, with numbers of reported sporadic cases increasing in industrialized nations, where the virus is spread primarily through zoonotic transmission.
</p>
