<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Rep Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Rep Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRIID</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-6625</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6633</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7582078</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33123391</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/8822753</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 Pneumonia in Patients on Chronic Hydroxychloroquine Therapy: Three Cases of COVID-19 Pneumonia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9324-6883</contrib-id><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>Awan K.</given-names></name><email>awanrahman90@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7319-5668</contrib-id><name><surname>Purdy</surname><given-names>Adam G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3373-1873</contrib-id><name><surname>Ender</surname><given-names>Peter T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">
<sup>1</sup>Section of Pulmonary and Critical Care, St. Luke's University Health Network, Bethlehem, PA, USA</aff><aff id="I2">
<sup>2</sup>Section of Infectious Diseases, St. Luke's University Health Network, Bethlehem, PA, USA</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editor: Larry M. Bush</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>2020</volume><elocation-id>8822753</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Awan K. Rahman et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Hydroxychloroquine has gained popularity as a potential preventative and treatment of COVID-19 pneumonia due to its in vitro activity against the virus. These three cases of COVID-19 pneumonia of varying severities occurred in the setting of chronic hydroxychloroquine use. These cases argue against the use of hydroxychloroquine as a preventative or therapeutic option for COVID-19 pneumonia.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>SARS-CoV-2 is a nonsegmented, positive-sense RNA virus identified as the cause of the coronavirus pandemic of 2019 (COVID-19) [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The virus was first described in Wuhan, China, in December of 2019. Since then, SARS-CoV-2 has spread rapidly, causing a global pandemic. COVID-19 involves a wide spectrum of disease including asymptomatic infection, mild respiratory illness, and life-threatening respiratory failure with development of immune dysregulation and cytokine release syndrome (CRS) [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Thus far, only remdesivir has been approved by the FDA under Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) to treat COVID-19 and prevent progression of illness. There are currently no proven preventative antivirals [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic, hydroxychloroquine has gained popularity as a potential preventative approach and therapeutic option for COVID-19 pneumonia. Hydroxychloroquine has been shown to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication in vitro [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The antiviral activity of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine stems from their ability to inhibit fusion of the virus with cell membranes [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Other proposed mechanisms of protection include inhibition of nucleic acid replication and glycosylation of viral proteins [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The in vivo activity of hydroxychloroquine against SARS-CoV-2 is unclear.</p><p>Several studies with a variety of methodologies have argued for and against the efficacy of hydroxychloroquine in the treatment of COVID-19 [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. While awaiting the results of ongoing randomized trials using hydroxychloroquine for both the treatment and prevention of COVID-19 pneumonia, limited data are available to confirm efficacy.</p><p>Some have suggested that chronic hydroxychloroquine use in the setting of rheumatologic disease may be beneficial for the prevention of COVID-19 [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The following cases describe COVID-19 pneumonia of varying severities despite chronic hydroxychloroquine treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Case 1</title><p>A 55-year-old female with systemic lupus erythematous (SLE), fibromyalgia, type 2 diabetes, trigeminal neuralgia, and depression presented with a temperature of 102.4&#x02009;F, myalgia, and shortness of breath. She tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 via polymerase chain reaction (PCR) from a nasopharyngeal swab and had elevated inflammatory markers on admission (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Her chest X-ray was clear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). The patient had been maintained on hydroxychloroquine 200&#x02009;mg twice daily and methylprednisolone 8&#x02009;mg daily for treatment of SLE for years prior to becoming ill with COVID-19. The patient had an uncomplicated hospital course. She was continued on her outpatient regimen of hydroxychloroquine, and her methylprednisolone dose was increased to 16&#x02009;mg daily on admission. Additionally, she was treated with vitamin D, vitamin C, zinc, and atorvastatin on presentation. Her symptoms and inflammatory markers rapidly improved. She did not require any supplemental oxygen. The patient was discharged after fifteen days in stable condition.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Case 2</title><p>A 42-year-old female with systolic and diastolic congestive heart failure with an ejection fraction of 20% secondary to ischemic cardiomyopathy, epilepsy, hypertension, bipolar disorder, and SLE presented with a temperature of 102.2&#x02009;F, shortness of breath, and cough. She tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 via PCR of a nasopharyngeal swab on admission. She was chronically maintained on hydroxychloroquine 200&#x02009;mg twice daily and prednisone 15&#x02009;mg daily for SLE prior to this acute illness. While hospitalized, the patient had increasing oxygen requirements up to 15&#x02009;L via nasal cannula and elevated inflammatory and coagulation markers (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Her chest X-ray revealed worsening airspace disease, and subsequent computed tomography (CT) of the chest revealed diffuse areas of ground-glass opacities and bibasilar consolidations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). She was continued on her home hydroxychloroquine on admission, and her steroids were converted to intravenous methylprednisolone 80&#x02009;mg daily on the fourth day of hospitalization. She was also treated with atorvastatin, vitamin C, and zinc on presentation. With these measures, she was eventually tapered off of supplemental oxygen and discharged to an inpatient rehabilitation unit on a prednisone taper after sixteen days of care.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>4. Case 3</title><p>A 62-year-old female with SLE, sarcoidosis, fibromyalgia, asthma, pulmonary fibrosis, and type 2 diabetes presented with a temperature of 102.8&#x02009;F, cough, shortness of breath, fatigue, and diarrhea. She was in contact with a family member who had COVID-19 and subsequently tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 via PCR from a nasopharyngeal swab on admission. She had been chronically maintained on hydroxychloroquine 200&#x02009;mg twice daily and methylprednisolone 12&#x02009;mg daily for treatment of SLE and sarcoidosis prior to her current illness. The patient was continued on her outpatient dose of hydroxychloroquine, and her corticosteroid was converted to intravenous methylprednisolone 100&#x02009;mg every 12&#x02009;hours on the second day of hospitalization. She was also treated with vitamin D, vitamin C, zinc, and atorvastatin on admission. The patient clinically deteriorated despite these interventions. She was transferred to the intensive care unit for escalating oxygen requirements and developed increasing inflammatory and coagulation markers (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) a few days after presentation. She received a one-time dose of intravenous tocilizumab on the fourth day of hospitalization. CT pulmonary angiogram was negative for a pulmonary embolism, but did reveal worsening bilateral ground-glass opacities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). She was eventually intubated and mechanically ventilated. Additionally, the patient completed a five-day course of remdesivir starting on the tenth day of hospitalization. Unfortunately, she expired from respiratory failure nineteen days after admission.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>5. Discussion</title><p>Until effective treatment options are available, the COVID-19 pandemic will continue to have a detrimental impact on healthcare and daily life. To expedite the availability of agents to treat COVID-19, repurposed medications are being clinically evaluated. Hydroxychloroquine has gained popularity as a potential treatment for COVID-19 because of its in vitro antiviral and immunomodulatory properties [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Published and pre-peer reviewed analyses of hydroxychloroquine in the treatment of COVID-19 have argued both for and against the benefit of this medication for the treatment of SARS-CoV-2 infection [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These studies have methodologic limitations that hamper interpretation of the data. The lack of any consistent positive findings would argue against hydroxychloroquine being a potent and effective antiviral agent for the treatment of COVID-19.</p><p>Chloroquine, a close relative of hydroxychloroquine, has shown potent in vitro activity against influenza virus and other coronaviruses, including SARS-CoV-1. SARS-CoV-1 was the cause of the SARS epidemic in 2003 [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In vivo studies using chloroquine in various animal models have failed to consistently translate into successful outcomes in treating these viral infections [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In a randomized trial, chloroquine was ineffective at preventing influenza infection [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A comparison of chloroquine to hydroxychloroquine in vitro demonstrated that hydroxychloroquine was more effective against SAR-COV-2 [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This argues that hydroxychloroquine is a more potent agent than chloroquine for treating SARS-COV-2.</p><p>A more recent case series of individuals with rheumatic disease on hydroxychloroquine did not reveal any difference in the development of COVID-19 [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A randomized trial of postexposure prophylaxis using hydroxychloroquine did not reveal any protective effect of developing illness compatible with COVID-19 [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>The presented cases are similar to the abovementioned case series and add further doubt to any potent efficacy for hydroxychloroquine as a prophylactic or therapeutic agent against COVID-19 pneumonia. In comparison, the presented cases further demonstrate that hydroxychloroquine use does not decrease the severity of illness. The included patients had varying severities of illness including critical illness requiring ventilator support. Chronic glucocorticoid treatment in these patients may have increased the risk of breakthrough infection in the setting of hydroxychloroquine, which may confound interpretation of these findings. Additionally, pre-existing conditions may have contributed to the severity of illness in these patients.</p><p>These three cases reveal breakthrough infection with SARS-CoV-2 despite the ongoing chronic use of hydroxychloroquine. They demonstrate variability in inflammatory and coagulation markers, as well as severity of clinical disease, despite all patients being on hydroxychloroquine and glucocorticoid therapy (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). As the incidence of COVID-19 continues to increase, ongoing studies will offer insight into effective treatments for this devastating disease. The description of COVID-19 infection occurring despite chronic hydroxychloroquine use argues against this agent being a potent antiviral agent that will be effective in the prevention or treatment of this illness. Results of the ongoing prophylactic and treatment trials with this agent are eagerly awaited.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Consent</title><p>No written consent has been obtained from the patients as there is no patient identifiable data included in this case report.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meskini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>do Nascimento Pinto</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2019 Novel coronavirus (COVID-19) overview</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Public Health</italic></source><year>2019</year><volume>2020</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10389-020-01258-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arons</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Presymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infections and transmission in a skilled nursing facility</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">New England Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>382</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>p. 2081</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2008457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32329971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical and immunological features of severe and moderate coronavirus disease 2019</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Clinical Investigation</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>130</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2620</fpage><lpage>2629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI137244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32217835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">New England Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>382</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>1708</fpage><lpage>1720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2002032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gautret</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagier</surname><given-names>J.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical and microbiological effect of a combination of hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin in 80 COVID-19 patients with at least a six-day follow up: a pilot observational study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Travel Medicine and Infectious Disease</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.10166310.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gautret</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagier</surname><given-names>J.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID-19: results of an open-label non-randomized clinical trial</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Antimicrobial Agents</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro antiviral activity and projection of optimized dosing design of hydroxychloroquine for the treatment of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2)</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Clinical Infectious Diseases</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>71</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>p. 732</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devaux</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolain</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights on the antiviral effects of chloroquine against coronavirus: what to expect for COVID-19?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Antimicrobial Agents</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>55</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>p. 105938</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pilot study of hydroxychloroquine in treatment of patients with moderate COVID-19</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Zhejiang University (Medical Science)</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3785/j.issn.1008-9292.2020.03.03</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaugerre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Goff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>No evidence of rapid antiviral clearance or clinical benefit with the combination of hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin in patients with severe COVID-19 infection</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">M&#x000e9;decine et Maladies Infectieuses</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>50</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>p. 384</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.medmal.2020.03.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joob</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiwanitkit</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SLE, hydroxychloroquine and no SLE patients with COVID-19: a comment</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>79</volume><issue>6</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2020-217506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of hydroxychloroquine in patients with COVID-19: results of a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">medRxiv</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.22.20040758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breakthrough: chloroquine phosphate has shown apparent efficacy in treatment of COVID-19 associated pneumonia in clinical studies</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BioScience Trends</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>p. 72</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5582/bst.2020.01047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alghamdi</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Algaissi</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic use of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine in COVID-19 and other viral infections: a narrative review</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Travel Medicine and Infectious Disease</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chloroquine for influenza prevention: a randomised, double-blind, placebo controlled trial</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">The Lancet Infectious Diseases</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1473-3099(11)70065-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-80051819215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21550310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gianfrancesco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyrich</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Adely</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics associated with hospitalisation for COVID-19 in people with rheumatic disease: data from the COVID-19 Global Rheumatology Alliance physician-reported registry</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2020-217871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulware</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pullen</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangdiwala</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A randomized trial of hydroxychloroquine as postexposure prophylaxis for covid-19</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">New England Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>383</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>p. 517</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2016638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32492293</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Normal radiograph without evidence of acute intrathoracic process.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIID2020-8822753.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Chest X-ray demonstrating bilateral airspace opacities in the upper lung zones (a). CT chest demonstrating patchy ground-glass opacities (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIID2020-8822753.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Chest X-ray demonstrating bilateral ground-glass opacities, worse in the right upper lung (a). CTA chest demonstrating peripheral, patchy ground-glass infiltrates, and consolidations, more prominent on the left (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIID2020-8822753.003"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Peak markers of inflammation and coagulation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 2</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-dimer (<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibrinogen (mg/dL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">716</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">608</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESR (mm/hr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">571</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>