<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some immunologic factors of the innate and adaptive immune response result typical of RV infection and may contribute to the development of wheezing or asthma. Recent studies have observed that a Th-2-mediated immune response is more frequent after RV infection. Key factors in this immunologic pattern are interleukin (IL)-4, IL-5, IL-10, IL-13, IL-25, IL-33, and thymic stromal lymphopoietin (TSLP). All these mediators are now well known for taking part in the remodeling of the airway’s activation and subsequent wheezing development [
 <xref rid="B39-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Moreover, there are shreds of evidence about the fact that through Th2 cells activation, previous RV infection results are associated with the development of the so-called “indicators of atopy”: eosinophilia and allergen specific IgE [
 <xref rid="B52-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. RV bronchiolitis has been found statistically associated with eosinophilia, especially with a blood eosinophil count &gt;400/mm
 <sup>3</sup> [
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], more frequently than non-RV bronchiolitis [
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Moreover, as mentioned earlier, Amat and colleagues in 2018 found a correlation between co-infected RV + RSV bronchiolitis and the increased risk of sensitization to aeroallergens at three years at multivariate analysis [
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The other peculiar RV-related immunological aspects are represented by the low IFN responses, especially IFN-γ. Low IFN responses in early life increase the likelihood of respiratory illnesses, including those associated with wheezing. Moreover, studies on airway epithelial cells cultured from patients with asthma have observed a diminished production of IFN-β, IFN-γ, and IFN-λ, which facilitates RV replication during infection. Reduced IFN-γ responses in infancy are also observed in “atopic children”, and this fact may contribute to explain why atopy is a risk factor for virus-induced wheezing [
 <xref rid="B52-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Other studies have also identified differences in IFN-λ 1–3 levels in infants with RV or RSV bronchiolitis that may explain different clinical courses [
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-08-01620" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
