<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0025">In a recent general review on the effect of age on the transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in households, schools, and the community, Golstein et al. concluded that there was evidence that susceptibility to infection in children under the age of 10 years was significantly lower compared with adults 
 <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. This conclusion is indeed supported by epidemiological data from many countries. In Iceland, targeted screening of at-risk individuals showed a 6.7% positivity rate in children under 10 years of age compared with 13.7% in those older than 10. In population-based screening without risk factors, the positivity rate was 0% in children under 10 years of age compared with 0.8% in those older than 10 
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Current French epidemiological data are consistent with this. In week 33, the lowest incidence rate (per 100,000 inhabitants) was in the 0–14 age group (8.4), compared with 43.1 in the 15–44 age group, 19.5 in the 45–64 age group, 10.1 in the 65–74 age group, and 11.4 in the 75 and over age group 
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Data from the French GPIP-ACTIV pediatric network showed that the risk of PCR positivity during the epidemic period (March–April 2020) was 3 times higher in adults than in children 
 <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. The UK experience is identical to the one in France. Children under 16 years of age represented 1.1% of proven cases. The rate of positive tests was very low in children compared with adults 
 <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Data from the United States confirmed a low prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 infection in children who were asymptomatic and who were tested by PCR before surgery, clinic visits, or hospital admissions 
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The pooled prevalence of infection was 0.65% (95% CI: 0.47–0.83), but varied from 0 to 2.2% in a linear relationship with the mean weekly incidence of COVID-19 for the entire population of the same geographical area. Prevalence in asymptomatic children remained below 1% as long as the weekly incidence in the general population remained below 70/100,000. It reached 1.5% if this incidence rose to 120/100,000 (asymptomatic pediatric prevalence = 1.07 × weekly incidence [no. per 1000 general population] + 0.23) 
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. In an intrafamily transmissibility study analyzing 105 index patients and 392 home contacts, the secondary attack rate was 2.3% in children aged 0–5 years, 5.4% in those aged 6–17 years, and 17.1% in adults 
 <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. In Greece, the analysis of 23 family clusters showed that the adult was the first identified case in 91.3% of cases. Adult-to-adult transmissions were identified in 12 clusters, and adult-to-child transmissions in 19 clusters. There was no evidence of child-to-child or child-to-adult transmission 
 <xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. In Hunan (China), retrospective analysis of 210 clusters showed that only 8 of 210 clusters (3.5%) were linked to asymptomatic patients. The risk of transmission was increased at home. Susceptibility to infection increased with age. The number of infected contacts from index cases under 20 years of age was very low 
 <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. In a model based on multinational data, the susceptibility to infection in children was estimated to be half that of adults (0.40 [0.25–0.57] in 0–9-year-olds vs. 0.88 [0.70–0.99] in 60–69-year-olds) 
 <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. In the most recent meta-analysis, the average rate of secondary attack at home (10 studies) was 31.0% (95% CI: 19.4–42.7%) for adults and 15.7% (9.9–21.5%) for children under 18 years of age 
 <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>.
</p>
