<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From 1990 to 2019, the annual number of dengue cases showed an increasing trend. Since 2013, the annual number of dengue cases has been more than 2000, with the incidence rate above 0.14/100,000. However, it has been found that the reported cases of dengue fever in China were much lower than many other countries in the world. For example, the World Health Organization reported 187,333 cases of dengue fever in Southeast Asia in 2010, compared with 223 cases (0.12%) in China.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]
 </sup> Besides, the number of cases of dengue fever in China was significantly lower than that in the same latitude of the American countries or Africa areas, where an average of over 100,000 cases were reported per year.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]
 </sup> In this study, we also found that dengue fever cases reported in mainland China reached a peak in 2014, with a total of 46,864 cases (incidence rate: 3.4582/100,000), which mainly contributed by Guangdong Province (45,189 cases, accounting for 96.43%). Cheng et al
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]
 </sup> found that the interaction of climate, intervention, and imported cases was the determining factor for the 2014 dengue epidemic in Guangzhou, Guangdong Province, which contributed 80.2% of dengue cases in mainland China. Li Geng
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]
 </sup> sequenced the envelope (E) gene sequences of 17 viral strains isolated from serum samples from 168 dengue patients in Guangzhou, and found that 6 genotype I were from Thailand, 2 genotype I were from Malaya Peninsula, and 9 genotype I were from Malaysia. Lai et al
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
 </sup> also believes that the increase in the number of reported dengue cases between 1990 and 2014 may be due to changes in diagnostic criteria and case definitions, which introduces more sensitive and rapid laboratory tests. At the same time, we observed that the epidemic season for dengue fever was autumn. This seasonal pattern was different from Latin America, such as Brazil, which was mainly prevalent in summer. Previous studies have found that this is due to the high temperature and heavy rainfall in summer in Brazil, and the different intensity of vector control activities.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]
 </sup> In terms of months, June to December was the main period for dengue outbreaks in mainland China, and reached its peak from September to November. Previous studies have reported that the prevalence of dengue was closely related to temperature.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]
 </sup> When the temperature was between 25°C and 28°C, the risk of dengue transmission was the highest.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]
 </sup> From September to November, the temperature in many provinces in mainland China was still above 18°C, which may was the threshold that mosquitoes cannot transmit the virus. A recent study on the relationship between dengue cases and meteorological factors in Cali, Colombia, also found a strong correlation between dengue cases and the minimum temperature threshold of 18.0°C.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]
 </sup> Similarly, Chuan et al
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]
 </sup> analyzed the cases of dengue fever in Guangzhou from 2006 to 2014 and found that 18.25°C was the threshold between the current month's minimum temperature and the incidence of dengue fever. Sun et al
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]
 </sup> observed that the outbreak of dengue between September and November was due to almost all indigenous cases occurring during this period. In addition, our study shows that the overall trend of Guangdong Province was highly consistent with that of mainland China. Li et al
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]
 </sup> conducted a sensitivity analysis and found that delayed mosquito control, continued importation, the spread of asymptomatic dengue infection, and abnormally high precipitation made Guangdong Province a major contributor to dengue in the mainland Chinese.
</p>
