<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ASF has brought a grievous blow to China, which is the world’s largest pork producer and consumer, with pork production accounting for about 53% of the world’s supply. Further, pork is the main source of high-quality protein for Chinese residents, with the consumption accounting for 62% of total meat consumption [
 <xref rid="B1-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Until 2017, the pig industry in China has been modernizing and expanding, and it is estimated that there will be about 700 million pigs annually. Nevertheless, the first ASF outbreaks in China was declared in Shenbei New Area, Shenyang, Liaoning in August 2018 [
 <xref rid="B11-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Zhou et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] found that ASFV-SY18, the first outbreak strain diagnosed in China, belonged to the genotype II group and shared 100% nucleotide identity with the strains isolated in Georgia, Russia, and Estonia based on the p72 gene fragment, which indicated the close relationship among these viruses. Within a few months after the first ASF outbreak, it quickly swept through most provinces in China. By 24 July 2020, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of the People’s Republic of China (MARA) has reported 178 ASF outbreaks (including four outbreaks in wild boar) in 31 provinces, municipalities and autonomous regions (the ASF outbreaks distribution map in China is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vaccines-08-00531-f002">Figure 2</xref>, The outbreaks were mainly distributed in major economic zones with frequent trade of pig industry, with a trend of increasing southward on the whole. As is shown in 
 <xref rid="vaccines-08-00531-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, the southwest region was the most severely affected with 25.84% (46/178) of outbreaks, followed by the northeast region with 16.85% (30/178) of outbreaks. Among the region Heilongjiang accounted for the largest cumulative number of reported susceptible and dead pigs [
 <xref rid="B17-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. At least 1.2 million pigs have been culled, causing tens of billions of direct economic losses. According to statistics from the National Bureau of statistics of China, in 2019, the number of live pigs and pork production in China were both decreased year on year. Compared with the same period last year, with 544 million live pigs, the number of live pigs dropped 21.6%, and pork production was 42.55 million tons, lower 21.3%. In the first quarter of 2020, affected by the persistent impact of ASF, the number of live pigs in the country was 131.29 million, which was 57.14 million less than the same period last year, dropped 30.3%; and the pork production was 10.38 million tons, which was 4260 million tons less than the same period last year, dropped 29.1% [
 <xref rid="B19-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In 2019, China’s pork export volume was 210,000 tons, a year-on-year decrease of 36.17%, which has tremendous consequences for international trade. In the face of strong and sustained demand, the available pork supply has subsequently declined, leading to a substantial increase in the price of pork sold on the domestic market, from 12.2 yuan per kg (February 2019) to 36.1 yuan per kg in February 2020 [
 <xref rid="B22-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The outbreak of ASF caused a considerable loss of pig capacity in China, and the pig industry has suffered a devastating blow. It is expected that it will be difficult to recover to its previous level within 3–5 years [
 <xref rid="B23-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Due to the concealment and complexity of ASFV transmission, the epidemic situation in China is still not optimistic. 
</p>
