<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">All considered, the possibility that the current epidemic of COVID-19 occurred in humans without the obligatory intervention of an intermediary animal species, appears highly plausible. Study on the genome sequence in COVID-19 found 96.2% identity with a previous SARS-like-CoV, the RaTG13
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Like the RaTg13, the novel coronavirus was able to use ACE2 receptors as cell entry mechanism, confirming that also the new coronavirus had a bat origin
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. According to Andersen et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>, a direct spillover of ancestors of the novel coronavirus might have been possible by acquiring the current genomic features through adaptations during undetected human-to-human transmissions. In fact, all the COVID19 genomes so far sequenced have the same features described above, indicating that they might have originated from a common ancestor
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. If COVID-19 had pre-adapted in another animal species, then there would be a risk of future re-emergence events. In contrast, if the adaptive process had occurred in humans, the repeated zoonotic transfers would be unlikely to take off without the occurrence of the same series of mutations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>: a time interval between different outbreaks would be expected, reflecting the time for the virus to adapt from the reservoir to the human host. It would seem an unlikely option, considering that COVID-19 had already well adapted to human host, with a very successful human-to-human transmission that allows the virus to be maintained within the population. Humans could thus be considered to have become the reservoir of COVID-19, eliminating the need of additional spillover from animal to human to keep the infection going.
</p>
