<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RT-PCR testing was reported to have high specificity but its sensitivity was low, at only 59–70% [
 <xref rid="b11-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="b28-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This means that excluding a suspected case of COVID-19 infection requires multiple negative results. RT-PCR testing is time-consuming and this increases the risk of spread in the population due to the highly contagious nature of COVID-19. CT examination is relatively easy to perform and can thus provide a quick diagnosis. In most COVID-19 confirmed cases, typical CT imaging findings were reported [
 <xref rid="b11-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Typical CT imaging findings were observed in symptomatic patients with negative RT-PCR results [
 <xref rid="b29-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="b30-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Even asymptomatic patients could have positive CT images and these could be the basis for imaging assist in early diagnosis [
 <xref rid="b31-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Jiang et al. reported the CT imaging features of 17 asymptomatic health care workers diagnosed with COVID-19 infection by RT-PCR. The study revealed that all the health care workers had a history of close contact with COVID-19 patients and their CT images were positive for COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="b32-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The lesions in patients receiving treatment reduced in size while those in patients not receiving treatment were enlarged. In a study of 1014 patients, the results showed that 59% had positive RT-PCR results and 88% had positive CT results. The sensitivity of CT in identifying COVID-19 was 97% [
 <xref rid="b28-medscimonit-26-e924582" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], which indicates that CT examination is a reliable, practical, and rapid method in the diagnosis of COVID-19, especially in epidemic areas where the focus is rapid detection with high sensitivity.
</p>
