<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para10">Of the 37 million people estimated to be living with HIV globally, approximately 62% are on life-saving antiretroviral therapy (ART) and 53% are virally suppressed.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Detectable viral load increases HIV-associated morbidity and mortality
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and increases HIV transmission.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> Standard clinic-based delivery of ART, including a growing number of streamlined delivery models for stable patients
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> who have suppressed viral load after 12 months of treatment, have successfully expanded ART coverage globally. However, people with detectable viral load are usually not eligible for streamlined services, such as fast-track ART refills. In the generalised epidemic setting in southern and eastern Africa, where the majority of people living with HIV reside, the overall rate of viral suppression is 54% in South Africa and 64% in Uganda.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Further, men are less likely to be virally suppressed than women.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Client barriers to care, such as missed wages, transport costs, and long waiting times for clinic visits and ART refills, are associated with detectable viral load.
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> These barriers are amplified among men who are less likely to seek care in part due to gender norms and stigma.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Innovations in efficient service delivery—including expanding differentiated services to people with detectable viral load—are needed for people living with HIV, particularly men and people aged younger than 30 years, to achieve the UNAIDS 90-90-90 goal of 73% viral suppression among all people living with HIV.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</p>
