<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para20">
 <boxed-text id="cetextbox10">
  <caption>
   <title>Research in context</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="para30">
   <bold>Evidence before this study</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para40">Although the proportion of people living with HIV who know their status has increased, approaching the UNAIDS goal of 90%, the proportion of people living with HIV who have started lifesaving antiretroviral therapy (ART) and met the gold-standard metric of success, viral suppression, lags behind by about a third, particularly among men. Viral suppression decreases morbidity and mortality for people living with HIV and stops transmission to their partners. Before this study, randomised trials had not tested the effectiveness of community-based ART initiation, monitoring, and resupply; an innovative approach to overcome barriers associated with accessing clinic-based services such as clinic hours and transport costs. Observational evidence suggests that community-based ART could increase ART initiation and viral suppression. A systematic review and meta-analysis from 2019 evaluated the effectiveness of community-based HIV initiatives in achieving the UNAIDS 90-90-90 targets; 90% of people living with HIV knowing their status, 90% of those starting ART, and 90% of those reaching viral suppression. In the meta-analysis, 11 databases were searched to identify community-based interventions for HIV published between 2007 and 2018. 37 studies were identified that evaluated community-based strategies to increase viral suppression. Success was defined as the intervention achieving 73% viral suppression (at the population level). For the outcome of viral suppression, community health workers and peers increased the relative risk of viral suppression by 40% (pooled OR 1·40, 95% CI 1·06–1·86) and the authors encouraged evaluation of community-based delivery of ART. Another study evaluated the effect of starting ART at the clinic and then transferring stable clients to decentralised medication delivery and adherence clubs (a hybrid clinic-community approach) on viral suppression compared with remaining at the clinic. They found no decrease in viral suppression with this clinic-community hybrid approach, showing the effectiveness of community ART refills. Test and treat studies for HIV prevention, which had a poor enrolment of men at 28% in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa, and 29% in Zambia and South Africa, did not show the expected effect on HIV incidence, which might be due in part to not reaching enough men for HIV services. Comprehensive community-based services have the potential to close the gap in ART coverage for different demographics.</p>
  <p id="para50">
   <bold>Added value of this study</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para60">This study presents new evidence from a randomised clinical trial in South Africa and Uganda on the effectiveness of community-based ART initiation, monitoring, and resupply to reach higher viral suppression, particularly among men. We present the intervention costs and a scenario in which the cost could be potentially similar or lower per person who is virally suppressed, compared with the current clinic approach.</p>
  <p id="para70">
   <bold>Implications of all the available evidence</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para80">We showed that community-based initiation and delivery of ART is an effective strategy and could be scaled up to address the gap in viral suppression overall and for men in particular. Although this client-centred approach will require adaptation of services including expanding to new delivery platforms, cost might not be a limiting factor due to the increase in health gains seen with a high proportion of people reaching viral suppression.</p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
