<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0280">We conclude by noting some predictions and expectations:
 <list list-type="simple" id="l0025">
  <list-item id="u0055">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0285">We expect the pattern of further spread of the new Coronavirus (COVID-19) to be dictated mostly by primary in-fall until a high level of person-to-person infectivity might 
    <italic>possibly</italic> be achieved and the virus then acquires the status of an endemic virus.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0060">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0290">Viral contamination of the “environment” in the most general sense explains most of the apparent contagion, e.g., news reports like in 
    <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0065">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0295">Thus, the possibility cannot be ruled out that the 
    <italic>Diamond Princess</italic> cruise ship (and the more recent Westerdam cruiseship) in the South China Sea was contaminated by a fragment of the main COVID-19 dust cloud. Similar inexplicable events appeared to happen for ships at sea during the 1918–1919 Spanish Flu Pandemic (
    <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Hoyle &amp; Wickramasinghe, 1979</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0070">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0300">And, further to this, other drifting COVID-19 smaller dust clouds that have not as yet made land fall may target remote island and other communities, as was also the case during the 1918–1919 Spanish Flu Pandemic (
    <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Hoyle &amp; Wickramasinghe, 1979</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0075">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0305">Given the low mutation rate, the very wide apparent in-fall infectivity pattern (
    <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>) the expectation is this pure viral culture has inoculated millions of Chinese citizens (as well as potentially millions of wild and domestic animals in China) inducing protective adaptive immune responses (Acquired Herd Immunity) on a very large scale.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0080">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0310">Thus, development of a so called “COVID-19 vaccine” which is much in the news at the time of writing would be a waste of public tax-payer funds if mounted on the scale envisaged by governments and national centers for disease control.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0085">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0315">We thus expect the decline of the epidemic (peaking and declining at time of writing) to be driven by this mass natural vaccination process now underway in China. So, the suddenly emerging COVID-19 epidemic, like many similar suddenly emerging human epidemics in the past (SARs, MERs, ZIKAV), is expected to rapidly end by the self-limiting processes of wide spread herd immunity (a pattern likely to be repeated in other countries, 
    <xref rid="s7515" ref-type="sec">Appendix C</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0090">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0320">We thus expect that the incidence of serum antibodies specific for COVID-19 to be wide-spread in the Chinese population in the coming months. So, millions will be potentially immunized for life against future infections with COVID-19.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0095">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0325">How long will COVID-19 remain potentially infective in the physical environment? Clearly for some time—given that over the space of a month or so many cases appeared rapidly, spread by environmental contamination in our view, and not by traditional person-to-person generated aerosols at the height of the donor's infection. This is consistent with those news reports out of China “As the death toll rose to 80, China said, increasing concerns about the potential the virus was infectious even before symptoms were visible rapidity of its spread.” (Heidi Han and Kieran Gair, Associated Press, 
    <italic>The Australian</italic> newspaper January 27, 2020.)
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
