<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Upon arrival to Israel all 11 citizens were retested, and two were found to be positive for SARS-COV-2. One was a 76-year-old male, and the other was a 62-year-old woman who was also positive by viral cultures 4 days after arrival (see 
 <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">xsSupplementary Table S1</xref>). Both were spouses of COVID-19 patients admitted to hospitals in Japan. Therefore, we assume that those two acquired the virus before plane boarding and were infective during flight. Both of them remained asymptomatic after the flight. While on the plane (see sitting scheme on 
 <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), all passengers were instructed to have surgical masks and to replace it every 3 hours for the duration of the flight. Few were using FFP2 masks with unidirectional valve instead. During the 13.5 hours flight, the passengers were allowed to take off masks for eating and drinking. Based on history taken, most of the passengers took off masks during two meals served for ~15 min each. On board, the passengers were moving within the cabin freely, many have kept masks on, and were using the restrooms on the back of the aircraft. Upon arrival to Israel all passengers were put into compulsory isolation for 14 days due to their presence on the Diamond Princess. All passengers that tested negative upon arrival were found to be negative on six consecutive tests during the 14 days of quarantine, even after being in close proximity during the flight with the two positive COVID-19 patients. During the SARS epidemic, there were few reports suggesting transfer of SARS from infected passengers to others during flights.
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> However, a later study
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> suggested a rather low risk of transmission. An additional study from Singapore supported low transmission during flights,
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> which was confirmed in serological and virus spread simulation studies.
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> Those studies led World Health Organization (WHO) to a conclusion that the risk of SARS transmission in airplanes is rather low (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/csr/sars/travel/airtravel/en/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/csr/sars/travel/airtravel/en/</ext-link>).
</p>
