<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, vaccination of pigs with complex ASFV antigen preparations was carried out in order to find an appropriate balance between antibody and cell-mediated ASFV immune response. In 2017, Lopera-Madrid et al., found that vaccination with HEK 293-purified recombinant ASFV proteins (p72, p54, p12) could promote the production of ASFV-specific antibodies, but did not enhance cellular immunity. However, enhanced vaccination with Modified vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA)-vectored antigens (p72, EP153R and CD2v) could complement the former and promote the production of IFN-γ by cellular immunity [
 <xref rid="B104-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. On the basis of DNA vaccines, a strategy of DNA prime and recombinant vaccinia virus (VACV) boost has been proposed in order to orient the encoded antigens to specific antigen presentation pathways to enhance the induction of protective responses, and has also been widely used to screen the immunogenicity and potential protective antigens of ASFV. In 2018, Jancovich et al. identified a subset of ASFV antigens including p30, p72, and D117L that could effectively stimulate humoral and cellular immunity by screening 47 viral genes with this method. However, after the challenge of Georgia 2007/1, despite the viral load in blood and lymphoid tissues of vaccinated pigs decreased significantly, all vaccinated pigs developed acute ASF, and more severe clinical and pathological signs were observed [
 <xref rid="B105-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. On the basis of previous work, researchers proposed recombinant adenoviruses (r Ad) prime and MVA boost as improved delivery systems. In 2019, Netherton et al. screened 12 proteins that could induce ASFV-specific cellular immune response in pigs from ASFV OUR/T33 strain. Accordingly, five ASFV antigens, MGF110-4L, MGF110-5L, M448R, C129R, and I215L were defined as good antibody inducers by r Ad prime and enhanced vaccination with MVA virus encoding the same antigen, further targeting the determinants of ASFV cellular immune response. Although this candidate vaccine could not protect vaccinated pigs from acute ASFV OURT88/1 challenge, some vaccinated pigs showed delayed clinical symptoms and reduced viremia [
 <xref rid="B49-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Similarly, in May 2020, Goatley’s group selected different antigen pools of viral vectors to induce the production of ASFV-specific antibodies and cellular immune responses. In this study an antigen pool consisting of eight ASFV adenoviral vectors, where the ASFV genes B602L, B646L/p72, CP204L/p30, E183L/p54, E199L, EP153R, F317L, and MGF505-5R were embedded, respectively, were used to immunize pigs, and boost with MVA virus encoding the same antigen. Two animal trials were carried out successively, with promising results [
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], in the second animal experiment, 6/6 of pigs were protected from lethal doses of virulent ASFV I strain. In fact, the number of survivors after vaccination with the same antigen pool differed between the two trials, presumably because the immune dose of recombinant viral vectors was increased and an overreaction of the immune system were treated with flunixin meglumine (a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory and antipyretic drug) on day 5 after challenge, compared with experiment 1, which provided 2/6 protection. On the whole, this research achievement is an unprecedented breakthrough since the development of ASFV live-vectored vaccine.
</p>
