<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our vision, the same gene deletion in different strains do not invariably have the identical outcomes, because the effect on the attenuation and protection against ASFV may be strain dependent. In 2020, Chen et al., found that unlike Georgia 2007, the Chinese HLJ/2018 virus (HLJ/18-9GL&amp;UK-del) with a similar deletion of 9GL and UK was attenuated in pigs, but could not provide any protection against homologous virus challenge. The researchers have shown that the molecular basis of the virulence of ASFV may vary among strains, and that the biological changes caused by gene deletion in one ASFV strain may differ in other strains [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In 2017, Monteagudo et al. found that the virulence of BA71ΔCD2 obtained by artificially deleting the CD2v gene of the genotype I ASFV stain BA71 was significantly reduced, and this candidate strain was not only resistant to the homologous parental virulent strain (BA71), but also provided certain cross-protection to heterologous virulent strains (E75, Georgia 2007/1). Ultimately, the induced immune protection was dose-dependent and correlated with the ability of BA71ΔCD2 to induce specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in vitro [
 <xref rid="B80-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Unexpectedly, deletion of the CD2-like gene from the genome of ASFV II Georgia/2010 does not attenuate virulence in swine [
 <xref rid="B81-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. This inconsistency in results may be attributed to a variety of factors, including discrepancy in animal genetics and viral strains, etc., and the diversity of ASFV isolates with different virulence complicates the assignment of ascertaining the determinants of immune protection. Furthermore, for the same strain, when selecting deleted genes, it is uncertain whether deleting more virulence genes simultaneously, and its protective effect, is more ideal. For example, in 2016, O’Donnell’ team further deleted MGF360/505 on the basis of ASFV-Georgia 2007/1-Δ9GL, although the deleted strain was highly attenuated, it had no protective effect on the infection of homologous virulent strains [
 <xref rid="B56-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], and the same problem occurred when Ramirez-Medina et al. simultaneously deleting 9GL, UK, and NL genes of the Georgia/2007 strain [
 <xref rid="B82-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Overall, the related mechanism is still much less explored, and researchers need to optimize deletable gene combinations in further work to fill the gap in the study of related virulence or immune escape genes.
</p>
