<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">The coronavirus epidemic (COVID-19) is the main problem this year that affects all people in the world (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Baud et al., 2020</xref>). This is an infectious disease caused by a newly discovered coronavirus. This virus is a member of related viruses that cause diseases in mammals and birds. In humans, coronaviruses cause respiratory tract infections that can be mild, such as some cases of the common cold (among other possible causes, predominantly rhinoviruses), and others that can be lethal, such as SARS, MERS, and COVID-19. Among them, COVID-19 is an enveloped viruse with a positive-sense single-stranded RNA genome and a nucleocapsid of helical symmetry. The genome size of coronaviruses ranges from approximately 27 to 34 kilobases, the largest among known RNA viruses (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Fehr et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Sexton et al., 2016</xref>). Until now, many scientists have tried to find methods to cure this disease (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Hui David et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). Also, many models have been proposed to consider the growth rate of the transmission risk factor for COVID19 (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Anzai et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Cojocaru et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Kaplan, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Khan &amp; Atangana, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Nishiura et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">2020b</xref>). For example, in (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Khan &amp; Atangana, 2020</xref>), the authors have considered the mathematical modelling and dynamics of the novel corona virus (2019-nCoV). They have described the brief details of interaction among bats and unknown hosts, and then among people and the infection reservoir (seafood market) (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Khan &amp; Atangana, 2020</xref>). In parallel, another group has estimated the risk of transmission of the novel coronavirus (2019-nCov). They have estimated when the effective daily reproduction ratio will fall below 1, and when the epidemic will peak (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020a</xref>). In (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020b</xref>), the authors have adopted a deterministic model to shed light on the transmission dynamics of the novel coronavirus, and assess the impact of public health interventions on infection (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020b</xref>).
</p>
