<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">In another work, the impact of reduced travel on the exportation dynamics of the novel coronavirus infection (COVID-19) has been considered. It has been shown that the decision to control travel volume through restrictions on freedom of movement should be balanced between the resulting estimated epidemiological impact and predicted economic fallout (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Anzai et al., 2020</xref>). In another paper, the authors have estimated the rate of under-ascertainment of the novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) infection. They have done this estimation by using Japanese passenger data on evacuation flights. Assuming that the mean detection window of the virus can be informed by the mean serial interval (estimated at 7.5 days), the ascertainment rate of infection was estimated at 9/100 (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Nishiura et al., 2020</xref>). In another research, it has been argued that given that a vaccine cannot be developed and deployed for at least a year, preventing further transmission relies upon standard principles of containment, two of which are the isolation of known cases and the quarantine of persons believed at high risk of exposure. That article has presented probability models for assessing the effectiveness of case isolation and quarantine within a community during the initial phase of an outbreak with illustrations based on early observations from Wuhan (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Kaplan, 2019</xref>). In other investigation, the authors have discussed controlling infection in predator-prey systems with transmission dynamics. They have illustrated if and when applying such preventive treatments leads to a disease prevalence drop in both populations. They have conducted their study using an optimal control model seeking to minimize the treatment cost(s), subject to the transmission dynamics and predator-prey dynamics (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Cojocaru et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
