<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In developing countries, most pig breeding remains traditional, small-scale, and self-sufficient. Small-scale family farming plays a major role in the introduction, dissemination and colonization of ASF due to its low biosecurity, backward feeding methods and techniques, insufficient understanding of animal health regulations, or even non-compliance with regulations [
 <xref rid="B37-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. At present, pig farming in China is in the transition stage from bulk culture to large-scale farming, with 26 million pig farm households. Although the proportion of large-scale farming is increasing year by year, less than 1% of pig farms have more than 500 sows annually, and the small-scale farming model will still exist for a long time. The first outbreak of ASF in China was detected in domestic pigs in Shenyang [
 <xref rid="B12-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], contact tracing and field investigations found that illegal transportation and a lower biosecurity level played a significant part in the whole transmission process [
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Small and medium-scale farms with low biosecurity levels in China have brought great challenges to ASF epidemic control, created conditions for the breeding and spread of ASF, increased great difficulties and burdens for epidemic prevention personnel to trace the epidemic situation. Fifty-four percent of the reported outbreaks in 2018 were from small- and medium-sized farms, further illustrating the lack of biosecurity control in individual scattered households [
 <xref rid="B19-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The diversification of breeding modes, high feeding density and weak biosafety awareness of practitioners have aggravated the pressure on the prevention and control of ASF in China. Therefore, more attention should be paid to improving animal husbandry and raising biosecurity levels [
 <xref rid="B22-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-vaccines-08-00531" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
