<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the above analysis of the global ASF vaccine research status, the recombinant LAVs developed with the attenuated strain of ASFV virulence gene knockout has the most optimistic prospects as a short/medium-term vaccine candidate in the future. However, before practical application, comprehensive evaluation of the safety risks, including virulence re-enhancement, adverse reactions, and persistent infection of the candidate strains, is needed. In addition, it is necessary to develop a matched diagnosis technology of DIVA, the establishment of ASFV culture passage cell lines, and small animal infection models for vaccine research and production, and, most importantly, basic research on how viruses regulate host responses to infection and the role of virus-encoded proteins in evading host defenses will contribute to developing the next generation of recombinant LAVs. At the same time, ASF subunit vaccines, DNA vaccines, and live virus-vectored vaccines have great research potential with tremendous advantages in safety and DIVA diagnostic technology, but we must consider that although these vaccines can induce strong antigen-specific humoral and cellular immune responses, they can rarely provide complete immune protection against lethal ASFV strains. Undoubtedly, we need to identify more antigens with protective potential and, on this basis, explore the combinations of antigens to induce high levels of immune protection. Moreover, the delivery systems and vaccination strategies need further optimized. Specifically, we must fully understand the structure and function of the main proteins of ASFV, the mechanism of infection and immunity, the recognition of the main immunogens and vaccine targets in order to conduct a more in-depth study of genetically engineered vaccines, and comprehensively evaluate their safety and immune effects in targeted animals. Ultimately, the mechanism of natural hosts against ASFV, including wild boar and warthog, will be helpful to target key factors in the development of ASFV vaccine. In conclusion, there is still a long way to go in the development of the ASFV vaccine.</p>
