<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para180">Participants in the community-based ART delivery group received same-day ART initiation including standardised counselling and the national HIV programmes' first-line efavirenz-based ART regimen. 7 days after ART initiation, participants received a telephone call to ask about symptoms, ART side-effects, and adverse events. After enrolment, participants returned for in-person follow-up visits at month 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 for ART resupply, clinical monitoring, counselling, and ascertainment of adverse events and social harms. Follow-up visits were done at a mobile van parked at a known location and at a scheduled time. ART supply was dispensed for 1 month, 2 months, and then every 3 months thereafter. Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole prophylaxis was dispensed according to country guidelines and tuberculosis preventive therapy (isoniazid) was provided from month 1. Participants received appointments for their mobile visits, with an automated text message reminder the week before their visit. Participants were able to reschedule visits by text message, request additional ART resupply if travelling, and nominate someone else to collect their medication. Participants who missed visits were contacted and their visit rescheduled. The mobile service was regularly available on evenings and weekends. Staff used a mobile phone application for standardised monitoring that included counselling guidelines and required all the steps to be completed before the encounter was closed. For HIV and ART monitoring, participants completed a clinical questionnaire to screen for symptoms of ART adverse events, tuberculosis, and other common opportunistic infections. Point-of-care creatinine testing was done to monitor renal function. HIV plasma viral load was assessed for treatment success at month 6. Text messages were sent with viral load results without mentioning HIV to protect confidentiality regarding their HIV infection and next steps according to whether they had detectable or undetectable viral load (eg, “All is going well. Keep up the good work.” or “Please contact us for more information.”). Participants received individualised adherence support. Participants who required additional clinical services were referred for care and followed up until they were linked to a clinic. Participants in the community-based ART delivery group were administratively linked to the clinic and their files kept up to date.</p>
