<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All the subtypes of coronaviruses (CoV) come under the Coronaviridae family. They are pleomorphic RNA viruses which contain crown-shaped protein subunits with a size of 80–160 nm and polarity of 27–32 kb. Due to the enormous rate of recombination of coronavirus which in turn because of various transcription anomalies and changes in RNA dependent RNA polymerase enzyme, the mutation in CoV is higher.[
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] From November–December 2019, severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS-CoV-2) caused atypical pneumonia in a few cases which had a possible origin in the wet markets in the city of Wuhan, China.[
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Later on, when the spread increased many folds which resulted in the World Health Organization (WHO) acknowledging this coronavirus as a public health emergency of international interest (PHEIC).[
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] It was found out that CoV was structurally related to the SARS virus which caused severe respiratory distress. Earlier epidemics, that is, SARS and the Middle-East respiratory syndrome (MERS) caused havoc and had caused a lot of fatalities as well as problems for the medical fraternity.[
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Since coronavirus has been stated as a PHEIC, it will prioritize the disease in all the countries wherein global effort will be put into place to halt this outbreak.[
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] CoV has spread quickly throughout East Asia as well as Europe amidst strict lockdowns and quarantine.[
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] As of April 25
 <sup>th</sup>, 2020, according to WHO, almost 210 countries are affected, with close to 29 lakh people suffering from this viral disease and with 200,568 deaths, thus a pandemic has been declared with the United States of America being the current hotspot for this outbreak where more than 9 lakh people are CoV positive and there is around 52,000 deaths reported [
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>].
</p>
