<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">Considering the burden COVID-19 is already placing on our healthcare system and Emergency Departments (EDs), the compounding cumbersome additions of Influenza-Like-Illness (ILI) can further devastate the healthcare system, especially our healthcare workers. In a study by D'Amore et al. many patients seek care for ILI in the ED, as seen earlier this year with a sharp increase in ED visits at the start of the pandemic in the US [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This study showed one in four providers suffering from ILI after caring for over 1000 influenza-positive patients [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The high transmission ratio of influenza therefore puts others, particularly healthcare workers, at risk for contracting the virus. This highlights the importance of implementing proactive measures in order to spare and protect already limited personnel and diagnostic resources. Emergency and critical care departments, in preparation for the impending influx of additional COVID-19/ILI illnesses, are able to utilized the Center for Disease Control and Prevention's Pandemic Influenza Triage Tool in order to safely process patients presenting with signs and symptoms of an ILI [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Other measures EDs are taking include limiting patient inflow by triaging through telemedicine/online platforms prior to patient arrival and identifying patients coming in with respiratory symptoms so that proper precautions can be followed [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. One of the most effective measures is the use of vaccination [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Influenza vaccination is underutilized in the US, with most age groups having &lt; 50% utilization. Influenza vaccines are cost-effective and substantially reduce the severity and number of patients developing influenza and influenza like illnesses. Mass influenza vaccination should occur prior to the peak of the seasonal epidemic. Due to the high transmissibility of influenza, it is important to protect those who have weakened or developing immune systems. Without a current COVID-19 vaccine, routes to decrease co-infection must rely heavily on influenza prevention through vaccination. Aside from vaccination, the maintenance and enforcement of the current non-pharmacological interventions (NPI) including social distancing and proper hygiene are essential tools for combating the upcoming intersection of influenza and COVID-19.
</p>
