<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0005">In Canada, new HCV infections occur mainly among people who inject drugs (PWID) (N. Z. 
 <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Janjua, Yu, et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, syndemic conditions of co-occurring mental illness, HIV co-infection and higher material deprivation are more common among people living with HCV (PLHCV) compared to HCV-negative individuals (
 <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">McKee et al., 2018</xref>), prompting a need to examine data by HCV status. In British Columbia (BC), an estimated 1.2 to 1.5% of the population injects drugs and more than 65% of those will have a lifetime exposure to HCV (
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Jacka et al., 2020</xref>; N. Z. 
 <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Janjua et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Public Health Agency of Canada, 2014</xref>). Increasing rates of injecting drug use have been observed in Canada and the US since 2010, likely exacerbated by policies to reduce prescription opioid overprescribing, diversion and misuse (
 <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Powell et al., 2019</xref>). Other policies (e.g. prescription drug monitoring programs, more stringent guidelines) have also been implicated (
 <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Martins et al., 2019</xref>). A national US study observed a 76% increase in drug treatment admissions (from 13% to 22%) due to injecting drug use between 2004 and 2014; these increases were particularly pronounced among individuals 20 to 39 years of age (
 <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Zibbell et al., 2018</xref>). Acute HCV infections subsequently tripled in the US between 2011 and 2015 (
 <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez &amp; Trotter, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Zibbell et al., 2018</xref>), representing a reversal in progress towards reducing rates of acute HCV in the US, which declined by almost 50% between 2001 and 2010. Similarly, HCV incidence in BC decreased between 2001 and 2012 and then began rising thereafter (
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Li Y et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
